{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 1.1.1}", "question": "If $a, b$ are relatively prime, then we can find integers $x, y$ such that $ax+by=1$", "solution": "We write $a=bq+r$ by the Euclidean algorithm, and since $a, b$ are relatively prime we know $r\\ne0$ so $0<r<|b|$. We see that $b,r$ are relatively prime, or their common factor would have to divide $a$ as well. So, $b=rq_{1}+r_{1}$ with $0<r_{1}<|r|$. We can then write $r=r_{1}q_{2}+r_{2}$ and continuing in this fashion, we will eventually arrive at $r_{k}=1$ for some $k$. Working backward, we see that $1=ax+by$ for some $x, y\\in\\mathbb{Z}.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 1.1.2}", "question": "Every positive integer greater than 1 has a prime divisor.", "solution": "Suppose that there is a positive integer having no prime divisors. Since the set of positive integers with no prime divisors is nonempty, there is a least positive integer $n$ with no prime divisors. Since $n$ divides itself, $n$ is not prime. Hence we can write $n=ab$ with $1<a<n$ and $1<b<n.$ Since $a<n$, $a$ must have a prime divisor. But any divisor of $a$ is also a divisor of $n$, so $n$ must have a prime divisor. This is a contradiction. Therefore every positive integer has at least one prime divisor.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 1.1.3}", "question": "There are infinitely many primes.", "solution": "Suppose that there are only finitely many primes, that is, suppose that there is no prime greater than $n$ where $n$ is an integer. Consider the integer $a=n!+1$ where $n\\ge1$. By Theorem 1.1.2, $a$ has at least one prime divisor, which we denote by $p$. If $p\\le n$, then $p|n!$ and $p|(a-n!)=1$. This is impossible. Hence $p>n$. Therefore we can see that there is a prime greater than $n$ for every positive integer $n$. Hence there are infinitely many primes.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 1.1.4}", "question": "If $p$ is prime and $p|ab$, then $p|a$ or $p|b$.", "solution": "Suppose that $p$ is prime and $p|ab$ where $a$ and $b$ are integers. If $p$ does not divide $a$, then $a$ and $p$ are coprime. Then $\\exists x, y\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ such that $ax+py=1$. Then we have $abx+pby=b$ and $pby=b-abx$. Hence $p|b-abx$. Thus $p|b$. Similarly, if $p$ does not divide $b$, we see that $p|a.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 1.1.5}", "question": "$\\mathbb{Z}$ has unique factorization.", "solution": "Existence. Suppose that there is an integer greater than 1 which cannot be written as a product of primes. Then there exists a least integer $m$ with such a property. Since $m$ is not a prime, $m$ has a positive divisor $d$ such that $m=de$ where $e$ is an integer and $1<d<m$, $1<e<m.$ Since $m$ is the least integer which cannot be written as a product of primes, we can write $d$ and $e$ as products of primes such that $d=p_{1}p_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{r}$ and $e=q_{1}q_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot q_{s}$. Hence $m=de=p_{1}p_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{r}\\cdot q_{1}q_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot q_{s}$. This contradicts our assumption about $m$. Hence all integers can be written as products of primes.\n\nUniqueness. Suppose that an integer $a$ is written as\n\n$a=p_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{r}=q_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot q_{s}$\n\nwhere $p_{i}$ and $q_{j}$ are primes for $1\\le i\\le r,$ $1\\le j\\le s$. Then $p_{1}|q_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot q_{s},$ so there exists $q_{j}$ such that $p_{1}|q_{j}$ for some $j$. Without loss of generality, we can let $q_{j}$ be $q_{1}$. Since $p_{1}$ is a prime, we see that $p_{1}=q_{1}$. Dividing $p_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{r}=q_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot q_{s}$ by $p_{1}=q_{1}$, we have $p_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{r}=q_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot q_{s}.$ Similarly there exists $q_{j}$ such that $p_{2}|q_{j}$ for some $j$. Let $q_{j}$ be $q_{2}$. Then $q_{2}=p_{2}$. Hence there exist $q_{1},...,q_{r}$ such that $p_{i}=q_{j}$ for $1\\le i\\le r$ and $r\\le s$. If $r<s$, then we see that $1=q_{r+1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot q_{s}$. This is impossible. Hence $r=s.$ Therefore the factorization is unique.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Example 1.1.6}", "question": "Show that $S=1+\\frac{1}{2}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\frac{1}{n}$ is not an integer for $n>1$.", "solution": "Let $k\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ be the highest power of 2 less than $n$, so that $2^{k}\\le n<2^{k+1}$. Let $m$ be the least common multiple of $1,2,...,n$ excepting $2^{k}$. Then $mS=m+\\frac{m}{2}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\frac{m}{n}$. Each of the numbers on the right-hand side of this equation are integers, except for $m/2^{k}$. If $m/2^{k}$ were an integer, then $2^{k}$ would have to divide the least common multiple of the number $1,2,...,2^{k}-1,2^{k}+1,...,n$ which it does not. So $mS$ is not an integer, which implies that $S$ cannot be an integer.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.7}", "question": "Show that $1+\\frac{1}{3}+\\frac{1}{5}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\frac{1}{2n-1}$ is not an integer for $n>1$.", "solution": "Let $S =1+ \\frac{1}{3} + \\frac{1}{5} + \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot + \\frac{1}{2n-1}$. We can find an integer $k$ such that $3^k \\le 2n - 1 < 3^{k+1}$. Define $m$ to be the least common multiple of all the numbers $3, 5,... , 2n - 1$ except for $3^k$. Then $mS = m +\\frac{m}{3} +\\frac{m}{5} + \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot +\\frac{m}{2n - 1}$. Each of the numbers on the right side of this equation is an integer, except for $m/3^k$. If $m/3^k$ were an integer, then there would be some integer $b$ such that $m = 3^kb$, but $3^k$ does not divide $3, 5,... , 3^k - 2, 3^k + 2,... , 2n - 1$ so it cannot divide their least common multiple. Therefore $mS$ is not an integer, and clearly neither is $S$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.8}", "question": "Let $a_{1},...,a_{n}$ for $n\\ge2$ be nonzero integers. Suppose there is a prime $p$ and positive integer $h$ such that $p^{h}|a_{i}$ for some $i$ and $p^{h}$ does not divide $a_{j}$ for all $j\\ne i.$ Then show that $S=\\frac{1}{a_{1}}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\frac{1}{a_{n}}$ is not an integer.", "solution": "Let $h$ be the maximum power of $p$ dividing $a_i$. We use the notation $p^h \\| a_i$ to mean that $p^h | a_i$ but $p^{h+1} \\nmid a_i$. Let $m$ be the least common multiple of $a_1,... ,a_{i-1}, a_i/p^h, a_{i+1},... ,a_n$. Then $mS = \\frac{m}{a_1} + \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot + \\frac{m}{a_{i-1}} + \\frac{m}{a_i} + \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot + \\frac{m}{a_n}$. We see that $m/a_j$ is an integer for $j = 1, 2,... ,i - 1, i + 1,... ,n$. However, $a_i$ does not divide $m$, since if it did then $p^h$ would clearly have to divide $m$, which means we can find a $b \\in \\mathbb{Z}$ such that $m = p^hb$. Since $p^h$ does not divide $a_j$ for $j = 1,... ,i - 1, i + 1,... ,n$, it does not divide their least common multiple. Hence $m/a_i$ is not an integer, which implies that $mS$ is not an integer. Therefore $S = \\frac{1}{a_1} + \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot + \\frac{1}{a_n}$ is not an integer.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.9}", "question": "Prove that if $n$ is a composite integer, then $n$ has a prime factor not exceeding $\\sqrt{n}$", "solution": "Since $n$ is composite, we can write $n = ab$ where $a$ and $b$ are integers with $1 < a \\le b<n$. We have $a \\le \\sqrt{n}$ since otherwise $\\sqrt{n}<a \\le b$ and $ab > \\sqrt{n}\\sqrt{n} = n$. Now, $a$ certainly has a prime divisor, and any prime divisor of $a$ is also a prime divisor of $n$. Hence $n$ has a prime factor which is less than or equal to $\\sqrt{n}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.10}", "question": "Show that if the smallest prime factor $p$ of the positive integer $n$ exceeds $\\sqrt[3]{n}$, then $n/p$ must be prime or 1.", "solution": "Suppose that the smallest prime factor $p$ of the positive integer $n$ exceeds $\\sqrt[3]{n}$. Then $p>n^{1/3}$. Hence $n/p < n^{2/3}$. If $n/p$ is composite, $n/p$ has a prime factor not exceeding $\\sqrt{n/p}$ by Exercise 1.1.9. We see that $\\sqrt{n/p} < n^{1/3}$. A prime factor of $n/p$ is also that of $n$, and so we have found a prime factor which is smaller than $n^{1/3}$, which contradicts our assumption. Therefore $n/p$ is a prime or 1.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.11}", "question": "Let $p$ be prime. Show that each of the binomial coefficients $\\binom{p}{k}$, $1\\le k\\le p-1$, is divisible by $p$.", "solution": "Since $\\binom{p}{k}= \\frac{p!}{k! (p - k)!}$ we see that the numerator is divisible by $p$, and the denominator is not, for $1 \\le k \\le p - 1$. The result is now evident.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.12}", "question": "Prove that if $p$ is an odd prime, then $2^{p-1}\\equiv1$ (mod $p$).", "solution": "$2^p = (1 + 1)^p = 1+ \\sum_{k=1}^{p-1}\\binom{p}{k} + 1 \\equiv 1 + 1 \\pmod p$ by the previous exercise.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.13}", "question": "Prove Fermat's little Theorem: If $a, p\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ with $p$ a prime, and $p\\nmid a$, prove that $a^{p-1}\\equiv1$ (mod $p$).", "solution": "We can apply induction. For instance, $3^p = (1 + 2)^p = 1+ \\sum_{k=1}^{p-1}\\binom{p}{k}2^k + 2^p \\equiv 1+2^p \\pmod p$ since the binomial coefficients are divisible by $p$. By the previous exercise $2^p \\equiv 2 \\pmod p$ and so we find that $3^p \\equiv 3 \\pmod p$.\n\nAlternate Solution. We consider the field $\\mathbb{Z}/p\\mathbb{Z}$, obtained by taking congruences mod $p$. Let $\\bar{a}$ denote the class of $a \\pmod p$. If $p \\nmid a$, then $\\bar{a} \\not\\equiv 0 \\pmod p$, and so $\\bar{a}$ is a unit in the field $\\mathbb{Z}/p\\mathbb{Z}$. The units of this field form a multiplicative group $G$ of order $p - 1$. By elementary group theory, $\\bar{a}^{|G|} = \\bar{a}^{p-1} = 1$, which means that $a^{p-1} \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 1.1.14}", "question": "Given $a, n\\in\\mathbb{Z}$, $a^{\\phi(n)}\\equiv1$ (mod $n$) when $gcd(a,n)=1.$ This is a theorem due to Euler.", "solution": "The case where $n$ is prime is clearly a special case of Fermat's little Theorem. The argument is basically the same as that of the alternate solution to Exercise 1.1.13. Consider the ring $\\mathbb{Z}/n\\mathbb{Z}$. If $a, n$ are coprime, then $\\overline{a}$ is a unit in this ring. The units form a multiplicative group of order $\\phi(n)$, and so clearly $\\overline{a}^{\\phi(n)}=\\overline{1}$ Thus, $a^{\\phi(n)}\\equiv1$ (mod $n$).", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.15}", "question": "Show that $n|\\phi(a^{n}-1)$ for any $a>n$.", "solution": "$a^n \\equiv 1 \\pmod{a^n - 1}$ and $n$ is the smallest power of $a$ with this property. Thus, $a$ has order $n \\pmod{a^n - 1}$. Therefore, $n | \\phi(a^n - 1)$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.16}", "question": "Show that $n\\nmid 2^{n}-1$ for any natural number $n>1$.", "solution": "Let us suppose the set of $n > 1$ such that $2^n \\equiv 1 \\pmod n$ is nonempty. By the well-ordering principle, there is a least such number, call it $n_0$. Then $2^{n_0} \\equiv 1 \\pmod{n_0}$. By Euler's theorem, $2^{\\phi(n_0)} \\equiv 1 \\pmod{n_0}$. Let $d = (n_0, \\phi(n_0))$. By the Euclidean algorithm, we can find integers $x$ and $y$ so that $n_0x + \\phi(n_0)y = d$. Thus, $2^d \\equiv 1 \\pmod{n_0}$. If $d > 1$, this gives $2^d \\equiv 1 \\pmod d$ contradicting the minimality of $n_0$. Thus, $d = 1$ and we get $2 \\equiv 1 \\pmod{n_0}$ which is also a contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.17}", "question": "Show that $\\frac{\\phi(n)}{n}=\\prod_{p|n}(1-\\frac{1}{p})$ by interpreting the left-hand side as the probability that a random number chosen from $1\\le a\\le n$ is coprime to $n$.", "solution": "The probability that a number chosen from $1 \\le a \\le n$ is coprime to $n$ is clearly $\\phi(n)/n$. On the other hand, this is tantamount to insisting that our number is not divisible by any prime divisors of $n$, which is represented by the right-hand side of the formula.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.18}", "question": "Show that $\\phi$ is multiplicative (i.e., $\\phi(mn)=\\phi(m)\\phi(n)$ when $gcd(m,n)=1$) and $\\phi(p^{\\alpha})=p^{\\alpha-1}(p-1)$ for $p$ prime.", "solution": "By the previous exercise, it is clear that $\\phi$ is multiplicative. When $n = p^\\alpha$, we find $\\phi(p^\\alpha) = p^\\alpha(1 - \\frac{1}{p}) = p^{\\alpha-1}(p - 1)$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.19}", "question": "Find the last two digits of $3^{1000}$.", "solution": "We find the residue class that $3^{1000}$ belongs to in $\\mathbb{Z}/100\\mathbb{Z}$. This is the same as finding the last two digits. By Euler's theorem, $3^{40} \\equiv 1 \\pmod{100}$, since $\\phi(100) = \\phi(4)\\phi(25) = 2(20) = 40$. Therefore, $3^{1000} = (3^{40})^{25} \\equiv 1 \\pmod{100}$. The last two digits are 01.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.20}", "question": "Find the last two digits of $2^{1000}$.", "solution": "We need to find the residue class of $2^{1000}$ in $\\mathbb{Z}/100\\mathbb{Z}$. Since 2 is not coprime to 100, we cannot apply Euler's theorem as in the previous exercise. However, we have $x = 2^{1000} \\equiv 1 \\pmod{25}$, $x = 2^{1000} \\equiv 0 \\pmod 4$. We determine which residue classes $z \\pmod{100}$ satisfy $z \\equiv 1 \\pmod{25}$ and $z \\equiv 0 \\pmod 4$. The last condition means $z = 4k$. We solve $4k \\equiv 1 \\pmod{25}$. Thus, $6(4k) \\equiv 6 \\pmod{25}$ so that $k \\equiv -6 \\pmod{25}$. That is, $k \\equiv 19 \\pmod{25}$. Hence, $z = (19)4 = 76$. This means $2^{1000} \\equiv 76 \\pmod{100}$. The last two digits are 76.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.21}", "question": "Let $p_{k}$ denote the kth prime. Prove that $p_{k+1}\\le p_{1}p_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{k}+1$", "solution": "We see that the number $p_1p_2 \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_k+1$ is coprime to $p_1, p_2,... ,p_k$ and either must be prime, or divisible by a prime different from $p_1,... ,p_k$. Thus, $p_{k+1} \\le p_1p_2 \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_k + 1$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.22}", "question": "Show that $p_{k}<2^{2^{k}}$ where $p_{k}$ denotes the kth prime.", "solution": "From the preceding exercise, we know that $p_{k+1} \\le p_1 \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_k + 1$. Now we have $p_1 < 2^{2^1}$ and $p_2 < 2^{2^2}$. Suppose that $p_k < 2^{2^k}$ is true for $2 < k \\le n$. Then $p_{n+1} \\le p_1p_2 \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_n + 1 < 2^{2^1}2^{2^2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot 2^{2^n}+ 1 = 2^{2^{n+1}-2} + 1 < 2^{2^{n+1}}$. Hence $p_n < 2^{2^n}$ is true for $n \\ge 1$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.23}", "question": "Prove that $\\pi(x)\\ge log(log~x)$.", "solution": "From the previous exercise, we have that $p_n < 2^{2^n}$ for $n \\ge 1$. Hence we can see that $\\pi(2^{2^n}) \\ge n$. For $x > 2$, choose an integer $n$ so that $e^{e^{n-1}} < x \\le e^{e^n}$. Then $\\log x \\le e^n \\log e = e^n$ and $\\log(\\log x) \\le n \\log e = n$. If $n > 2$, then $e^{e^{n-1}} > 2^{2^n}$. $\\pi(x) \\ge \\pi(e^{e^{n-1}}) \\ge \\pi(e^{2^n}) \\ge \\pi(2^{2^n}) \\ge n \\ge \\log(\\log x)$. This proves the result.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.24}", "question": "By observing that any natural number can be written as $sr^{2}$ with s squarefree, show that $\\sqrt{x}\\le2^{\\pi(x)}$. Deduce that $\\pi(x)\\ge\\frac{log~x}{2~log~2}.$", "solution": "For any set of primes $S$ define $f_S(x)$ to be the number of integers $n$ such that $1 \\le n \\le x$ with $\\gamma(n) \\subset S$ where $\\gamma(n)$ is the set of primes dividing $n$. Suppose that $S$ is a finite set with $t$ elements. Write such an $n$ in the form $n = r^2s$ with $s$ squarefree. Since $1 \\le r^2s \\le x$, we see that $r \\le \\sqrt{x}$ and there are at most $2^t$ choices for $s$ corresponding to the various subsets of $S$ since $s$ is squarefree. Thus $f_S(x) \\le 2^t\\sqrt{x}$. Put $\\pi(x) = m$ so that $p_{m+1} > x$. If $S = \\{p_1,... ,p_m\\}$, then $f_S(x) = x$. Then $x \\le 2^m\\sqrt{x} = 2^{\\pi(x)}\\sqrt{x}$. Thus $\\sqrt{x} \\le 2^{\\pi(x)}$ and hence $\\frac{1}{2} \\log x \\le \\pi(x) \\log 2$, or equivalently, $\\pi(x) \\ge \\frac{\\log x}{2 \\log 2}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.25(i)}", "question": "Let $\\psi(x)=\\sum_{p^{\\alpha}\\le x}log~p$ where the summation is over prime powers $p^{\\alpha}\\le x$. (i) For $0\\le x\\le1$, show that $x(1-x)\\le\\frac{1}{4}$ Deduce that $\\int_{0}^{1}x^{n}(1-x)^{n}dx\\le\\frac{1}{4^{n}}$ for every natural number n.", "solution": "Clearly $4x^2 - 4x + 1 = (2x - 1)^2 \\ge 0$ so (i) is now immediate.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.25(ii)}", "question": "Let $\\psi(x)=\\sum_{p^{\\alpha}\\le x}log~p$ where the summation is over prime powers $p^{\\alpha}\\le x$. (ii) Show that $e^{\\psi(2n+1)}\\int_{0}^{1}x^{n}(1-x)^{n}dx$ is a positive integer. Deduce that $\\psi(2n+1)\\ge2n~log~2$.", "solution": "The integral $\\int_{0}^{1} x^n(1 - x)^n dx$ consists of a sum of rational numbers whose denominators are less than $2n + 1$. Since $lcm(1, 2,... , 2n + 1) = e^{\\psi(2n+1)}$, we find $e^{\\psi(2n+1)} \\int_{0}^{1}x^n(1 - x)^n dx$ is a positive integer. Thus, $e^{\\psi(2n+1)} \\ge 2^{2n}$. This proves (ii).", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.25(iii)}", "question": "Let $\\psi(x)=\\sum_{p^{\\alpha}\\le x}log~p$ where the summation is over prime powers $p^{\\alpha}\\le x$. (iii) Prove that $\\psi(x)\\ge\\frac{1}{2}x~log~2$ for $x\\ge6$ Deduce that $\\pi(x)\\ge\\frac{x~log~2}{2~log~x}$ for $x\\ge6$", "solution": "For (iii), choose $n$ so that $2n - 1 \\le x < 2n + 1$. Then, by (ii), $\\psi(x) \\ge \\psi(2n - 1) \\ge (2n - 2) \\log 2 > (x - 3) \\log 2$. For $x \\ge 6$, $x - 3 > x/2$ so that $\\psi(x) > x \\log 2/2$. Since $\\psi(x) \\le \\pi(x) \\log x$, we deduce that $\\pi(x) \\ge\\frac{x \\log 2}{2 \\log x}$ for $x \\ge 6$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.1.26}", "question": "By observing that $\\prod_{n<p\\le2n}p|\\binom{2n}{n}$ show that $\\pi(x)\\le\\frac{9x~log~2}{log~x}$ for every integer $x\\ge2$", "solution": "Since $\\prod_{n<p\\le2n} p \\le \\binom{2n}{n}$, we deduce that $\\sum_{n<p\\le2n} \\log p \\le 2n \\log 2$ because $\\binom{2n}{n} \\le 2^{2n}$. Therefore $\\theta(2n) - \\theta(n) \\le 2n \\log 2$, where $\\theta(n) = \\sum_{p\\le n} \\log p$. An easy induction shows that $\\theta(2^r) \\le 2^{r+1} \\log 2$ for every positive integer $r$. Given an integer $x \\ge 2$, determine $r$ so that $2^r \\le x < 2^{r+1}$. Then $\\theta(x) \\le \\theta(2^{r+1}) \\le 2^{r+2} \\log 2 \\le 4x \\log 2$. We deduce, in particular, $\\sum_{\\sqrt{x}<p\\le x} \\log p \\le 4x \\log 2$, so that $(\\frac{1}{2} \\log x) (\\pi(x) - \\pi(\\sqrt{x})) \\le 4x \\log 2$. This means $\\pi(x) - \\pi(\\sqrt{x}) \\le\\frac{8x \\log 2}{\\log x}$ and $\\pi(x) \\le\\frac{8x \\log 2}{\\log x}+ \\sqrt{x} \\le\\frac{9x \\log 2}{\\log x}$ because $\\sqrt{x} \\le\\frac{x \\log 2}{\\log x}$ for $x \\ge 10$, as is easily checked by examining the graph of $f(x) = \\sqrt{x} \\log 2 - \\log x$. For $x \\le 10$, the inequality is verified directly.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.2.1}", "question": "Suppose that $a, b, c\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ If $ab=c^{2}$ and $(a,b)=1$, then show that $a=d^{2}$ and $b=e^{2}$ for some $d, e\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ More generally, if $ab=c^{g}$ then $a=d^{g}$ and $b=e^{g}$ for some $d, e\\in\\mathbb{Z}.$", "solution": "Write $a = p_1^{\\alpha_1} p_2^{\\alpha_2} \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_r^{\\alpha_r}$ and $b = q_1^{\\beta_1} q_2^{\\beta_2} \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot q_s^{\\beta_s}$ where $p_i$ and $q_j$ are primes for $1 \\le i \\le r$ and $1 \\le j \\le s$ and $p_i \\ne q_j$ for any $i, j$ since $(a, b) = 1$. $ab = (p_1^{\\alpha_1} \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_r^{\\alpha_r})(q_1^{\\beta_1} \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot q_s^{\\beta_s}) = c^2 = p_1^{2\\gamma_1} \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_r^{2\\gamma_r} \\cdot q_1^{2\\theta_1} \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot q_s^{2\\theta_s}$, where $c = p_1^{\\gamma_1} \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_r^{\\gamma_r} q_1^{\\theta_1} \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot q_s^{\\theta_s}$. By unique factorization, $\\alpha_i = 2\\gamma_i$ and $\\beta_j = 2\\theta_j$ for $1 \\le i \\le r$ and $1 \\le j \\le s$. Hence we can write $a = p_1^{2\\gamma_1} \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_r^{2\\gamma_r}$ and $b = q_1^{2\\theta_1} \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot q_s^{2\\theta_s}$, which shows that $a$ and $b$ are squares. The general case is proved similarly.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.2.4}", "question": "Show that $x^{4}-y^{4}=z^{2}$ has no nontrivial solution.", "solution": "Suppose that $x^4 - y^4 = (x^2 + y^2)(x^2 - y^2) = z^2$ has a nontrivial solution, and choose the solution such that $|x|$ is minimal. If $x$ is even, then both $y$ and $z$ must be odd (since $x, y, z$ are coprime). But then we can rewrite the equation as $(x^2)^2 = z^2 + (y^2)^2$ and we know from Exercise 1.2.2 that this equation has no solutions for $x$ even. So $x$ is odd. Suppose that $y$ is odd. We again write the equation as $(x^2)^2 = z^2+(y^2)^2$, and we see that by Exercise 1.2.2 we can write $z = 2ab, y^2 = a^2 - b^2, x^2 = a^2 + b^2$, for relatively prime integers $a, b$. Now, $a^4 - b^4 = (a^2 + b^2)(a^2 - b^2) = x^2y^2 = (xy)^2$, and we have found another solution to the equation $x^4 - y^4 = z^2$. But $a < \\sqrt{a^2 + b^2} = x$, contradicting our assumption about $x$. We conclude that there are no solutions for $y$ odd. Now suppose that $y$ is even. Then we can use Exercise 1.2.2 and write $y^2 = 2cd, z = c^2 - d^2, x^2 = c^2 + d^2$, where $c, d$ are coprime and of opposite parity. Without loss, we assume that $c$ is even, $d$ odd. But then we have $(2c, d) = 1$, and we can use Exercise 1.2.1 which says that we can find integers $s, t$ such that $2c = s^2, d = t^2$. In fact, $s$ is even so we can write $s = 2u$, and thus $c = 2u^2$. Therefore we can write $x^2 = c^2+d^2 = (2u^2)^2+ (t^2)^2$. We now deduce that we can find integers $v, w$ such that $2u^2 = 2vw, t^2 = v^2 - w^2, x = v^2 + w^2$. Since $u^2 = vw$, we can write $v = x_1^2$ and $w = y_1^2$ with $x_1$ and $y_1$ coprime. This gives $t^2 = x_1^4 - y_1^4$, which is a solution with $x_1 < v < x$, again a contradiction. Thus there are no nontrivial solutions.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.2.5}", "question": "Prove that if $f(x)\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x]$, then $f(x)\\equiv0$ (mod p) is solvable for infinitely many primes p.", "solution": "Let $f(x) = a_nx^n + \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot + a_0$. If $a_0 = 0$, then $p | f(p)$ for all $p$, so $f(x) \\equiv 0 \\pmod p$ is solvable for all $p$. So assume $a_0 \\ne 0$. Let $p_1,... ,p_k$ be a finite set of primes such that $f(x) \\equiv 0 \\pmod{p_i}$ is solvable. Let $m = p_1 \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_k a_0 y$. Then $f(m) = a_nm^n + \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot + a_0 = a_0(a_n \\frac{m^n}{a_0} + \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot + 1)$. Let $g(x) = a_n a_0^{n-1}x^n + a_{n-1} a_0^{n-2}x^{n-1} + \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot + a_1x + 1$. Then we can see that $(p_i, g(m)) = 1$ for $1 \\le i \\le k$. Hence $g(m)$ has a prime divisor different from $p_i$ for $1 \\le i \\le k$. The prime divisor of $g(m)$ is also that of $f(a_0m)$. Hence we can see that there is a new prime divisor of $f$ different from $p_i$ for $1 \\le i \\le k$. This is a contradiction. Therefore $f$ has infinitely many prime divisors.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.2.6}", "question": "Let q be prime. Show that there are infinitely many primes p so that $p\\equiv1$ (mod q).", "solution": "Let us consider the polynomial $f(x) = \\frac{x^q - 1}{x - 1} =1+ x + \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot + x^{q-1}$, and suppose that $p$ is a prime divisor of $f(x)$. Then $x^q \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$ for some $x$. Let $x_0$ be an integer such that $f(x_0) \\equiv 0 \\pmod p$. Then $x_0^q \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$. If $x_0$ is not congruent to 1 (mod $p$), then $q$ is the order of $x_0 \\pmod p$ since $q$ is a prime. Consider the multiplicative group $G = \\{1,... , p - 1\\}$. We see that $x_0 \\in G$. Since $q$ is the order of $x_0 \\pmod p$, we can see that $q | (p - 1)$. Hence $p - 1 \\equiv 0 \\pmod q$ and hence $p \\equiv 1 \\pmod q$. If $x_0 \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$, then $1 + x_0 + \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot + x_0^{q-1} \\equiv 0 \\pmod p$ means $p = q$. Therefore, any prime divisor of $f$ is either $q$ or $\\equiv 1 \\pmod q$. By Exercise 1.2.5, there are infinitely many primes $p$ such that $f(x) \\equiv 0 \\pmod p$ is solvable since $f(x) \\in \\mathbb{Z}[x]$. We conclude that there are infinitely many primes $p$ such that $p \\equiv 1 \\pmod q$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.2.7}", "question": "Show that $F_{n}$ divides $F_{m}-2$ if n is less than m, and from this deduce that $F_{n}$ and $F_{m}$ are relatively prime if $m\\ne n$.", "solution": "Write $m = n + k$ where $k$ is a nonzero positive integer. Then $\\frac{F_m - 2}{F_n} = \\frac{F_{n+k} - 2}{F_n} = \\frac{2^{2^{n+k}} - 1}{2^{2^n} + 1} = \\frac{(2^{2^n})^{2^k} - 1}{2^{2^n} + 1} = \\frac{t^{2^k} - 1}{t + 1}$ where $t = 2^{2^n}$. Since $k \\ge 1$, $2^k$ is even, so $t + 1 | t^{2^k} - 1$. Thus $F_n | F_m - 2$. Now, if $d = (F_n, F_m)$, then $d | F_n$ and $d | F_m$. Since $F_n | F_m - 2$, $d | F_m - 2$. Then $d | F_m - (F_m - 2) = 2$. Since $F_n$ is odd, $d$ must be odd, so $d = 1$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.2.8}", "question": "Consider the nth Fermat number $F_{n}=2^{2^{n}}+1$. Prove that every prime divisor of $F_{n}$ is of the form $2^{n+1}k+1$.", "solution": "Let $p$ be a prime divisor of $2^{2^n}+ 1$. Then $2^{2^n}\\equiv -1 \\pmod p$, so $(2^{2^n})^2 \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$. Hence we have $2^{2^{n+1}}\\equiv 1 \\pmod p$. We will show that the order of 2 (mod $p$) is $2^{n+1}$. Let $x = ord_p 2$. Since $x | 2^{n+1}$ we can write $x = 2^m$ where $m$ is an integer and $1 \\le m \\le n + 1$. Hence for all $n \\ge m$, $2^{2^n}\\equiv 1 \\pmod p$. But by assumption $2^{2^n}\\equiv -1 \\pmod p$, which implies that $2^{2^m}\\equiv 1 \\pmod p$ holds only if $m \\ge n + 1$. We now consider the multiplicative group $G = \\{1,... , p - 1\\}$. We must have $2^{n+1} | p - 1$ since $ord_p 2=2^{n+1}$ and the order of $G$ is $p - 1$. Therefore we can write $p - 1=2^{n+1}k$ where $k$ is an integer, and we conclude that $p = 2^{n+1}k + 1$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.2.9}", "question": "Given a natural number n, let $n=p_{1}^{\\alpha_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{k}^{\\alpha_{k}}$ be its unique factorization as a product of prime powers. We define the squarefree part of n, denoted $S(n)$, to be the product of the primes $p_{i}$ for which $\\alpha_{i}=1$ Let $f(x)\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x]$ be nonconstant and monic. Show that lim inf $S(f(n))$ is unbounded as n ranges over the integers.", "solution": "By Exercise 1.2.5, we know that $f$ has infinitely many prime divisors. Let $p$ be such a prime and suppose $f(x_0) \\equiv 0 \\pmod p$. Observe that $f(x_0 + p) \\equiv f(x_0) + pf'(x_o) \\pmod{p^2}$. We define the discriminant of a monic polynomial $f$ to be $\\prod_{i>j} (r_i - r_j )^2$, where $r_1,... ,r_n$ are the roots of $f$. If $p | f'(x_0)$, then $p$ would divide the discriminant of $f$. Choosing $p$ sufficiently large, we may assume this does not happen. In either case, we deduce that the squarefree part of $f(x_0)$ is divisible by $p$ or the squarefree part of $f(x_0 + p)$ is divisible by $p$. If $S(f(n))$ were bounded, we have derived a contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.3.1}", "question": "Assuming the ABC Conjecture, show that if $xyz\\ne0$ and $x^{n}+y^{n}=z^{n}$ for three mutually coprime integers x, y, and z, then n is bounded.", "solution": "First observe that $\\max\\{|x|, |y|, |z|\\} > 1$ for otherwise we have $xyz = 0$. By the ABC Conjecture, we have $\\max\\{|x|^n, |y|^n, |z|^n) \\le \\kappa(\\varepsilon)(rad(xyz))^{1+\\varepsilon}$. Without any loss of generality, suppose that $\\max \\{|x|, |y|, |z|\\}= |z|$. We deduce that $|z|^n \\le \\kappa(\\varepsilon)|z|^{3+3\\varepsilon}$. Since $|z| > 1$, we conclude that $n$ is bounded.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.3.2}", "question": "Let p be an odd prime. Suppose that $2^{n}\\equiv1$ (mod p) and $2^{n}\\not\\equiv1$ (mod $p^{2}$). Show that $2^{d}\\not\\equiv1$ (mod $p^{2}$) where d is the order of 2 (mod p).", "solution": "Since $2^n \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$, we must have $d | n$. Write $n = de$. If $2^d =1+ kp$ and $p | k$, then $2^n = 2^{de} = (1 + kp)^e \\equiv 1 + kpe \\pmod{p^2} \\equiv 1 \\pmod{p^2}$, a contradiction. This proves the result.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.3.3}", "question": "Assuming the ABC Conjecture, show that there are infinitely many primes p such that $2^{p-1}\\ne1$ (mod $p^{2}$).", "solution": "Let us write $2^n - 1 = u_nv_n$ where $u_n$ is the squarefree part of $2^n - 1$ and $v_n$ is the squarefull (or powerfull) part of $2^n - 1$. (Recall that a number $N$ is called squarefull (powerfull) if for every prime $q | N$ we have $q^2 | N$. Thus for any number $N$, $N/S(N)$ is squarefull (or powerfull) with $S(N)$ the squarefree part of $N$.) Therefore $(u_n, v_n)=1$. We begin by showing that if $p | u_n$, then $2^{p-1} \\not\\equiv 1 \\pmod{p^2}$. Indeed, we know that $p | 2^n-1$ and $p^2 \\nmid 2^n-1$. By Exercise 1.3.2, $p^2 \\nmid 2^d -1$ where $d$ is the order of 2 (mod $p$). Now $d | (p-1)$ by the little theorem of Fermat and Lagrange's theorem. Write $df = p - 1$. Then $2^d =1+ kp$ with $p \\nmid k$ so that $2^{p-1} = (1 + kp)^f \\equiv 1 + kfp \\pmod{p^2}$. Since $f | p - 1$ and $p \\nmid k$, we find that $2^{p-1} \\not\\equiv 1 \\pmod{p^2}$ for every prime $p$ dividing $u_n$. Now suppose there are only finitely many such primes $p$. Since $u_n$ is squarefree, this implies that $u_n$ is bounded. Now consider the ABC equation: $(2^n - 1) + 1 = 2^n$. The ABC Conjecture implies that $2^n \\le \\kappa(\\varepsilon)(2 rad(2^n - 1))^{1+\\varepsilon}$. But $rad(2^n - 1) \\le u_nv_n^{1/2}$ and so $u_nv_n = 2^n - 1 < 2^n \\le \\kappa(\\varepsilon)(2u_nv_n^{1/2})^{1+\\varepsilon}$. Since $u_n$ is bounded, this implies that $v_n$ is bounded, and hence $n$ is bounded, a contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.3.4}", "question": "Show that the number of primes $p\\le x$ for which $2^{p-1}\\not\\equiv1$ (mod p$^2$) is $\\gg log~x/log~log~x,$ assuming the ABC Conjecture.", "solution": "If for any $n$, we have $u_n = 1$, then the ABC Conjecture implies, as above, that $n$ is bounded. Thus for $n$ sufficiently large (say $n>N$), $u_n > 1$. For each prime $q$ satisfying $N<q \\le (\\log x)/ \\log 2$, we have $u_q > 1$. Moreover, for any two distinct primes $q_1$ and $q_2$, $gcd(2^{q_1} - 1, 2^{q_2} - 1) = 1$ because $p | 2^{q_1} - 1$ and $p | 2^{q_2} - 1$ implies that the order of 2 (mod $p$) divides $q_1$ and $q_2$ and so it divides their gcd, which is 1. This implies that $p | 1$, which is a contradiction. Thus, for every prime $p | u_q$, we find $2^{p-1} \\not\\equiv 1 \\pmod{p^2}$. In addition, the $u_q$s are mutually coprime. In this way we obtain $\\pi(\\frac{\\log x}{\\log 2}) \\ge \\frac{\\log x}{\\log 2 \\log 2 \\log ( \\frac{\\log x}{\\log 2} )}$ by Exercise 1.1.25 = $\\frac{\\log x}{2(\\log \\log x - \\log \\log 2)} > \\frac{\\log x}{\\log \\log x}$, primes $p<x$ such that $2^{p-1} \\not\\equiv 2 \\pmod{p^2}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.3.5}", "question": "Show that if the Erdös conjecture above is true, then there are infinitely many primes p such that $2^{p-1}\\not\\equiv1$ (mod $p^{2}$.", "solution": "Suppose for $p>p_0$ that $2^{p-1} \\equiv 1 \\pmod{p^2}$. Let $t = \\prod_{p\\le p_0} p$. Then $\\phi(t) = \\prod_{p\\le p_0} (p - 1)$. Now consider the sequence $c_n = 2^{nt\\phi(t)} - 1$. We claim that $c_n$ is powerfull. Indeed if $2 < p \\le p_0$, then by Euler's theorem $p^2 | c_n$. If $p>p_0$, and $p | c_n$, then $p^2 | v_{nt\\phi(t)}$ by the argument in Exercise 1.3.3. Thus $p^2 | c_n$ and so $c_n$ is squarefull. For $n$ even, say $n = 2k$, we deduce that both $2^{kt\\phi(t)} - 1$ and $2^{kt\\phi(t)} + 1$ are powerfull. But then, so is $2^{kt\\phi(t)}$, contrary to the Erdös conjecture.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.3.6}", "question": "Assuming the ABC Conjecture, prove that there are only finitely many n such that $n-1$, n, $n+1$ are squarefull.", "solution": "If $n - 1, n, n + 1$ are squarefull, consider the ABC equation $(n^2 - 1) + 1 = n^2$. Then, $n^2 \\le \\kappa(\\varepsilon)(rad(n^2(n^2 - 1)))^{1+\\varepsilon} \\le \\kappa(\\varepsilon)(n^{1/2}\\sqrt{n - 1}\\sqrt{n + 1})^{1+\\varepsilon}$ since $n, n - 1,$ and $n + 1$ are all squarefull. This implies $n^2 \\le \\kappa(\\varepsilon)n^{3/2 + 3\\varepsilon/2}$, which means $n$ is bounded.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.3.7}", "question": "Suppose that a and b are odd positive integers satisfying $rad(a^{n}-2)=rad(b^{n}-2)$ for every natural number n. Assuming ABC, prove that $a=b$. (This problem is due to H. Kisilevsky.)", "solution": "Suppose without loss that $a<b$. Hence $\\log b > \\log a$ so we can choose $\\varepsilon > 0$ so that $\\log b > (1 + \\varepsilon) \\log a$. Now apply the ABC Conjecture to the equation $(b^n - 2) + 2 = b^n$. Then $b^n \\le \\kappa(\\varepsilon)(2b rad(b^n - 2))^{1+\\varepsilon} \\le \\kappa(\\varepsilon)(2b rad(a^n - 2))^{1+\\varepsilon} \\le \\kappa(\\varepsilon)(2ba^n)^{1+\\varepsilon}$. Taking nth roots and letting $n \\to \\infty$ gives $\\log b \\le (1 + \\varepsilon) \\log a$, which is a contradiction. This completes the proof.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.1}", "question": "Show that every proper ideal of Z is of the form nZ for some integer n.", "solution": "Suppose there is an ideal $I$ for which this is not true. Then show that there exist elements $a, b \\in I$ such that $gcd(a, b) = 1$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.2}", "question": "An ideal I is called prime if $ab\\in I$ implies $a\\in I$ or $b\\in I.$ Prove that every prime ideal of Z is of the form pZ for some prime integer p.", "solution": "If $I$ is an ideal, then it is of the form $nZ$ for some integer $n$ by the previous question. Then $ab \\in I$ implies that $n | ab$. But then since $I$ is prime, either $a \\in I$ or $b \\in I$, so $n | a$ or $n | b$, implying that $n$ is prime.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.3}", "question": "Prove that if the number of prime Fermat numbers is finite, then the number of primes of the form $2^{n}+1$ is finite.", "solution": "Consider primes of the form $2^n + 1$. If $n$ has an odd factor, say $n = rs$ with $r$ odd, then $2^{rs} + 1$ is divisible by $2^s + 1$, and is therefore not prime.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.4}", "question": "If $n>1$ and $a^{n}-1$ is prime, prove that $a=2$ and n is prime.", "solution": "If $a > 2$, then $a^n - 1$ is divisible by $a - 1$. So assume $a = 2$. Then if $n$ has a factor, say $k$, then $2^k - 1 | 2^n - 1$. Therefore if $a^n - 1$ is prime, $a = 2$ and $n$ is prime. Numbers of this form are called Mersenne numbers.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.6}", "question": "Prove that if p is an odd prime, any prime divisor of $2^{p}-1$ is of the form $2kp+1$, with k a positive integer.", "solution": "Suppose $q$ is a prime divisor of $2^p -1$. Then $q$ must be odd. We note that $2^p \\equiv 1 \\pmod q$ and also, by Fermat's little Theorem, $2^{q-1} \\equiv 1 \\pmod q$. Then $p | (q - 1)$ since $p$ is prime. Then $q \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$ so $q = mp + 1$ but since $q$ is odd, $m = 2k$ for some $k$, and so $q = 2kp + 1$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.7}", "question": "Show that there are no integer solutions to the equation $x^{4}-y^{4}= 2z^{2}$.", "solution": "We will consider only solutions with $gcd(x, y) = 1$, since any common factor of $x, y$ will also divide $z$. Therefore any solution to this equation with $gcd(x, y) \\ne 1$ will lead to a solution with $gcd(x, y) = 1$. We notice that since the right-hand side of the equation is even, $x$ and $y$ are either both even or both odd. Since $x, y$ are coprime, they must be odd. Then $x^4 - y^4 \\equiv 0 \\pmod 4$ and so $z$ is even. We can factor the equation as $(x^2 + y^2)(x^2 - y^2)=2z^2$. We note that $x^2 +y^2 \\equiv 2 \\pmod 4$ and $x^2 -y^2 \\equiv 0 \\pmod 4$, so $(x^2 +y^2)/2$ is odd. Now we rewrite our equation as $\\frac{x^2 + y^2}{2}(x^2 - y^2) = z^2$. If there is an integer $\\delta$ such that $\\delta | (x^2 +y^2)/2$ and $\\delta | x^2 -y^2$, then $\\delta | 2x^2$. It is easy to see that the two factors are coprime, and so we can write $x + y = 2c^2, x - y = 2d^2$. Now we notice that we have $(x + y)^2 + (x - y)^2 = 2x^2 + 2y^2 = 2(x^2 + y^2)$. Given our expressions above, this translates into the equation $4c^4 + 4d^4 = 4a^2$, but we know that $x^4 + y^4 = z^2$ has no solutions in Z. Thus, the given equation has no solution.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.8}", "question": "Let p be an odd prime number. Show that the numerator of $1+\\frac{1}{2}+\\frac{1}{3}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\frac{1}{p-1}$ is divisible by p.", "solution": "Look at the sum modulo p.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.9}", "question": "Let p be an odd prime number greater than 3. Show that the numerator of $1+\\frac{1}{2}+\\frac{1}{3}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\frac{1}{p-1}$ is divisible by $p^{2}$.", "solution": "Pair up $1/i$ and $1/(p - i)$ and consider the sum mod $p$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.10}", "question": "(Wilson's Theorem) Show that $n>1$ is prime if and only if n divides $(n-1)!+1$", "solution": "When $n$ is prime, consider $(n - 1)! \\pmod n$ by pairing each residue class with its multiplicative inverse.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.11}", "question": "For each $n>1$, let Q be the product of all numbers $a<n$ which are coprime to n. Show that $Q\\equiv\\pm1$ (mod n).", "solution": "$Q$ is clearly congruent to the product of elements of order 2. Now pair up $a$ and $(n - a)$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.12}", "question": "In the previous exercise, show that $Q\\equiv1$ (mod n) whenever n is odd and has at least two prime factors.", "solution": "Clearly $Q \\equiv (-1)^s \\pmod n$ where $2^s$ is the number of elements $a$ satisfying $a^2 \\equiv 1 \\pmod n$. Use the Chinese Remainder Theorem (see Exercise 5.3.13) to determine $s$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.13}", "question": "Use Exercises 1.2.7 and 1.2.8 to show that there are infinitely many primes $\\equiv1$ (mod 2 ) for any given r.", "solution": "If $p | F_n$, then $p \\equiv 1 \\pmod{2^{n+1}}$. For each $n \\ge r$, we have $p \\equiv 1 \\pmod{2^r}$. By Exercise 1.2.7 these primes are all distinct.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.14}", "question": "Suppose p is an odd prime such that $2p+1=q$ is also prime. Show that the equation $x^{p}+2y^{p}+5z^{p}=0$ has no solutions in integers.", "solution": "Consider the equation mod $q$. Then $x^p \\equiv \\pm1$ or $0 \\pmod q$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.15}", "question": "If  and y are coprime integers, show that if $(x+y)$ and $\\frac{x^{p}+y^{p}}{x+y}$ have a common prime factor, it must be p.", "solution": "Suppose a prime $q$ is a common factor. Then $0 \\equiv \\frac{x^p + y^p}{x + y} \\equiv x^{p-1} - x^{p-2}y + \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot + y^{p-1} \\equiv px^{p-1} \\pmod q$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.16}", "question": "(Sophie Germain's Trick) Let p be a prime such that $2p+ 1=q>3$ is also prime. Show that $x^{p}+y^{p}+z^{p}=0$ has no integral solutions with płxyz.", "solution": "By the previous exercise, $x + y = a^p$ and $(x^p + y^p)/(x + y) = c^p$ for some integers $a$ and $c$. By symmetry, $y + z = b^p, x + z = d^p$. If $q \\nmid xyz$, then $x^p + y^p + z^p \\equiv 0 \\pmod q$ is impossible since $\\pm1 \\pm 1 \\pm 1 \\equiv 0 \\pmod q$ is impossible. Now suppose $q | xyz$. If $q | x$, then $q \\nmid yz$ so that $2x + y + z \\equiv b^p \\equiv a^p + d^p \\pmod q$ which again is impossible if $a, b,$ and $d$ are coprime to $q$. Thus one of these must be divisible by $q$. It is easy to see that this must be $b$. Thus, $y + z \\equiv 0 \\pmod q$. Since $\\frac{y^p + z^p}{y + z}$ is also a $p$th power, $t^p$ (say), we obtain the congruence $t^p \\equiv py^{p-1} \\pmod q$. Since $q$ does not divide $t$, we deduce that $py^{p-1} \\equiv \\pm1 \\pmod q$. Also, $x + y = a^p$ implies $y \\equiv a^p \\pmod q$ so that $y$ is a $p$th power mod $q$ which is coprime to $q$. Thus, $p \\equiv \\pm1 \\pmod q$, a contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.17}", "question": "Assuming ABC, show that there are only finitely many consecutive cubefull numbers.", "solution": "If $n - 1$ and $n$ are cubefull, then apply ABC to $n - (n - 1) = 1$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.18}", "question": "Show that $\\sum_{p}\\frac{1}{p}=+\\infty,$ where the summation is over prime numbers.", "solution": "Clearly, $\\sum_{n\\le x} \\frac{1}{n} \\le \\prod_{p\\le x}(1 - \\frac{1}{p})^{-1}= \\prod_{p\\le x}(1 +\\frac{1}{p}+\\frac{1}{p^2} + \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot)$ since every natural number $n \\le x$ can be written as a product of primes $p \\le x$. Now take logs. Then $\\sum_{p\\le x} \\frac{1}{p} + O(1) \\ge \\log(\\sum_{n\\le x}\\frac{1}{n})$. Since the harmonic series diverges, the result follows.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.19(a)}", "question": "(Bertrand's Postulate) (a) If $a_{0}\\ge a_{1}\\ge a_{2}\\ge\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot$ is a decreasing sequence of real numbers tending to 0, show that $\\sum_{n=0}^{\\infty}(-1)^{n}a_{n}\\le a_{0}-a_{1}+a_{2}$ .", "solution": "From $\\sum_{n=0}^{\\infty} (-1)^na_n = a_0 - (a_1 - a_2) - (a_3 - a_4) - \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot$, (a) is immediate.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.19(b)}", "question": "(Bertrand's Postulate) (b) Let $T(x)=\\sum_{n\\le x}\\psi(x/n)$ where $\\psi(x)$ is defined as in Exercise 1.1.25. Show that $T(x)=x~log~x-x+O(log~x).$", "solution": "To see (b), observe that $\\sum_{n\\le x} \\log n = \\sum_{n\\le x} (\\sum_{p^\\alpha|n}\\log p) = \\sum_{m\\le x}\\psi(\\frac{x}{m}) = T(x)$. By comparing areas, $\\sum_{n\\le x} \\log n = \\int_{1}^{x} (\\log t) dt + O(\\log x)$ implies (b).", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 1.4.19(c)}", "question": "(Bertrand's Postulate) (c) Show that $T(x)-2T(\\frac{x}{2})=\\sum_{n\\le x}(-1)^{n-1}\\psi(\\frac{x}{n})=(log~2)x+O(log~x).$ Deduce that $\\psi(x)-\\psi(\\frac{x}{2})\\ge\\frac{1}{3}(log~2)x+O(log~x).$", "solution": "The first part of (c) is now clear. Since $\\psi(x/n)$ is a decreasing function of $n$, we apply (a) to get $\\psi(x) - \\psi(\\frac{x}{2})+ \\psi(\\frac{x}{3})\\ge (\\log 2)x + O(\\log x)$. By Exercise 1.1.14, $\\psi(x) \\le 2x \\log 2$. Therefore, $\\psi(x) - \\psi(\\frac{x}{2})\\ge \\frac{1}{3} (\\log 2)x + O(\\log x)$. Hence, there is a prime between $x/2$ and $x$ for $x$ sufficiently large.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.1.1}", "question": "Show that for $Re(s)>1$ \n$$\\zeta(s)=\\prod_{p}(1-\\frac{1}{p^{s}})^{-1},$$\nwhere the product is over prime numbers $p$.", "solution": "Since every natural number can be factored uniquely as a product of prime powers, it is clear that when we expand the product\n$$\\prod_{p}(1+\\frac{1}{p^{s}}+\\frac{1}{p^{2s}}+\\frac{1}{p^{3s}}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot)$$\nthe term $1/n^{s}$ occurs exactly once. The assertion is now evident.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.1.2}", "question": "Let $K$ be an algebraic number field and $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ its ring of integers. The Dedekind zeta function $\\zeta_{K}(s)$ is defined for $Re(s)>1$ as the infinite series\n$$\\zeta_{K}(s)=\\sum_{\\mathfrak{a}}\\frac{1}{(N\\mathfrak{a})^{s}},$$\nwhere the sum is over all ideals of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Show that the infinite series is absolutely convergent for $Re(s)>1$.", "solution": "For any $s$ with $Re(s)>1$, it suffices to show that the partial sums\n$$\\sum_{N\\mathfrak{a}\\le x}\\frac{1}{(N\\mathfrak{a})^{s}}$$\nare bounded. Indeed, since any ideal can be expressed as a product of powers of prime ideals, it is evident that\n$$\\sum_{N\\mathfrak{a}\\le x}\\frac{1}{(N\\mathfrak{a})^{\\sigma}}\\le\\prod_{N\\mathfrak{p}\\le x}(1+\\frac{1}{(N\\mathfrak{p})^{\\sigma}}+\\frac{1}{(N\\mathfrak{p})^{2\\sigma}}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot)$$\nwhere $\\sigma=Re(s)>1$. Hence\n$$\\sum_{N\\mathfrak{a}\\le x}\\frac{1}{(N\\mathfrak{a})^{\\sigma}}\\le\\prod_{N\\mathfrak{p}\\le x}(1-\\frac{1}{(N\\mathfrak{p})^{\\sigma}})^{-1}.$$\nFor each prime ideal $\\mathfrak{p}$, we have a unique prime number $p$ such that $N(\\mathfrak{p})=p^{f}$ for some integer $f$. Moreover, there are at most $[K:\\mathbb{Q}]$ prime ideals corresponding to the same prime $p$. In fact, they are determined from the factorization $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{e_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{g}^{e_{g}}$ and by Exercise 5.3.17, $\\sum_{i=1}^{g}e_{i}f_{i}=[K:\\mathbb{Q}]$ where $N\\mathfrak{p}_{i}=p^{f_{i}}$. Since $e_{i}\\ge1$ and $f_{i}\\ge1$ we find $g\\le[K:\\mathbb{Q}]$. Hence\n$$\\sum_{N\\mathfrak{a}\\le x}\\frac{1}{(N\\mathfrak{a})^{\\sigma}}\\le\\prod_{p\\le x}(1-\\frac{1}{p^{\\sigma}})^{-[K:\\mathbb{Q}]}.$$\nSince the product $\\prod_{p}(1-p^{-\\sigma})^{-1}$ converges absolutely for $\\sigma>1$, the result follows.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.1.3}", "question": "Prove that for $Re(s)>1,$\n$$\\zeta_{K}(s)=\\prod_{\\mathfrak{p}}(1-\\frac{1}{(N\\mathfrak{p})^{s}})^{-1}.$$", "solution": "Since every ideal $\\mathfrak{a}$ can be written uniquely as a product of prime ideals (see Theorem 5.3.6), we find that when the product\n$$\\prod_{\\mathfrak{p}}(1+\\frac{1}{(N\\mathfrak{p})^{s}}+\\frac{1}{(N\\mathfrak{p})^{2s}}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot)$$\nis expanded, $1/(N\\mathfrak{a})^{s}$ occurs exactly once for each ideal $\\mathfrak{a}$ of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 10.1.4}", "question": "Let $\\{a_{m}\\}_{m=1}^{\\infty}$ be a sequence of complex numbers, and let $A(x)=\\sum_{m\\le x}a_{m}=O(x^{\\delta})$, for some $\\delta\\ge0$. Then\n$$\\sum_{m=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{a_{m}}{m^{s}}$$\nconverges for $Re(s)>\\delta$ and in this half-plane we have\n$$\\sum_{m=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{a_{m}}{m^{s}}=s\\int_{1}^{\\infty}\\frac{A(x)dx}{x^{s+1}}$$\nfor $Re(s)>1$.", "solution": "We write\n$\\sum_{m=1}^{M}\\frac{a_{m}}{m^{s}}=\\sum_{m=1}^{M}(A(m)-A(m-1))m^{-s}$\n$=A(M)M^{-s}+\\sum_{m=1}^{M-1}A(m)\\{m^{-s}-(m+1)^{-s}\\}$.\nSince $m^{-s}-(m+1)^{-s}=s\\int_{m}^{m+1}\\frac{dx}{x^{s+1}}$, we get\n$\\sum_{m=1}^{M}\\frac{a_{m}}{m^{s}}=\\frac{A(M)}{M^{s}}+s\\int_{1}^{M}\\frac{A(x)dx}{x^{s+1}}.$\nFor $Re(s)>\\delta,$ we find\n$lim_{M\\rightarrow\\infty}\\frac{A(M)}{M^{s}}=0,$\nsince $A(x)=O(x^{\\delta})$. Hence, the partial sums converge for $Re(s)>\\delta$ and we have\n$\\sum_{m=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{a_{m}}{m^{s}}=s\\int_{1}^{\\infty}\\frac{A(x)dx}{x^{s+1}}$\nin this half-plane.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.1.5}", "question": "Show that $(s-1)\\zeta(s)$ can be extended analytically for $Re(s)>0$.", "solution": "We apply Theorem 10.1.4 with $a_{m}=1$. Then $A(x)=[x]$, the greatest integer less than or equal to $x$. Thus,\n$$\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{1}{n^{s}}=s\\int_{1}^{\\infty}\\frac{[x]dx}{x^{s+1}}.$$\nWriting $[x]=x-\\{x\\}$ we obtain for $Re(s)>1$,\n$$\\zeta(s)=\\frac{s}{s-1}-s\\int_{1}^{\\infty}\\frac{\\{x\\}dx}{x^{s+1}}.$$\nSince $\\{x\\}$ is bounded by 1, the latter integral converges for $Re(s)>0.$ Thus, $(s-1)\\zeta(s)$ is analytic for $Re(s)>0$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.1.6}", "question": "Evaluate\n$$lim_{s\\rightarrow1}(s-1)\\zeta(s).$$", "solution": "From the previous exercise we have\n$$lim_{s\\rightarrow1}(s-1)\\zeta(s)=lim_{s\\rightarrow1}s-lim_{s\\rightarrow1}s(s-1)\\int_{1}^{\\infty}\\frac{\\{x\\}dx}{x^{s+1}}$$\nand the latter limit is zero since the integral is bounded. Hence, the desired limit is 1.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.1.8}", "question": "For $K=\\mathbb{Q}(i)$, evaluate\n$$lim_{s\\rightarrow1^{+}}(s-1)\\zeta_{K}(s).$$", "solution": "Clearly, this limit is $\\pi/4.$ (Referencing the solution to Example 10.1.7 which derives the analytic continuation)", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.2.1}", "question": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})$ with $d$ squarefree, and denote by $a_{n}$ the number of ideals in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ of norm $n$. Show that $a_{n}$ is multiplicative. (That is, prove that if $(n,m)=1$, then $a_{nm}=a_{n}a_{m}.$).", "solution": "Let $\\mathfrak{a}$ be an ideal of norm $n$ and let $n=\\prod_{i=1}^{k}p_{i}^{\\alpha_{i}}$ be the unique factorization of $n$ into distinct prime powers. Then by unique factorization of ideals, $\\mathfrak{a}=\\prod_{j=1}^{s}\\mathfrak{p}_{j}^{e_{j}}.$ We see immediately that $a_{n}=\\prod_{i=1}^{k}a_{p_{i}^{\\alpha_{i}}}.$ This implies that $a_{n}$ is multiplicative.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.2.2}", "question": "Show that for an odd prime $p$, $a_{p}=1+(\\frac{d}{p})$.", "solution": "By Theorem 7.4.2, we see that an odd prime $p$ splits in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})$ if and only if $(\\frac{d}{p})=1$, in which case there are two ideals of norm $p$. If $p$ does not split, there are no ideals of norm $p$. Finally, if $p$ ramifies, then $(\\frac{d}{p})=0$ and there is only one ideal of norm $p$, by Exercise 7.4.3.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.2.3}", "question": "Let $d_{K}$ be the discriminant of $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})$. Show that for all primes $p$, $a_{p}=1+(\\frac{d_{K}}{p})$.", "solution": "Since $d_{K}=d$ or $4d$, the result is clear for odd primes $p$ from the previous exercise. We therefore need only consider $p=2$. If $2|d_{K}$, then by Theorem 7.4.5, 2 ramifies and there is only one ideal of norm 2. If $2\\nmid d_{K}$, then\n$$(\\frac{d_{K}}{2})=\\begin{cases}1&if~d_{K}\\equiv1~(mod~8),\\\\ -1&if~d_{K}\\equiv5~(mod~8),\\end{cases}$$\nby the definition of the Kronecker symbol. The result is now immediate from Theorem 7.4.5.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.2.4}", "question": "Show that for all primes $p$,\n$$a_{p^{\\alpha}}=\\sum_{j=1}^{\\alpha}(\\frac{d_{K}}{p^{j}})=\\sum_{\\delta|p^{\\alpha}}(\\frac{d_{K}}{\\delta}).$$", "solution": "The norm of any prime ideal is either $p$ or $p^{2}$ the latter occurring if and only if $(\\frac{d}{p})=-1$. Thus for $\\alpha=2$, the formula is established and for $\\alpha=1$, the previous exercise applies. If $(\\frac{d}{p})=-1$ then clearly $a_{p^{\\alpha}}=0$ if $\\alpha$ is odd and if $\\alpha$ is even, then there is only one ideal of norm $p^{\\alpha}$. If $p$ splits, then any ideal of norm $p^{\\alpha}$ must be of the form $\\mathfrak{p}^{j}(\\mathfrak{p}^{\\prime})^{\\alpha-j}$ for some $j$, where $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}^{\\prime}$. It is now clear that $a_{p^{\\alpha}}=\\alpha+1$ which is the sum $\\sum_{j=0}^{\\alpha}(\\frac{d_{K}}{p^{j}})$. Finally, if $p$ ramifies, there is only one ideal of norm $p^{\\alpha}$, namely $\\mathfrak{p}^{\\alpha}$ where $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathfrak{p}^{2}$. This completes the proof.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.2.5}", "question": "Prove that\n$$a_{n}=\\sum_{\\delta|n}(\\frac{d_{K}}{\\delta}).$$", "solution": "Since $a_{n}$ is multiplicative, $a_{n}=\\prod_{p^{\\alpha}||n}(\\sum_{j=0}^{\\alpha}(\\frac{d_{K}}{p^j}))$ by the previous exercise. The result is now immediate upon expanding the product.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.2.6}", "question": "Let $d_{K}$ be the discriminant of the quadratic field $K$. Show that there is an $n>0$ such that $(\\frac{d_{K}}{n})=-1.$", "solution": "We know that $d_{K}\\equiv0$ or 1 (mod 4). If $d_{K}\\equiv1$ (mod 4), then for any odd $n$ we have $(\\frac{d_{K}}{n})=(\\frac{n}{|d_{K}|})$. Let $|d_{K}|=pa$ where $p$ is an odd prime. Since $d_{K}$ is squarefree, $p\\nmid a$. Let $u$ be a quadratic nonresidue modulo $p$. We can find an odd $n\\equiv u$ (mod $p$) and $n\\equiv1$ (mod $2a$) by the Chinese Remainder Theorem. Then\n$$(\\frac{d_{K}}{n})=(\\frac{n}{p})(\\frac{n}{a})=(\\frac{u}{p})(\\frac{1}{a})=-1,$$\nas desired. If $d_{K}$ is even, let $d_{K}=d_{1}d_{2}$ where $d_{1}$ is 4 or 8 and $d_{2}$ is an odd discriminant. Then $(\\frac{d_{K}}{n})=(\\frac{d_{1}}{n})(\\frac{d_{2}}{n})$ by definition of the Kronecker symbol. Since $d_{1}=4$ or 8, it is easy to find an $a$ such that $(\\frac{d_{1}}{a})=-1$. Choose $n\\equiv a$ (mod $d_{1}$), $n\\equiv1$ (mod $d_{2}$). Then $(\\frac{d_{K}}{n})=-1$, as desired.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.2.7}", "question": "Show that\n$$|\\sum_{n\\le x}(\\frac{d_{K}}{n})|\\le|d_{K}|.$$", "solution": "Let $S=\\sum_{n~mod|d_{K}|}(\\frac{d_{K}}{n})$. Choose $n_{0}$ such that $(n_{0},|d_{K}|)=1$ and $(\\frac{d_{K}}{n_{0}})=-1$ (This is possible by the previous exercise.) Then\n$(\\frac{d_{K}}{n_{0}})S=\\sum_{n~mod|d_{K}|}(\\frac{d_{K}}{nn_{0}})$.\nAs $n$ ranges over residue classes mod $|d_{K}|$ so does $nn_{0}$. Hence $-S=(\\frac{d_{K}}{n_{0}})S=S$ so that $S=0$.\nNow define $v$ by $v|d_{K}|\\le x<(v+1)|d_{K}|$. Then,\n$\\sum_{n\\le x}(\\frac{d_{K}}{n})=\\sum_{|d_{K}|v\\le n<x}(\\frac{d_{K}}{n})$ since\n$\\sum_{n<|d_{K}|v}(\\frac{d_{K}}{n})=\\sum_{j=1}^{v}(\\sum_{(j-1)|d_{K}|<n<j|d_{K}|}(\\frac{d_{K}}{n}))$\nand the inner sum is zero because it is equal to $S$. Thus $|\\sum_{n\\le x}(\\frac{d_{K}}{n})|\\le|d_{K}|.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 10.2.8}", "question": "Let $f(n)=\\sum_{\\delta|n}g(\\delta)h(\\frac{n}{\\delta})$ and define $G(x)=\\sum_{n\\le x}g(n),$ $H(x)=\\sum_{n\\le x}h(n)$. Then for any $y>0$,\n$$\\sum_{n\\le x}f(n)=\\sum_{\\delta\\le y}g(\\delta)H(\\frac{x}{\\delta})+\\sum_{\\delta<\\frac{x}{y}}h(\\delta)G(\\frac{x}{\\delta})-G(y)H(\\frac{x}{y}).$$", "solution": "We have\n$\\sum_{n\\le x}f(n)=\\sum_{\\delta e\\le x}g(\\delta)h(e)$\n$=\\sum_{\\delta e\\le x, \\delta\\le y}g(\\delta)h(e)+\\sum_{\\delta e\\le x, \\delta>y}g(\\delta)h(e)$\n$=\\sum_{\\delta\\le y}g(\\delta)H(\\frac{x}{\\delta})+\\sum_{e\\le\\frac{x}{y}}h(e)\\{G(\\frac{x}{e})-G(y)\\}$\n$=\\sum_{\\delta\\le y}g(\\delta)H(\\frac{x}{\\delta})+\\sum_{e\\le\\frac{x}{y}}h(e)G(\\frac{x}{e})-G(y)H(\\frac{x}{y})$\nas desired.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Example 10.2.9}", "question": "Let $K$ be a quadratic field, and $a_{n}$ the number of ideals of norm $n$ in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Show that\n$$\\sum_{n\\le x}a_{n}=cx+O(\\sqrt{x}),$$\nwhere $c=\\sum_{\\delta=1}^{\\infty}(\\frac{d_{K}}{\\delta})\\frac{1}{\\delta}.$", "solution": "By Exercise 10.2.5, $a_{n}=\\sum_{\\delta|n}(\\frac{d_{K}}{\\delta})$ so that we can apply Theorem 10.2.8 with $g(\\delta)=(\\frac{d_{K}}{\\delta})$ and $h(\\delta)=1$, $y=\\sqrt{x}.$ We get\n$$\\sum_{n\\le x}a_{n}=\\sum_{\\delta\\le\\sqrt{x}}(\\frac{d_{K}}{\\delta})[\\frac{x}{\\delta}]+\\sum_{\\delta<\\sqrt{x}}G(\\frac{x}{\\delta})-G(\\sqrt{x})[\\sqrt{x}].$$\nBy Exercise 10.2.7, $|G(x)|\\le|d_{K}|$ Hence\n$$\\sum_{n\\le x}a_{n}=\\sum_{\\delta\\le\\sqrt{x}}(\\frac{d_{K}}{\\delta})[\\frac{x}{\\delta}]+O(\\sqrt{x}).$$\nNow $[x/\\delta]=x/\\delta+O(1)$ so that\n$\\sum_{n\\le x}a_{n}=\\sum_{\\delta\\le\\sqrt{x}}(\\frac{d_{K}}{\\delta})\\frac{x}{\\delta}+O(\\sqrt{x}).$\nFinally, $\\sum_{\\delta\\le\\sqrt{x}}(\\frac{d_{K}}{\\delta})\\frac{1}{\\delta}=\\sum_{\\delta=1}^{\\infty}(\\frac{d_{K}}{\\delta})\\frac{1}{\\delta}-\\sum_{\\delta>\\sqrt{x}}(\\frac{d_{K}}{\\delta})\\frac{1}{\\delta}$ and by Theorem 10.1.4 we see that $\\sum_{\\delta=1}^{\\infty}(\\frac{d_{K}}{\\delta})\\frac{1}{\\delta}$ converges and $\\sum_{\\delta>\\sqrt{x}}(\\frac{d_{K}}{\\delta})\\frac{1}{\\delta}=O(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{x}})$.\nTherefore $\\sum_{n\\le x}a_{n}=cx+O(\\sqrt{x}).$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.2.10}", "question": "If $K$ is a quadratic field, show that $(s-1)\\zeta_{K}(s)$ extends to an analytic function for $Re(s)>\\frac{1}{2}$.", "solution": "By Theorem 10.1.4,\n$$\\zeta_{K}(s)=\\frac{cs}{s-1}+s\\int_{1}^{\\infty}\\frac{E(x)dx}{x^{s+1}},$$\nwhere $E(x)=O(\\sqrt{x})$. The integral therefore converges for $Re(s)>\\frac{1}{2}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.3.1}", "question": "Show that $L(s,\\chi)$ converges absolutely for $Re(s)>1$.", "solution": "Since $|\\chi(n)|\\le1$, we have\n$$|\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{\\chi(n)}{n^{s}}|\\le\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{1}{n^{\\sigma}},$$\nwhere $\\sigma=Re(s)$. The latter series converges absolutely for $Re(s)>1.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.3.2}", "question": "Prove that $|\\sum_{n\\le x}\\chi(n)|\\le m.$", "solution": "If $\\chi$ is nontrivial, there is an $a$ (mod $m$) coprime to $m$ such that $\\chi(a)\\ne1$. Then\n$\\sum_{b~mod~m}\\chi(b)=\\sum_{b~mod~m}\\chi(ab)=\\chi(a)\\sum_{b~mod~m}\\chi(b).$\nHence $\\sum_{b~mod~m, (b,m)=1}\\chi(b)=0.$\nNow, partition the interval $[1, x]$ into subintervals of length $m$ and suppose that $km<x\\le(k+1)m$. Then\n$\\sum_{n\\le x}\\chi(n)=\\sum_{n\\le km}\\chi(n)+\\sum_{km<n\\le x}\\chi(n).$\nThe first sum on the right-hand side is zero and the second sum is bounded by $m$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.3.3}", "question": "If $\\chi$ is nontrivial, show that $L(s,\\chi)$ extends to an analytic function for $Re(s)>0$.", "solution": "By Theorem 10.1.4, this is now immediate.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.3.4}", "question": "For $Re(s)>1$, show that\n$$L(s,\\chi)=\\prod_{p}(1-\\frac{\\chi(p)}{p^{s}})^{-1}$$", "solution": "Since $\\chi$ is completely multiplicative,\n$$L(s,\\chi)=\\prod_{p}(1+\\frac{\\chi(p)}{p^{s}}+\\frac{\\chi(p^{2})}{p^{2s}}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot) =\\prod_{p}(1+\\frac{\\chi(p)}{p^{s}}+\\frac{\\chi(p)^{2}}{p^{s}}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot) =\\prod_{p}(1-\\frac{\\chi(p)}{p^{s}})^{-1}.$$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.3.5}", "question": "Show that\n$$\\sum_{\\chi~mod~m}\\overline{\\chi}(a)\\chi(b)=\\begin{cases}\\varphi(m)&if~a\\equiv b(mod~m),\\\\ 0&otherwise.\\end{cases}$$", "solution": "If $a\\equiv b$ (mod $m$), the result is clear. If $a\\not\\equiv b$ (mod $m$), let $\\psi$ be a character such that $\\psi(a)\\ne\\psi(b)$. Then\n$\\sum_{\\chi~mod~m}\\psi(ba^{-1})\\chi(ba^{-1})=\\sum_{\\chi~mod~m}(\\psi\\chi)(ba^{-1}) =\\sum_{\\chi~mod~m}\\chi(ba^{-1})$,\nbecause as $\\chi$ ranges over characters mod $m$, so does $\\psi\\chi.$ But\n$(1-\\psi(ba^{-1}))\\sum_{\\chi~mod~m}\\chi(ba^{-1})=0$\nso the result follows.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.3.6}", "question": "For $Re(s)>1$, show that\n$$\\sum_{\\chi~mod~m}log~L(s,\\chi)=\\varphi(m)\\sum_{p^{n}\\equiv1~mod~m}\\frac{1}{np^{ns}}$$", "solution": "By Exercises 10.3.3 and 10.3.5, we find\n$$\\sum_{\\chi~mod~m}log~L(s,\\chi)=\\sum_{n,p}\\frac{1}{np^{ns}}\\sum_{\\chi~mod~m}\\chi(p^{n}) =\\varphi(m)\\sum_{p^{n}\\equiv1(mod~m)}\\frac{1}{np^{ns}}.$$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.3.7}", "question": "For $Re(s)>1$ show that\n$$\\sum_{\\chi~mod~m}\\overline{\\chi}(a)log~L(s,\\chi)=\\varphi(m)\\sum_{p^{n}\\equiv a~mod~m}\\frac{1}{np^{ns}}.$$", "solution": "By Exercise 10.3.3,\n$$\\sum_{\\chi~mod~m}\\overline{\\chi}(a)log~L(s,\\chi)=\\sum_{n,p}\\frac{1}{np^{ns}}\\sum_{\\chi~mod~m}\\overline{\\chi}(a)\\chi(p^{n})$$\nsince the series converges absolutely in $Re(s)>1.$ By Exercise 10.3.5, the inner sum on the right-hand side is $\\varphi(m)$ when $p^{n}\\equiv a$ (mod $m$) and zero otherwise. The result is now immediate.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.3.8}", "question": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m})$. Set $f(s)=\\prod_{\\chi}L(s,\\chi).$ Show that $\\zeta_{K}(s)/f(s)$ is analytic for $Re(s)>\\frac{1}{2}$", "solution": "The primes that split completely in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m})$ are those primes $p\\equiv1$ (mod $m$). Thus, because there are $\\phi(m)$ ideals of norm $p$ for $p\\equiv1$ (mod $m$),\n$\\zeta_{K}(s)=\\prod_{\\mathfrak{p}}(1-\\frac{1}{(N\\mathfrak{p})^{s}})^{-1} =\\prod_{p\\equiv1~mod~m}(1-\\frac{1}{p^{s}})^{-\\phi(m)}g(s),$\nwhere $g(s)$ is analytic for $Re(s)>\\frac{1}{2}$. By Exercise 10.3.6\n$\\prod_{\\chi}L(s,\\chi)=\\prod_{p\\equiv1~mod~m}(1-\\frac{1}{p^{s}})^{-\\phi(m)}h(s),$\nwhere $h(s)$ is analytic and nonzero for $Re(s)>\\frac{1}{2}$. Thus, $\\zeta_{K}(s)/f(s)$ is analytic for $Re(s)>\\frac{1}{2}$. This gives the analytic continuation of $\\zeta_{K}(s)$ for $Re(s)>\\frac{1}{2}$. We can in fact show that $\\zeta_{K}(s)=\\prod_{\\chi}L(s,\\chi).$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Lemma 10.4.1}", "question": "Let $\\{a_{n}\\}$ be a sequence of nonnegative numbers. There exists $\\sigma_{0}\\in\\mathbb{R}$ (possibly infinite) such that\n$$f(s)=\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{a_{n}}{n^{s}}$$\nconverges for $\\sigma>\\sigma_{0}$ and diverges for $\\sigma<\\sigma_{0}$. Moreover, if $s\\in\\mathbb{C}$, with $Re(s)>\\sigma_{0}$ then the series converges uniformly in $Re(s)\\ge\\sigma_{0}+\\delta$ for any $\\delta>0$ and\n$$f^{(k)}(s)=(-1)^{k}\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{a_{n}(log~n)^{k}}{n^{s}}$$\nfor $Re(s)>\\sigma_{0}$. ($\\sigma_{0}$ is called the abscissa of convergence of the (Dirichlet) series $\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}a_{n}n^{-s}.$)", "solution": "If there is no real value of $s$ for which the series converges, we take $\\sigma_{0}=\\infty$. Therefore, suppose there is some real $s_{0}$ for which the series converges. Clearly by the comparison test, the series converges for $Re(s)>s_{0}$ since the coefficients are nonnegative. Now let $\\sigma_{0}$ be the infimum of all real $s_{0}$ for which the series converges. The uniform convergence in $Re(s)\\ge\\sigma_{0}+\\delta$ for any $\\delta>0$ is now immediate. Because of this, we can differentiate term by term to calculate $f^{(k)}(s)$ for $Re(s)>\\sigma_{0}.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 10.4.2}", "question": "Let $a_{n}\\ge0$ be a sequence of nonnegative numbers. Then\n$$f(s)=\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{a_{n}}{n^{s}}$$\ndefines a holomorphic function in $Re(s)>\\sigma_{0}$ and $s=\\sigma_{0}$ is a singular point of $f(s)$. (Here $\\sigma_{0}$ is the abscissa of convergence of the Dirichlet series.)", "solution": "By the previous lemma, it is clear that $f(s)$ is holomorphic in $Re(s)>\\sigma_{0}$. If $f$ is not singular at $s=\\sigma_{0}$, then there is a disk $D=\\{s:|s-\\sigma_{1}|<\\delta\\}$, where $\\sigma_{1}>\\sigma_{0}$ such that $|\\sigma_{0}-\\sigma_{1}|<\\delta$ and a holomorphic function $g$ in $D$ such that $g(s)=f(s)$ for $Re(s)>\\sigma_{0}$, $s\\in D$. By Taylor's formula\n$$g(s)=\\sum_{k=0}^{\\infty}\\frac{g^{(k)}(\\sigma_{1})}{k!}(s-\\sigma_{1})^{k}=\\sum_{k=0}^{\\infty}\\frac{f^{(k)}(\\sigma_{1})}{k!}(s-\\sigma_{1})^{k}$$\nsince $g(s)=f(s)$ for $s$ in a neighborhood of $\\sigma_{1}$. Thus, the series\n$$\\sum_{k=0}^{\\infty}\\frac{(-1)^{k}f^{(k)}(\\sigma_{1})}{k!}(\\sigma_{1}-s)^{k}$$\nconverges absolutely for any $s\\in D$. By the lemma, we can write this series as the double series\n$$\\sum_{k=0}^{\\infty}\\frac{(\\sigma_{1}-s)^{k}}{k!}\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{a_{n}(log~n)^{k}}{n^{\\sigma_{1}}}$$\nIf $\\sigma_{1}-\\delta<s<\\sigma_{1}$, this convergent double series consists of nonnegative terms and we may interchange the summations to find\n$$\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{a_{n}}{n^{\\sigma_{1}}}\\sum_{k=0}^{\\infty}\\frac{(\\sigma_{1}-s)^{k}(log~n)^{k}}{k!}=\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{a_{n}}{n^{s}}<\\infty.$$\nSince $\\sigma_{1}-\\delta<\\sigma_{0}<\\sigma_{1}$, this is a contradiction for $s=\\sigma_{0}$. Therefore, the abscissa of convergence is a singular point of $f(s)$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.4.3}", "question": "With the notation as in Section 10.3, write $f(s)=\\prod_{\\chi}L(s,\\chi)=\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{c_{n}}{n^{s}}.$ Show that $c_{n}\\ge0$.", "solution": "This is immediate from Exercise 10.3.6 because\n$$f(s)=exp(\\phi(m)\\sum_{p^{n}\\equiv1~mod~m}\\frac{1}{np^{ns}}).$$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.4.4}", "question": "With notation as in the previous exercise, show that $\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{c_{n}}{n^{s}}$ diverges for $s=1/\\phi(m)$.", "solution": "By Euler's theorem (Theorem 1.1.14), $p^{\\phi(m)}\\equiv1(mod~m)$ for prime $p\\nmid m$. Thus,\n$f(1/\\phi(m)) = exp(\\phi(m)\\sum_{p^{n}\\equiv1~mod~m}\\frac{1}{np^{n/\\phi(m)}}) \\ge exp(\\sum_{p|m}\\frac{1}{p})$.\nSince $\\sum_{p}\\frac{1}{p}=+\\infty,$ we are done (by Exercise 1.4.18).", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 10.4.5}", "question": "Let $L(s,\\chi)$ be defined as above. Then $L(1,\\chi)\\ne0$ for $\\chi\\ne\\chi_{0}$.", "solution": "By the previous exercise, the abscissa of convergence of $f(s)=\\prod_{\\chi}L(s,\\chi)=\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{c_{n}}{n^{s}}$ is greater than or equal to $1/\\varphi(m)$. If for some $\\chi\\ne\\chi_{0}$ we have $L(1,\\chi)=0,$ then $f(s)$ is holomorphic at $s=1$ since the zero of $L(s,\\chi)$ cancels the simple pole at $s=1$ of $L(s,\\chi_{0})=\\zeta(s)\\prod_{p|m}(1-\\frac{1}{p^{s}})$.\nBy Exercise 10.3.3, each $L(s,\\chi)$ extends to an analytic function for $Re(s)>0$. By Exercise 10.1.5, $\\zeta(s)$ (and hence $L(s,\\chi_{0})$) is analytic for $Re(s)>0$, $s\\ne1$. Thus, $f(s)$ is analytic for $Re(s)>0$. By Theorem 10.4.2, the abscissa of convergence of the Dirichlet series $\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{c_{n}}{n^{s}}$ is not in $Re(s)>0$ which contradicts the divergence of the series at $s=1/\\varphi(m)$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.4.6}", "question": "Show that $\\sum_{p\\equiv1(mod~m)}\\frac{1}{p}=+\\infty.$", "solution": "By Exercise 10.3.6,\n$$\\sum_{p^{n}\\equiv1~mod~m}\\frac{1}{np^{ns}}=\\frac{1}{\\phi(m)}\\sum_{\\chi~mod~m}log~L(s,\\chi).$$\nAs $s\\rightarrow1^{+}$ we see that $\\sum_{p\\equiv1~mod~m}\\frac{1}{p}=+\\infty$ because $L(1,\\chi)\\ne0$ for $\\chi\\ne\\chi_{0}$ and\n$lim_{s\\rightarrow1^{+}}log~L(s,\\chi_{0})=lim_{s\\rightarrow1^{+}}log(\\zeta(s)\\prod_{p|m}(1-\\frac{1}{p^{s}}))=+\\infty.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.4.7}", "question": "Show that if $gcd(a,m)=1$ then $\\sum_{p\\equiv a(mod~m)}\\frac{1}{p}=+\\infty.$", "solution": "By Exercise 10.3.7,\n$$\\sum_{p^{n}\\equiv a~mod~m}\\frac{1}{np^{ns}}=\\frac{1}{\\phi(m)}\\sum_{\\chi~mod~m}\\overline{\\chi}(a)log~L(s,\\chi).$$\nAs $s\\rightarrow1^{+}$ we see that $\\sum_{p\\equiv a~mod~m}\\frac{1}{p}=+\\infty$ again because $L(1,\\chi)\\ne0$ for $\\chi\\ne\\chi_{0}$ and $lim_{s\\rightarrow1^{+}}log~L(s,\\chi_{0})=+\\infty$. Hence there are infinitely many primes in any given coprime residue class mod $m$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.5.2}", "question": "Show that $|g(\\chi)|=\\sqrt{m}$.", "solution": "$$\\sum_{n=1}^{m-1}|\\chi(n)|^{2}|g(\\overline{\\chi})|^{2}=\\sum_{n=0}^{m-1}|\\sum_{b~mod~m}\\overline{\\chi}(b)e^{2\\pi ibn/m}|^{2}$$\n$$=\\sum_{b_{1},b_{2}}\\overline{\\chi}(b_{1})\\chi(b_{2})\\sum_{n=0}^{m-1}e^{2\\pi i(b_{1}-b_{2})n/m}.$$\nThe last sum is the sum of a geometric progression and is 0 unless $b_{1}\\equiv b_{2}$ (mod $m$) in which case it is $m$. Thus,\n$$\\phi(m)|g(\\overline{\\chi})|^{2}=m\\phi(m)$$\nfrom which the result follows.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.5.3}", "question": "Establish the Pólya-Vinogradov inequality:\n$$|\\sum_{n\\le x}\\chi(n)|\\le\\frac{1}{2}m^{1/2}(1+log~m)$$\nfor any nontrivial character $\\chi$ (mod $m$).", "solution": "By the two previous exercises, we get\n$$\\sum_{n\\le x}\\chi(n)=g(\\overline{\\chi})^{-1}\\sum_{n\\le x}(\\sum_{b~mod~m}\\overline{\\chi}(b)e^{2\\pi ibn/m})$$\nInterchanging summation gives\n$$\\sum_{n\\le x}e^{2\\pi ibn/m}=\\frac{e^{2\\pi ib([x]+1)/m}-1}{e^{2\\pi ib/m}-1},$$\nprovided $b\\not\\equiv0$ (mod $m$). Observe that the numerator is bounded by 2 and the denominator can be written as\n$e^{\\pi ib/m}(e^{\\pi ib/m}-e^{-\\pi ib/m})=2ie^{\\pi ib/m}sin\\frac{\\pi b}{m}$\nso that for $b\\not\\equiv0$ (mod $m$)\n$$|\\sum_{n\\le x}e^{2\\pi ibn/m}|\\le\\frac{1}{|sin\\frac{\\pi b}{m}|}.$$\nSince $|sin\\frac{\\pi b}{m}|=|sin\\frac{\\pi(m-b)}{m}|$, we may suppose $b\\le m/2.$ In that case, $|sin\\frac{\\pi b}{m}|\\ge\\frac{2}{\\pi}(\\frac{\\pi b}{m})$ because $sin~x\\ge2x/\\pi$ for $0\\le x\\le\\pi/2$, as is seen by looking at the graph of sin $x$. Therefore\n$$|\\sum_{n\\le x}\\chi(n)|\\le|g(\\overline{\\chi}|^{-1}\\sum_{b~mod~m}\\frac{m}{2b} \\le\\frac{\\sqrt{m}}{2}log~m.$$\nThe last inequality follows by noting that\n$\\sum_{b\\le m}\\frac{1}{b}\\le1+\\int_{1}^{m}\\frac{dt}{t}=1+log~m.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.5.4}", "question": "Let $p$ be prime. Let $\\chi$ be a character mod $p$. Show that there is an $a\\le p^{1/2}(1+log~p)$ such that $\\chi(a)\\ne1$.", "solution": "If each $a\\le p^{1/2}(1+log~p)=u(say)$ satisfies $\\chi(a)=1$ then $\\sum_{a\\le u}\\chi(a)=u.$ By the Pólya-Vinogradov inequality, the left-hand side is $\\le\\frac{1}{2}p^{1/2}(1+log~p)$, which is a contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.5.5}", "question": "Show that if $\\chi$ is a nontrivial character mod $m$, then\n$$L(1,\\chi)=\\sum_{n\\le u}\\frac{\\chi(n)}{n}+O(\\frac{\\sqrt{m}log~m}{u})$$", "solution": "By Theorem 10.1.4,\n$$\\sum_{n>u}\\frac{\\chi(n)}{n}=\\int_{1}^{\\infty}\\frac{A(x)dx}{x^{2}}$$\nwhere $A(x)=\\begin{cases}0&if~x<u,\\\\ \\sum_{u<n\\le x}\\chi(n)&if~x\\ge u.\\end{cases}$\nBy Pólya-Vinogradov, $A(x)=O(\\sqrt{m}log~m)$ and so\n$\\sum_{n>u}\\frac{\\chi(n)}{n}=\\int_{u}^{\\infty}\\frac{A(x)dx}{x^{2}}=O(\\frac{\\sqrt{m}log~m}{u})$.\nTherefore\n$$L(1,\\chi)=\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{\\chi(n)}{n}=\\sum_{n\\le u}\\frac{\\chi(n)}{n}+O(\\frac{\\sqrt{m}log~m}{u})$$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.5.6}", "question": "Let $D$ be a bounded open set in $\\mathbb{R}^{2}$ and let $N(x)$ denote the number of lattice points in $D$. Show that\n$$lim_{x\\rightarrow\\infty}\\frac{N(x)}{x^{2}}=vol(D).$$", "solution": "Without loss of generality, we may translate our region by a lattice point to the first quadrant. A lattice point $(u,v)\\in xD$ if and only if $(u/x,v/x)\\in D.$ This suggests we partition the plane into squares of length $1/x$ with sides parallel to the coordinate axes. This then partitions $D$ into small squares each of area $1/x^{2}$. The number of lattice points of $xD$ is then clearly the number of \"interior squares.\" For this partition of the region, we write down the lower and upper Riemann sums. Let $I_{x}$ denote the number of \"interior\" squares, and $B_{x}$ the number of \"boundary\" squares. Then, by the definition of the Riemann integral\n$$lim_{x\\rightarrow\\infty}\\frac{I_{x}}{x^{2}}=lim_{x\\rightarrow\\infty}\\frac{I_{x}+B_{x}}{x^{2}}=vol(D).$$\nOn the other hand, $I_{x}\\le N(x)\\le I_{x}+B_{x}$ so that $\\frac{I_{x}}{x^{2}}\\le vol(D)\\le\\frac{I_{x}+B_{x}}{x^{2}}$. Thus, $lim_{x\\rightarrow\\infty}\\frac{N(x)}{x^{2}}=vol(D)$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.5.7}", "question": "Let $K$ be an algebraic number field, and $C$ an ideal class of $K$. Let $N(x,C)$ be the number of nonzero ideals of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ belonging to $C$ with norm $\\le x$. Fix an integral ideal $\\mathfrak{b}$ in $C^{-1}$. Show that $N(x,C)$ is the number of nonzero principal ideals $(\\alpha)$ with $\\alpha\\in\\mathfrak{b}$ with $|N_{K}(\\alpha)|\\le xN(\\mathfrak{b})$.", "solution": "For any $\\mathfrak{a}\\in C$, $\\mathfrak{ab}=(\\alpha)$ so that $(\\alpha)\\subseteq\\mathfrak{b}$. Moreover $N_{K}(\\alpha)=N(\\mathfrak{a})N(\\mathfrak{b})$. Conversely, if $\\alpha\\in\\mathfrak{b}$, let $\\mathfrak{a}=\\mathfrak{b}^{-1}(\\alpha)$ which is an integral ideal of norm $\\le x$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.5.8}", "question": "Let $K$ be an imaginary quadratic field, $C$ an ideal class of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, and $d_{K}$ the discriminant of $K$. Prove that\n$$lim_{x\\rightarrow\\infty}\\frac{N(x,C)}{x}=\\frac{2\\pi}{w\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}},$$\nwhere $w$ is the number of roots of unity in $K$.", "solution": "By the previous exercise, $wN(x,C)$ is the number of integers $\\alpha\\in\\mathfrak{b}$ with $0<|N_{K}(\\alpha)|<x|N(\\mathfrak{b})|$ where $\\mathfrak{b}\\in C^{-1}$ is fixed. Let $\\beta_{1}$, $\\beta_{2}$ be an integral basis of $\\mathfrak{b},$ and let $\\beta_{1}^{\\prime}$, $\\beta_{2}^{\\prime}$ be the conjugates of $\\beta_{1}$, $\\beta_{2}$, respectively. Define\n$$D=\\{(u,v)\\in\\mathbb{R}^{2}:0<|u\\beta_{1}+v\\beta_{2}|^{2}<1\\}.$$\nClearly $D$ is bounded (as is easily verified). Then $wN(x,C)$ is the number of lattice points in $\\sqrt{x}D$ so that (by the penultimate exercise)\n$$lim_{x\\rightarrow\\infty}\\frac{wN(x,C)}{x}=vol(D).$$\nSet $u_{1}=Re(u\\beta_{1}+v\\beta_{2})$, $u_{2}=Im(u\\beta_{1}+v\\beta_{2})$ so that\n$$vol(D)=\\iint_{|u\\beta_{1}+v\\beta_{2}|^{2}<1}du~dv$$\n$$=\\frac{2}{N\\mathfrak{b}\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}}\\cdot\\iint_{u_{1}^{2}+u_{2}^{2}<1}du_{1}du_{2} =\\frac{2\\pi}{N\\mathfrak{b}\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}}.$$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.5.9}", "question": "Let $K$ be a real quadratic field with discriminant $d_{K}$, and fundamental unit $\\epsilon$. Let $C$ be an ideal class of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ Show that\n$$lim_{x\\rightarrow\\infty}\\frac{N(x,C)}{x}=\\frac{2~log~\\epsilon}{\\sqrt{d_{K}}}$$\nwhere $N(x,C)$ denotes the number of integral ideals of norm $\\le x$ lying in the class $C$.", "solution": "As in the previous two exercises, we fix an ideal $\\mathfrak{b}\\in C^{-1}$ and we are reduced to counting the number $(\\alpha)$, with $(N_{K}(\\alpha))\\le xN\\mathfrak{b}.$ Therefore, fix an integral basis $\\beta_{1}$, $\\beta_{2}$ of $\\mathfrak{b}$, $\\beta_{1}^{\\prime}$, $\\beta_{2}^{\\prime}$ denote the conjugates, respectively. Notice that we have infinitely many choices of $\\alpha$ since $(\\alpha)=(\\epsilon^{m}\\alpha)$ for any integer $m$. Our first step is to isolate only one generator. Since $\\alpha/\\alpha^{\\prime}$ is a unit of norm $\\pm1$, there is an integer $m$ so that $-2m~log~\\epsilon\\le log|\\frac{\\alpha}{\\alpha^{\\prime}}|<(-2m+2)log~\\epsilon.$ Thus, setting $\\omega=\\epsilon^{m}\\alpha$, we find $0\\le log|\\frac{\\omega}{|N_{K}(\\omega)^{1/2}|}|<log~\\epsilon.$\nIf $\\omega_{1}$, $\\omega_{2}$ are associated elements of $\\mathfrak{b}$ satisfying the same inequality, then the fact that $\\omega_{1}=\\eta\\omega_{2}$ for some unit $\\eta$ gives $1\\le|\\eta|<\\epsilon$. Thus, $\\eta=\\pm1$ because $\\epsilon$ is a fundamental unit. Therefore $2N(x,C)$ is the number of $\\omega\\in\\mathfrak{b}$ such that $0<|N_{K}(\\omega)|<(N\\mathfrak{b})x$, $0\\le log|\\frac{\\omega}{|N_{K}(\\omega)|^{1/2}}|<log~\\epsilon.$ Now consider\n$$D=\\{(u,v)\\in\\mathbb{R}^{2}:0<|u\\beta_{1}+v\\beta_{2}||u\\beta_{1}^{\\prime}+v\\beta_{2}^{\\prime}|<1, 0<log|\\frac{u\\beta_{1}+v\\beta_{2}}{|u\\beta_{1}+v\\beta_{2}|^{1/2}|u\\beta_{1}^{\\prime}+v\\beta_{2}^{\\prime}|^{1/2}}|<log~\\epsilon.\\}$$\nProceeding as in the previous question gives\n$$lim_{x\\rightarrow\\infty}\\frac{2N(x,C)}{x}=\\frac{4~log~\\epsilon}{\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}}.$$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.5.10}", "question": "Let $K$ be an imaginary quadratic field. Let $N(x;K)$ denote the number of integral ideals of norm $\\le x.$ Show that\n$$lim_{x\\rightarrow\\infty}\\frac{N(x;K)}{x}=\\frac{2\\pi h}{w\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}},$$\nwhere $h$ denotes the class number of $K$.", "solution": "Clearly, $N(x;K)=\\sum_{C}N(x,C)$ where the (finite) sum is over the ideal classes of $K$. Thus, $lim_{x\\rightarrow\\infty}\\frac{N(x;K)}{x}=\\sum_{C}lim_{x\\rightarrow\\infty}\\frac{N(x,C)}{x}$ and by the penultimate question, $lim_{x\\rightarrow\\infty}\\frac{N(x,C)}{x}=\\frac{2\\pi}{w\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}}.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.5.11}", "question": "Let $K$ be a real quadratic field. Let $N(x;K)$ denote the number of integral ideals of norm $\\le x$. Show that\n$$lim_{x\\rightarrow\\infty}\\frac{N(x;K)}{x}=\\frac{2h~log~\\epsilon}{\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}},$$\nwhere $h$ is the class number of $K$.", "solution": "This follows exactly as in the previous question except that we invoke the corresponding limit of $N(x,C)$ for the real quadratic case.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.5.12}", "question": "Suppose that $K$ is a quadratic field with discriminant $d_{K}$. Show that\n$$\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}(\\frac{d_{K}}{n})\\frac{1}{n}=\\begin{cases}\\frac{2\\pi h}{w\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}}&if~d_{K}<0,\\\\ \\frac{2h~log~\\epsilon}{\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}}&if~d_{K}>0,\\end{cases}$$\nwhere $h$ denotes the class number of $K$.", "solution": "By Example 10.2.9, the number of integral ideals of norm $\\le x$ is $cx+O(\\sqrt{x})$ where $c=\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}(\\frac{d_{K}}{n})\\frac{1}{n}.$ Thus, $lim_{x\\rightarrow\\infty}\\frac{N(x,K)}{x}=\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}(\\frac{d_{K}}{n})\\frac{1}{n}.$ Comparing this limit with the previous two questions gives the desired result.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.5.13}", "question": "Let $d$ be squarefree and positive. Using Dirichlet's class number formula, prove that the class number of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-d})$ is $O(\\sqrt{d}log~d)$.", "solution": "Let $D$ be the discriminant of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-d})$. By Dirichlet's class number formula,\n$\\frac{2\\pi h}{w\\sqrt{|D|}}=\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}(\\frac{D}{n})\\frac{1}{n}.$\nSince $|D|=|d|$ or $4|d|$, it suffices to prove that $\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}(\\frac{D}{n})\\frac{1}{n}=O(log~d).$\nBy a previous exercise (Exercise 10.5.5), we have for any $u\\ge1$,\n$\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}(\\frac{D}{n})\\frac{1}{n}=\\sum_{n\\le u}(\\frac{D}{n})\\frac{1}{n}+O(\\frac{\\sqrt{d}log~d}{u})$\nwhich was derived using the Pólya-Vinogradov inequality. Choosing $u=\\sqrt{d}$ and noting that $\\sum_{n\\le\\sqrt{d}}(\\frac{D}{n})\\frac{1}{n}=O(log~d),$ we obtain the result.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.5.14}", "question": "Let $d$ be squarefree and positive. Using Dirichlet's class number formula, prove that the class number $h$ of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})$ is $O(\\sqrt{d})$.", "solution": "Let $D$ be the discriminant of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})$. By Dirichlet's class number formula\n$\\frac{2h~log~\\epsilon}{\\sqrt{|D|}}=\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}(\\frac{D}{n})\\frac{1}{n},$\nwhere $\\epsilon$ is the fundamental unit of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})$. Since $\\epsilon=a+b\\sqrt{d}$ or $\\frac{a+b\\sqrt{d}}{2}$ for integers $a, b$ and $a^{2}-db^{2}=\\pm1$ or $\\pm4$ we deduce that $log~\\epsilon\\gg log~d$. Estimating the infinite series as in the previous question, the result is now immediate.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.5.15}", "question": "With $\\psi(x)$ defined (as in Chapter 1) by $\\psi(x)=\\sum_{p^{\\alpha}\\le x}log~p,$ prove that for $Re(s)>1$,\n$$-\\frac{\\zeta^{\\prime}}{\\zeta}(s)=s\\int_{1}^{\\infty}\\frac{\\psi(x)}{x^{s+1}}dx.$$", "solution": "Taking logs of the identity $\\zeta(s)=\\prod_{p}(1-\\frac{1}{p^{s}})^{-1}$ we differentiate to obtain\n$$-\\frac{\\zeta^{\\prime}}{\\zeta}(s)=\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{\\Lambda(n)}{n^{s}},$$\nwhere $\\Lambda(n)=log~p$ if $n=p^{\\alpha}$ and 0 otherwise. It is clear that $\\psi(x)=\\sum_{n\\le x}\\Lambda(n)$ and so the result now follows by Theorem 10.1.4.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 10.5.16}", "question": "If for any $\\epsilon>0$, $\\psi(x)=x+O(x^{1/2+\\epsilon})$ show that $\\zeta(s)\\ne0$ for $Re(s)>\\frac{1}{2}$", "solution": "If the given estimate holds, we obtain an analytic continuation of $-\\frac{\\zeta^{\\prime}}{\\zeta}(s)$ for $Re(s)>\\frac{1}{2}$, apart from a simple pole at $s=1$ Thus $\\zeta(s)$ has no zeros in $Re(s)>\\frac{1}{2}$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.1.1}", "question": "Let $B_x$ be the region defined in the text (counting ideals in a fixed ideal class). Show that $B_{x}$ is a bounded region in $\\mathbb{R}^{n}$.", "solution": "Since the integral basis $\\beta_{1},...,\\beta_{n}$ is linearly independent over $\\mathbb{Q}$, the discriminant $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\beta_{1},...,\\beta_{n})=[det(\\beta_{i}^{(j)})]^{2}\\ne0$. Thus the linear map $\\phi(x_{1},...,x_{n})=(\\alpha^{(1)},...,\\alpha^{(n)})$ is invertible. Let M be the largest of the values $|log|\\epsilon_{j}^{(i)}||$ for $1\\le i$, $j\\le r$. Then for each element of $B_{x}$, we have from the second relation defining $B_{x}$, $|\\alpha^{(i)}|\\le e^{rM}(N(\\mathfrak{b})x)^{1/n}$, holds for $1\\le i\\le n$. Therefore the image of $\\phi$ is a bounded set and thus the inverse image is bounded.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.1.2}", "question": "Show that $tB_{1}=B_{t^{n}}$ for any $t>0$.", "solution": "There are two conditions defining $B_{x}$. The second one involving units is invariant under the homogenous change of variables. The first inequality gets multiplied by $t^{n}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.1.3}", "question": "Show that $N(x,C)=O(x)$. Deduce that $N(x;K)=O(x).$", "solution": "We may write the $x_{i}$ in terms of the $\\alpha^{(i)}$'s by inverting the transformation matrix, as noted in Exercise 11.1.1. As the $\\alpha^{(i)}$'s are $O(x^{1/n})$ we deduce that the $x_{i}$ are $O(x^{1/n})$. The result is now immediate.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 11.1.4}", "question": "Prove Theorem 11.1.4 (Dedekind): $vol(B_{1})=\\frac{2^{r_{1}}(2\\pi)^{r_{2}}R_{K}}{\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}}.$", "solution": "Let M be the maximal value of $|log|\\epsilon_{j}^{(i)}||$ for $j=1,...,r$. We first complete the domain $B_{x}$ by adding the points of the space lying in the subspace $\\alpha^{(i)}=0$ for some i and that also satisfy the inequalities $|\\alpha^{(j)}|\\le e^{rM}(xN(\\mathfrak{b}))^{1/n}$, $j=1,2,...,n$. Since these subspaces are of lower dimension, their contribution to the volume is negligible. We denote the completed space by $B_{x}^{*}$. If we now change variables and put $x_{j}=y_{j}x^{1/n}$, we see that the volume is equal to $x\\int\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\int_{B_{1}^{*}}dy_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot dy_{n}=J$ (say). Now $B_{1}^{*}$ is the domain described by $\\alpha^{(i)}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}y_{j}\\beta_{j}^{(i)}$ ($1\\le i\\le n$) and $0<|\\alpha^{(1)}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\alpha^{(n)}|\\le N(\\mathfrak{b})$, so that there exist $c_{j}$ for $1\\le j\\le r$ satisfying $0\\le c_{j}<1$ and $log(|\\alpha^{(i)}||N(\\alpha)|^{-1/n})=\\sum_{j=1}^{r}c_{j}log|\\epsilon_{j}^{(i)}|$ ($1\\le i\\le n$) or $|\\alpha^{(i)}|\\le e^{rM}(N(\\mathfrak{b}))^{1/n}$, $1\\le i\\le n$ and at least one $\\alpha^{(i)}=0$. As noted, the region defined by these latter conditions are manifolds of lower dimension and thus make no contribution to the n-fold integral and thus, these conditions may be omitted in the evaluation of J. To evaluate the integral, we change variables: $u_{i}:=\\alpha^{(i)}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}y_{j}\\beta_{j}^{(i)}$ for $1\\le i\\le r_{1}$, and $u_{i}+u_{i+r_{2}}\\sqrt{-1}:=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}y_{j}\\beta_{j}^{(i)}$ for $r_{1}+1\\le i\\le r_{1}+r_{2}$. Thus, with our convention concerning the ordering of embeddings, $u_{i}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}y_{j}(\\frac{\\beta_{j}^{(i)}+\\beta_{j}^{(i+r_{2})}}{2})$ and $u_{i+r_{2}}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}y_{j}(\\frac{\\beta_{j}^{(i)}-\\beta_{j}^{(i+r_{2})}}{2\\sqrt{-1}})$ for $r_{1}+1\\le i\\le r_{1}+r_{2}$. The absolute value of the Jacobian for this change of variables is easily computed to be $2^{-r_{2}}N(\\mathfrak{b})\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}$. Hence, $vol(B_{1}^{*})=\\frac{2^{r_{2}}}{N(\\mathfrak{b})\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}}\\int\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\int_{\\tilde{B}_{1}^{*}}du_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot du_{n},$ where $\\tilde{B}_{1}^{*}$ is the image of $B_{1}^{*}$ under the change of variables. The variables $u_{1},...,u_{r_{1}}$ may take one of two signs and so if we insist $u_{i}\\ge0$ for $i=1,...,r_{1}$, we must multiply our volume (with this additional constraint) by a factor of $2^{r_{1}}$. We now shift to polar co-ordinates. Put $\\rho_{j}=u_{j}$ ($1\\le j\\le r_{1}$) and $\\rho_{j}cos~\\theta_{j}=u_{j}$, $\\rho_{j}sin~\\theta_{j}=u_{j+r_{2}}$ ($r_{1}+1\\le j\\le r_{1}+r_{2}$), with $0\\le\\theta_{j}<2\\pi$ and $\\rho_{j}\\ge0$. The Jacobian of this transformation is easily seen to be $\\rho_{r_{1}+1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\rho_{r_{1}+r_{2}}.$ Thus, $vol(B_{1}^{*})=\\frac{2^{r_{1}+r_{2}}(2\\pi)^{r_{2}}}{N(\\mathfrak{b})\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}}\\int\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\int_{C_{1}^{*}}\\rho_{r_{1}+1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\rho_{r_{1}+r_{2}}d\\rho_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot d\\rho_{r_{1}+r_{2}}$ where $C_{1}^{*}$ is the domain described by: $0\\le\\prod_{j=1}^{r_{1}+r_{2}}\\rho_{j}^{e_{j}}\\le N(\\mathfrak{b})$ and $log~\\rho_{i}(\\prod_{j=1}^{r}\\rho_{j}^{e_{j}})^{-1/n}=\\sum_{j=1}^{r}c_{j}log|\\epsilon_{j}^{(i)}|$ for $1\\le i\\le r_{1}+r_{2}$. (Recall that $e_{i}=1$ for $1\\le i\\le r_{1}$ and 2 otherwise.) We make (yet) another change of variables. Put $\\tau_{j}=\\rho_{j}^{e_{j}}$ ($1\\le j\\le r_{1}+r_{2}$). The Jacobian of this transformation is easily seen to be $2^{-r_{2}}\\rho_{r_{1}+1}^{-1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\rho_{r_{1}+r_{2}}^{-1}$ so that the integral becomes $\\frac{2^{r_{1}}(2\\pi)^{r_{2}}}{N(\\mathfrak{b})\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}}\\int\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\int_{D_{1}^{*}}d\\tau_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot d\\tau_{r_{1}+r_{2}}$ where the region $D_{1}^{*}$ is described by the conditions $\\tau_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\tau_{r_{1}+r_{2}}\\le N(\\mathfrak{b})$, $\\tau_{i}>0$, and $log~\\tau_{i}=\\frac{e_{i}}{n}log(\\tau_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\tau_{r_{1}+r_{2}})+e_{i}\\sum_{j=1}^{r}c_{j}log|\\epsilon_{j}^{(i)}|.$ We make one final change of variables: write the $c_{i}$ in terms of the $\\tau_{i}$ and put $u=\\tau_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\tau_{r+1}$. The Jacobian of this transformation is now seen to be $R_{K}$ and the final result is $vol(B_{1})=\\frac{2^{r_{1}}(2\\pi)^{r_{2}}R_{K}}{N(\\mathfrak{b})\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}}\\int_{0}^{N(\\mathfrak{b})}du\\int_{0}^{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\int_{0}^{1}dc_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot dc_{r}=\\frac{2^{r_{1}}(2\\pi)^{r_{2}}R_{K}}{\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}}$ which completes the proof.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.1.6}", "question": "Prove that $\\zeta(s,C)$ extends to the region $\\mathbb{R}(s)>1-\\frac{1}{n}$ except for a simple pole at $s=1$ with residue $\\frac{2^{r_{1}}(2\\pi)^{r_{2}}R_{K}}{w\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}}$. Deduce that $\\zeta_{K}(s)$ extends to $\\mathbb{R}(s)>1-\\frac{1}{n}$ except for a simple pole at $s=1$ with residue $\\rho_{K}:=\\frac{2^{r_{1}}(2\\pi)^{r_{2}}h_{K}R_{K}}{w\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}}$ where $h_{K}$ denotes the class number of K.", "solution": "If we let $\\alpha_{K}=\\rho_{K}/h_{K}$ and consider the Dirichlet series $f(s)=\\sum_{m=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{a_{m}}{m^{s}}:=\\zeta(s,C)-\\alpha_{K}\\zeta(s),$ then by Theorem 11.1.5, we have $\\sum_{m\\le x}a_{m}=O(x^{1-\\frac{1}{n}}).$ By Theorem 10.1.4, $f(s)$ converges for $\\mathbb{R}(s)>1-\\frac{1}{n}$. As $\\zeta(s)$ has a simple pole at $s=1$ with residue 1, the latter assertions are immediate.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.1.7}", "question": "Prove that there are infinitely many prime ideals in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ which are of degree 1.", "solution": "We have $log~\\zeta_{K}(s)=\\sum_{\\mathfrak{p}}\\frac{1}{N(\\mathfrak{p})^{s}}+\\sum_{n\\ge2,\\mathfrak{p}}\\frac{1}{nN(\\mathfrak{p})^{ns}}$. The second sum is easily seen to converge for $\\mathbb{R}(s)>1/2$. The first sum can be separated into two parts, one over primes of first degree and the other over primes of degree $\\ge2$. Again, the second sum converges for $\\mathfrak{R}(s)>1/2$. If the first sum consisted of only finitely many terms, the right hand side would tend to a finite limit as $s\\rightarrow1^{+}$ which is not the case as the Dedekind zeta function has a simple pole at $s=1$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.1.8}", "question": "Prove that the number of prime ideals of degree $\\ge2$ and with norm $\\le x$ is $O(x^{1/2}log~x)$.", "solution": "If $\\mathfrak{p}$ is a prime ideal of degree $r\\ge2$ then $N(\\mathfrak{p})=p^{r}\\le x$ implies $r\\le(log~x)/log~2$ and $p\\le x^{1/2}$. For each prime, there are a bounded number of prime ideals in K above p. Thus, the final estimate is obtained by counting the number of possible pairs $(p,r)$ and this is $O(x^{1/2}log~x)$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.1.9}", "question": "Let $\\mu$ be defined on integral ideals $\\mathfrak{a}$ of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ as follows. $\\mu(\\mathcal{O}_{K})=1$, and if $\\mathfrak{a}$ is divisible by the square of a prime ideal, we set $\\mu(\\mathfrak{a})=0$. Otherwise, we let $\\mu(\\mathfrak{a})=(-1)^{k}$ when $\\mathfrak{a}$ is the product of k distinct prime ideals. Show that $\\sum_{\\mathfrak{b}|\\mathfrak{a}}\\mu(\\mathfrak{b})=0$ unless $\\mathfrak{a}=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "solution": "Clearly, the function $f(\\mathfrak{a})=\\sum_{\\mathfrak{b}|\\mathfrak{a}}\\mu(\\mathfrak{b})$ is multiplicative and so, it suffices to evaluate it on prime ideals. But this is clearly zero.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.1.10}", "question": "Prove that the number of ideals of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ of odd norm $\\le x$ is $\\rho_{K}x\\prod_{\\mathfrak{p}|2}(1-\\frac{1}{N(\\mathfrak{p})})+O(x^{1-\\frac{1}{n}}),$ where the product is over prime ideals of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ dividing $2\\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "solution": "By the previous exercise, the number of such ideals is $\\sum_{N(\\mathfrak{a})\\le x}\\sum_{\\mathfrak{b}|(\\mathfrak{a},2)}\\mu(\\mathfrak{b})$ since an ideal has odd norm if and only if it has no prime ideal divisor above 2. Interchanging summation and using Theorem 11.1.5, we obtain the result.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.1.11}", "question": "Let $A(x)$ be the number of ideals of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ of even norm $\\le x$ and $B(x)$ of odd norm $\\le x$. Show that $lim_{x\\rightarrow\\infty}\\frac{A(x)}{B(x)}=1$ if and only if $K=\\mathbb{Q}$ or K is a quadratic field in which 2 ramifies.", "solution": "From the previous exercise, we see that $B(x)=\\prod_{\\mathfrak{p}|2}(1-\\frac{1}{N(\\mathfrak{p})})\\rho_{K}x+O(x^{1-\\frac{1}{n}}).$ We see that $A(x)\\sim B(x)$ if and only if $A(x)+B(x)\\sim2B(x)$. That is, if and only if $\\frac{1}{2}=\\prod_{\\mathfrak{p}|2}(1-\\frac{1}{N(\\mathfrak{p})})$. Let $\\mathfrak{p}_{1},...,\\mathfrak{p}_{t}$ be the prime ideals above 2 with norms $2^{m_{1}},...,2^{m_{t}}$ respectively. The above equation implies $\\frac{1}{2}=\\prod_{i=1}^{t}(\\frac{2^{m_{i}}-1}{2^{m_{i}}})$. In other words, we have $2^{m_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+m_{t}-1}=\\prod_{i=1}^{t}(2^{m_{i}}-1).$ The right hand side is a product of odd numbers and so the only way the left hand side can be odd is if $m_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+m_{t}=1$ which means that there is only one prime ideal above 2 and it has norm 2. This can only happen if $K=\\mathbb{Q}$ or if K is a quadratic field in which 2 ramifies.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.1.12}", "question": "With notation as in the discussion preceding Theorem 11.1.4, let $V_{x}$ denote the set of n-tuples $(x_{1},...,x_{n})$ satisfying $|\\alpha^{(1)}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\alpha^{(n)}|\\le xN(\\mathfrak{b})$. Let $t=x^{1/n}$. Show that there is a $\\delta>0$ (independent of x) such that for each lattice point P contained in $V_{(t-\\delta)^{n}}$, all the points contained in the translate of the standard unit cube by P belong to $V_{x}$.", "solution": "We fix $\\delta>0$ and choose it appropriately later. We may write the norm form $\\alpha^{(1)}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\alpha^{(n)}$ as $\\sum_{i_{1},...,i_{n}}a_{i_{1},...,i_{n}}x_{1}^{i_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot x_{n}^{i_{n}}$ where the summation is over all positive integers $i_{1},...,i_{n}$ such that $i_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+i_{n}=n$ and the $a_{i_{1},...,i_{n}}$ are rational integers. If $P=(u_{1},...,u_{n})$, then any point contained in the translate of the standard unit cube by P is of the form $(u_{1}+t_{1},...,u_{n}+t_{n})$ with $t_{i}$ bounded by 1. Thus, by the solution of Exercise 11.1.1, we deduce that the norm of any such point is $\\sum_{i_{1},...,i_{n}}a_{i_{1},...,i_{n}}u_{1}^{i_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot u_{n}^{i_{n}}+O(x^{\\frac{n-1}{n}}).$ This has absolute norm $\\le(t-\\delta)^{n}+O(x^{\\frac{n-1}{n}})\\le x-n\\delta x^{\\frac{n-1}{n}}+O(x^{\\frac{n-1}{n}})\\le x$ if we choose $\\delta$ sufficiently large so that the negative sign dominates.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.2.1}", "question": "Show that $L(s,\\chi)$ converges absolutely for $\\mathfrak{R}(s)>1$ and that $L(s,\\chi)=\\prod_{\\mathfrak{p}}(1-\\frac{\\chi(\\mathfrak{p})}{N(\\mathfrak{p})^{s}})^{-1}$ in this region. Deduce that $L(s,\\chi)\\ne0$ for $\\mathfrak{R}(s)>1$.", "solution": "We have by multiplicativity of $\\chi$, $L(s,\\chi)=\\prod_{\\mathfrak{p}}(1-\\frac{\\chi(\\mathfrak{p})}{N(\\mathfrak{p})^{s}})^{-1}$ and the product converges absolutely for $\\mathfrak{R}(s)>1$ if and only if $\\sum_{\\mathfrak{p}}\\frac{1}{N(\\mathfrak{p})^{s}}$ converges in this region, which is certainly the case as there are only a bounded number of prime ideals above a given prime p. The non-vanishing is also clear.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.2.2}", "question": "If $\\chi$ is not the trivial character, show that $\\sum_{C}\\chi(C)=0$ where the summation is over the ideal classes C of H.", "solution": "If $\\chi$ is not the trivial character, there is a $C_{0}$ such that $\\chi(C_{0})\\ne 1$. Thus, $\\sum_{C}\\chi(CC_{0})=\\chi(C_{0})\\sum_{C}\\chi(C)$, where we have used the fact that as C runs over elements of the ideal class group, so does $CC_{0}$. The result is now immediate.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.2.3}", "question": "If $C_{1}$ and $C_{2}$ are distinct ideal classes, show that $\\sum_{\\chi}\\overline{\\chi(C_{1})}\\chi(C_{2})=0$. If $C_{1}=C_{2}$, show that the sum is $h_{K}$.", "solution": "If $C_{1}=C_{2}$, the result is clear. We consider the sum $\\sum_{\\chi}\\chi(A)$ for $A\\ne1$. We can then take a non-trivial character of the subgroup generated by A and extend this character to the full ideal class group in the usual way. Then, $\\sum_{\\chi}(\\chi\\psi)(A)=\\psi(A)\\sum_{\\chi}\\chi(A)$ and as before, the result is now evident.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 11.2.4}", "question": "Let n be the degree of $K/\\mathbb{Q}.$ If $\\chi\\ne\\chi_{0}$ then $L(s,\\chi)$ extends analytically to $\\mathfrak{R}(s)>1-\\frac{1}{n}$.", "solution": "By Theorem 11.1.5, we have $\\sum_{C}\\chi(C)\\sum_{\\mathfrak{a}\\in C,N(\\mathfrak{a})\\le x}1=\\sum_{C}\\chi(C)N(x,C)=O(x^{1-\\frac{1}{n}});$ since (by Exercise 11.2.2) $\\sum_{C}\\chi(C)=0$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.2.5}", "question": "Let C be an ideal class of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. For $\\mathfrak{R}(s)>1$ show that $\\sum_{\\chi}\\overline{\\chi}(C)log~L(s,\\chi)=h_{K}\\sum_{\\mathfrak{p}^{m}\\in C}\\frac{1}{mN(\\mathfrak{p})^{ms}}$ where the first summation is over the characters of the ideal class group and the second summation is over all prime ideals of $\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$ and natural numbers m such that $\\mathfrak{p}^{m}\\in C.$", "solution": "In the left hand side, we insert the series for $log~L(s,\\chi).$ By interchanging the summation and using the orthogonality relations established in the Exercise 11.2.3, we obtain the desired result.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.2.6}", "question": "Show that $\\sum_{n\\ge2,\\mathfrak{p}^{m}\\in C}\\frac{1}{mN(\\mathfrak{p})^{ms}}$ converges for $\\mathbb{R}(s)>1/2$.", "solution": "As noted earlier, the number of prime ideals above a fixed prime p is at most the degree of the number field. Thus, the result is clear from the fact that $\\sum_{m\\ge2,p}\\frac{1}{mp^{ms}}$ converges for $\\mathfrak{R}(s)>1/2$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.2.7}", "question": "If $\\chi^{2}\\ne\\chi_{0}$ show that $L(1,\\chi)\\ne0.$", "solution": "We use the classical inequality $3+4~cos~\\theta+cos~2\\theta\\ge0$ as follows. We write $\\chi(\\mathfrak{p})=e^{i\\theta_{p}}$ so that for real $\\sigma>1$, $\\mathfrak{R}(3~log~\\zeta_{K}(\\sigma)+4~log~L(\\sigma,\\chi)+log~L(\\sigma,\\chi^{2})) =\\sum_{m,\\mathfrak{p}}\\frac{1}{mN(\\mathfrak{p})^{\\sigma m}}(3+4~cos~\\theta_{p}+cos~2\\theta_{p})\\ge0.$ Hence, $|\\zeta_{K}(\\sigma)^{3}L(\\sigma,\\chi)^{4}L(\\sigma,\\chi^{2})|\\ge1$. If $L(1,\\chi)=0$ the left hand side of this inequality tends to zero as $\\sigma\\rightarrow1^{+}$, which is a contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.2.8}", "question": "Let C be a fixed ideal class in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Show that the set of prime $\\mathfrak{p}\\in C$ has Dirichlet density $1/h_{K}$.", "solution": "We have by the orthogonality relation, $\\sum_{\\chi}\\overline{\\chi(C)}log~L(s,\\chi)=h_{K}\\sum_{\\mathfrak{p}\\in C}\\frac{1}{N(\\mathfrak{p})^{s}}+O(1)$ as $s\\rightarrow1^{+}$. Since $L(1,\\chi)\\ne0$ we may take limits of the left hand side as $s\\rightarrow1^{+}$ and obtain a bounded quantity from the non-trivial characters. Since $L(s,\\chi_{0})=\\zeta_{K}(s)$, we deduce immediately that $lim_{s\\rightarrow1^{+}}\\frac{\\sum_{\\mathfrak{p}\\in C}1/N(\\mathfrak{p})^{s}}{log~\\zeta_{K}(s)}=\\frac{1}{h_{K}}$ as desired.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.2.9}", "question": "Let m be a natural number and $(a,m)=1$. Show that the set of primes $p\\equiv a(mod~m)$ has Dirichlet density $1/\\phi(m)$.", "solution": "This is immediate from Exercise 10.3.7.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.2.10}", "question": "Show that the set of primes p which can be written as $a^{2}+5b^{2}$ has Dirichlet density $1/4.$", "solution": "We have already seen that the class number of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-5})$ is 2. The set of prime ideals lying in the principal class are of the form $(a+b\\sqrt{-5})$ and have norm $a^{2}+5b^{2}$. By Hecke's theorem, the Dirichlet density of these prime ideals is $1/2$ and taking into account that there are two ideals of norm p in the principal class gives us the final density of $1/4.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.2.11}", "question": "Show that if $K=\\mathbb{Q}$, the principal ray class group mod m is isomorphic to $(\\mathbb{Z}/m\\mathbb{Z})^{*}$.", "solution": "The elements of the principal ray class group are the ideals (a) modulo m with a totally positive generator and $(\\alpha,m)=1.$ The result is now clear.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.3.1}", "question": "Show that the action of the Galois group on the set of prime ideals lying above a fixed prime p of k is a transitive action.", "solution": "Suppose not. Take a prime ideal which is not in the Galois orbit of $\\mathfrak{p}_{i}$ (say) lying above the prime ideal p. By the Chinese remainder theorem (Theorem 5.3.13), we may find an element $x\\in\\mathfrak{p}$ and $x-1\\in\\sigma(\\mathfrak{p}_{i})$ for all $\\sigma$ in the Galois group. But then, $N_{K/k}(x)$ is an integer of $\\mathcal{O}_{k}$ which on one hand is divisible by $\\mathfrak{p}$ and on the other coprime to p, a contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.3.4}", "question": "By taking $k=\\mathbb{Q}$ and $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m})$, deduce from Chebotarev's theorem the infinitude of primes in a given arithmetic progression a (mod m) with $(a,m)=1$.", "solution": "The Galois group consists of automorphisms $\\tau_{a}$ satisfying $\\tau_{a}(\\zeta_{m})=\\zeta_{m}^{a}$. Comparing this with the action of the Frobenius automorphism of p, we see that $\\sigma_{p}=\\tau_{a}$ where $p\\equiv a$ (mod p). By Chebotarev, the Dirichlet density of primes p for which $\\sigma_{p}=\\tau_{a}$ is $1/\\phi(m)$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.3.5}", "question": "If $k=\\mathbb{Q}$ and $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{D})$, deduce from Chebotarev's theorem that the set of primes p with Legendre symbol $(D/p)=1$ is of Dirichlet density $1/2$.", "solution": "By Theorem 7.4.2, we see that these are precisely the set of primes which split completely in K and by Chebotarev, the density of such primes is $1/2$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.3.6}", "question": "If $f(x)\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x]$ is an irreducible normal polynomial of degree n (that is, its splitting field has degree n over Q), then show that the set of primes p for which $f(x)\\equiv0$ (mod p) has a solution is of Dirichlet density $1/n$.", "solution": "By Theorem 5.5.1 and Exercise 5.5.2, we see that the set of primes p for which $f(x)\\equiv0$ (mod p) has a solution coincides with the set of primes p which split completely in the field obtained by adjoining a root of f. By our assumption, this is a Galois extension of degree n and to say p splits completely is equivalent to saying that $\\sigma_{p}=1.$ By Chebotarev, the Dirichlet density of such primes is $1/n.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.3.7}", "question": "If $f(x)\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x]$ is an irreducible polynomial of degree $n>1$, show that the set of primes p for which $f(x)\\equiv0$ (mod p) has a solution has Dirichlet density < 1.", "solution": "Let K be the splitting field of f over with Galois group G. Let H be the subgroup corresponding to the field obtained by adjoining a root of f to Q. It is not difficult to see that $f(x)\\equiv0$ (mod p) has a solution if and only if the Artin symbol $\\sigma_{p}$ lies in some conjugate of H. This is a set stable under conjugation. If we take into account that the identity element is common to all the conjugate subgroups of H, we obtain $|\\cup_{g\\in G}gHg^{-1}|\\le[G:H](|H|-1)+1=|G|+1-[G:H]<|G|$ if $[G:H]=n>1$, which is the case.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.3.8}", "question": "Let q be prime. Show that the set of primes p for which $p\\equiv1$ (mod q) and $2^{\\frac{p-1}{q}}\\equiv1(mod~p)$ has Dirichlet density $1/q(q-1)$.", "solution": "The second condition happens if and only if $x^{q}\\equiv2$ (mod p) has a solution and together with $p\\equiv1$ (mod p), the conditions are equivalent to saying p splits completely in the field $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{q},2^{1/q})$. As this field has degree $q(q-1)$, the result now follows from Chebotarev's theorem.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.3.9}", "question": "If a natural number n is a square mod p for a set of primes p which has Dirichlet density 1, show that n must be a square.", "solution": "If n is not a square, the field $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{n})$ is quadratic over and by Chebotarev, the density of primes for which n is not a square is $1/2$. (This shows that we can assert the conclusion of the theorem if the set of primes p for which n is a square has density $>1/2$.)", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.4.1}", "question": "Let G be a finite group and for each subgroup H of G and each irreducible character $\\psi$ of H define $a_{H}(\\psi,\\chi)$ by $Ind_{H}^{G}\\psi=\\sum_{\\chi}a_{H}(\\psi,\\chi)\\chi$ where the summation is over irreducible characters $\\chi$ of G. For each $\\chi$, let $A_{\\chi}$ be the vector $(a_{H}(\\psi,\\chi))$ as H varies over all cyclic subgroups of G and $\\psi$ varies over all irreducible characters of H. Show that the $A_{\\chi}$ are linearly independent over Q.", "solution": "If $\\sum_{\\chi}c_{\\chi}A_{\\chi}=0$ for some integers $c_{\\chi}$, then by Frobenius reciprocity, the character $\\phi=\\sum_{\\chi}c_{\\chi}\\chi$ restricts to the zero character on every cyclic subgroup. By the linear independence of characters (or equivalently, by the orthogonality relations), each $c_{\\chi}$ is equal to zero.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.4.2}", "question": "Let G be a finite group with t irreducible characters. By the previous exercise, choose a set of cyclic subgroups $H_{i}$ and characters $\\psi_{i}$ of $H_{i}$ so that the $t\\times t$ matrix $(a_{H_{i}}(\\psi_{i},\\chi))$ is non-singular. By inverting this matrix, show that any character $\\chi$ of G can be written as a rational linear combination of characters of the form $Ind_{H_{i}}^{G}\\psi_{i}$ with $H_{i}$ cyclic and $\\psi_{i}$ one-dimensional.", "solution": "Since the row rank of a matrix is equal to the column rank, it is clear that we can choose a set of such $H_{i}$ and $\\psi_{i}$'s. Thus, $Ind_{H_{i}}^{G}\\psi_{i}=\\sum_{\\chi}a_{H_{i}}(\\psi_{i},\\chi)\\chi$. Moreover, $a_{H}(\\psi,\\chi)=(Ind_{H}^{G}\\psi,\\chi)$ are all non-negative integers. Thus, the inverse matrix consists of rational entries.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.4.3}", "question": "Deduce from the previous exercise that some positive integer power of the Artin L-function $L(s,\\chi;K/k)$ attached to an irreducible character $\\chi$ admits a meromorphic continuation to $\\mathfrak{R}(s)=1$.", "solution": "By the previous exercise, we may write $L(s,\\chi;K/k)$ as a product of functions of the form $L(s,\\psi_{i},K/K^{H_{i}})^{m_{i}}$ with $m_{i}$ rational numbers. By the Artin reciprocity law, each $L(s,\\psi_{i},K/K^{H_{i}})$ coincides with $L(s,\\chi_{i})$ with $\\chi_{i}$ a Hecke character of $K^{H_{i}}$. As $L(s,\\chi_{i})$ has a meromorphic continuation to $\\mathfrak{R}(s)=1$, the result follows.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.4.4}", "question": "If $K/k$ is a finite Galois extension of algebraic number fields with group G, show that $\\zeta_{K}(s)=\\prod_{\\chi}L(s,\\chi;K/k)^{\\chi(1)},$ where the product is over all irreducible characters x of G.", "solution": "Since the right hand side represents the L-function attached to the regular representation, which is $Ind_{1}^{G}1$, we have that it is equal to $L(s,1,K/K)=\\zeta_{K}(s)$, by the invariance property under induction of Artin L-series.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.4.5}", "question": "Fix a complex number $s_{0}\\in\\mathbb{C}$ with $\\mathfrak{R}(s_{0})\\ge1$ and any finite Galois extension $K/k$ with Galois group G. For each subgroup H of G define the Heilbronn character $\\theta_{H}$ by $\\theta_{H}(g)=\\sum_{\\chi}n(H,\\chi)\\chi(g)$ where the summation is over all irreducible characters $\\chi$ of H and $n(H,\\chi)$ is the order of the pole of $L(s,\\chi;K/K^{H})$ at $s=s_{0}$. Show that $\\theta_{G}|_{H}=\\theta_{H}$.", "solution": "We have $\\theta_{G}|_{H}=\\sum_{\\chi}n(G,\\chi)\\chi|_{H}.$ But $\\chi|_{H}=\\sum_{\\psi}(\\chi|_{H},\\psi)\\psi$ where the sum is over irreducible characters of H. Thus, $\\theta_{G}|_{H}=\\sum_{\\psi}(\\sum_{\\chi}n(G,\\chi)(\\chi|_{H},\\psi))\\psi.$ By Frobenius reciprocity, $(\\chi|_{H},\\psi)=(\\chi,Ind_{H}^{G}\\psi)$ so that the inner sum is $\\sum_{\\chi}n(G,\\chi)(\\chi,Ind_{H}^{G}\\psi).$ This is equal to $n(H,\\psi)$ since $L(s,\\psi,K/K^{H})=L(s,Ind_{H}^{G}\\psi,K/k)=\\prod_{\\chi}L(s,\\chi,K/k)^{(\\chi,Ind_{H}^{G}\\psi)}.$ Thus, $\\theta_{G}|_{H}=\\sum_{\\psi}n(H,\\psi)\\psi=\\theta_{H}.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.4.6}", "question": "Show that $\\theta_{G}(1)$ equals the order at $s=s_{0}$ of the Dedekind zeta function $\\zeta_{K}(s)$.", "solution": "We have $\\theta_{G}(1)=\\sum_{\\chi}n(G,\\chi)\\chi(1)$ which by Exercise 11.4.4 is the order of $\\zeta_{K}(s)$ at $s=s_{0}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.4.7}", "question": "Show that $\\sum_{\\chi}n(G,\\chi)^{2}\\le(ord_{s=s_{0}}\\zeta_{K}(s))^{2}$.", "solution": "We compute $(\\theta_{G},\\theta_{G})$ using the orthogonality relations to obtain $\\sum_{\\chi}n(G,\\chi)^{2}.$ On the other hand, $(\\theta_{G},\\theta_{G})=\\frac{1}{|G|}\\sum_{g\\in G}|\\theta_{G}(g)|^{2}.$ By Exercise 11.4.5, $\\theta_{G}(g)=\\theta_{\\langle g\\rangle}(g)$. But if H is abelian, $n(H,\\psi)\\ge0$ by Artin's reciprocity law and so for $h\\in H$, $|\\theta_{H}(h)|\\le\\sum_{\\psi}n(H,\\psi)|\\psi(h)|.$ Thus, $|\\theta_{H}(h)|\\le\\sum_{\\psi}n(H,\\psi)=\\theta_{H}(1);$ which by Exercise 11.4.6 is the order of the Dedekind zeta function $\\zeta_{K}(s)$ at $s=s_{0}$. The result is now immediate.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.4.8}", "question": "For any irreducible non-trivial character $\\chi,$ deduce that $L(s,\\chi;K/k)$ admits an analytic continuation to $s=1$ and that $L(1,\\chi;K/k)\\ne0$.", "solution": "Since the Dedekind zeta function has a simple pole at $s=1.$ we see that the previous exercise applied to the point $s_{0}=1$ implies $\\sum_{\\chi\\ne1}n(G,\\chi)^{2}\\le0$ because $n(G,1)=1$ Hence, $n(G,\\chi)=0$ for any $\\chi\\ne1$ By Exercise 11.4.3 we are done.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.4.9}", "question": "Fix a conjugacy class C in $G=Gal(K/k)$ and choose $g_{C}\\in C$. Show that $\\sum_{m,\\mathfrak{p},\\sigma_{\\mathfrak{p}}^{m}\\in C}\\frac{1}{N(\\mathfrak{p})^{ms}}=\\frac{|C|}{|G|}\\sum_{\\chi}\\overline{\\chi(g_{C})}log~L(s,\\chi;K/k)$ .", "solution": "This is an immediate consequence of the orthogonality relations.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.4.10}", "question": "Show that $lim_{s\\rightarrow1^{+}}\\frac{\\sum_{\\mathfrak{p},\\sigma_{\\mathfrak{p}}\\in C}1/N(\\mathfrak{p})^{s}}{log~\\zeta_{k}(s)}=\\frac{|C|}{|G|}$ which is Chebotarev's theorem.", "solution": "We take the limit as $s\\rightarrow1^{+}$ in both sides of the equation of the previous exercise. Observe that by Exercise 11.4.8, the limit as $s\\rightarrow1^{+}$ of $log~L(s,\\chi;K/k)$ for $\\chi\\ne1$ is finite. Since $L(s,1;K/k)=\\zeta_{k}(s)$ the result is now immediate.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.4.12}", "question": "Let $K/k$ be a finite Galois extension of algebraic number fields. If $\\zeta_{K}(s)$ has a simple zero at $s=s_{0}$, then $L(s,\\chi;K/k)$ is analytic at $s=s_{0}$ for every irreducible character x of $Gal(K/k)$.", "solution": "If $\\zeta_{K}(s)$ has a simple zero at $s=s_{0}$, then $\\sum_{\\chi}n(G,\\chi)^{2}\\le1.$ By the meromorphy of Artin L-series, we have that each $n(G,\\chi)$ is an integer. The inequality implies that for at most one x, we have $|n(G,\\chi)|=1$. If x is non-abelian, then the factorization of $\\zeta_{K}(s)$ as in Exercise 11.4.4 gives a contradiction for the corresponding L-function introduces a pole or zero of order greater than 1. Hence x is abelian, but in this case the result is known by Artin reciprocity and Hecke's theorem.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.4.13}", "question": "For any irreducible character x of $Gal(K/k)$, show that $L(s,\\chi,K/k)\\zeta_{K}(s)$ is analytic for $s\\ne1$.", "solution": "This is immediate from the inequality $|n(G,\\chi)|\\le ord_{s=s_{0}}\\zeta_{K}(s)$ for $s_{0}\\ne1$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 11.4.14}", "question": "If $K/k$ is solvable, show that $\\sum_{\\chi\\ne1}n(G,\\chi)^{2}\\le(ord_{s=s_{0}}\\zeta_{K}(s)/\\zeta_{k}(s))^{2}$.", "solution": "Let $f=\\theta_{G}-n(G,1)1$ and note that $(f,f)=\\sum_{\\chi\\ne1}n(G,\\chi)^{2}.$ Now by Exercise 11.4.5 $f(g)=\\theta_{\\langle g\\rangle}(g)-n(G,1)=n(\\langle g\\rangle,1)-n(G,1)+\\sum_{\\psi\\ne1}n(\\langle g\\rangle,\\psi)\\psi(g).$ The subfield fixed by $\\langle g\\rangle$ is a subfield of K and we know Dedekind's conjecture for this extension. Thus, $n(\\langle g\\rangle,1)-n(G,1)\\ge0.$ Therefore, $|f(g)|\\le n(\\langle g\\rangle,1)-n(G,1)+\\sum_{\\psi\\ne1}n(\\langle g\\rangle,\\psi)=ord_{s=s_{0}}(\\zeta_{K}(s)/\\zeta_{k}(s)),$ from which the inequality follows.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Example 2.1.1", "question": "Let $R$ be an integral domain. Suppose there is a map $n:R\\rightarrow\\mathbb{N}$ such that:\n(i) $n(ab) = n(a)n(b)$ for all $a, b\\in R$; and\n(ii) $n(a)=1$ if and only if $a$ is a unit.\nWe call such a map a norm map, with $n(a)$ the norm of $a$. Show that every element of $R$ can be written as a product of irreducible elements.", "solution": "Suppose $b$ is an element of $R$. We proceed by induction on the norm of $b$.\nIf $b$ is irreducible, then we have nothing to prove, so assume that $b$ is an element of $R$ which is not irreducible. Then we can write $b=ac$ where neither $a$ nor $c$ is a unit. By condition (i),\n$$n(b)=n(ac)=n(a)n(c)$$\nand since $a, c$ are not units, then by condition (ii), $n(a)<n(b)$ and $n(c)<n(b)$.\nIf $a, c$ are irreducible, then we are finished. If not, their norms are smaller than the norm of $b$, and so by induction we can write them as products of irreducibles, thus finding an irreducible decomposition of $b$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 2.1.6", "question": "Show that if $R$ is a principal ideal domain, then $R$ is a unique factorization domain.", "solution": "Let $S$ be the set of elements of $R$ that cannot be written as a product of irreducibles. If $S$ is nonempty, take $a_{1}\\in S.$ Then $a_{1}$ is not irreducible, so we can write $a_{1}=a_{2}b_{2}$ where $a_{2}$, $b_{2}$ are not units. Then $(a_{1})\\subsetneq(a_{2})$ and $(a_{1})\\subsetneq(b_{2})$. If both $a_{2}$, $b_{2}\\notin S$, then we can write $a_{1}$ as a product of irreducibles, so we assume that $a_{2}\\in S$. We can inductively proceed until we arrive at an infinite chain of ideals,\n$$(a_{1})\\subsetneq(a_{2})\\subsetneq(a_{3})\\subsetneq\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\subsetneq(a_{n})\\subsetneq\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot$$\nNow consider $I=\\bigcup_{i=1}^{\\infty}(a_{i})$. This is an ideal of $R$, and because $R$ is a principal ideal domain, $I=(\\alpha)$ for some $\\alpha\\in R.$ Since $\\alpha\\in I$, $\\alpha\\in(a_{n})$ for some $n$, but then $(a_{n})=(a_{n+1})$. From this contradiction, we conclude that the set $S$ must be empty, so we know that if $R$ is a principal ideal domain, every element of $R$ satisfies the first condition for a unique factorization domain.\n\nNext we would like to show that if we have an irreducible element $\\pi$, and $\\pi|ab$ for $a, b\\in R,$ then $\\pi|a$ or $\\pi|b$. If $\\pi \\nmid a$, then the ideal $(a,\\pi)=R$, so there exist $x, y$ such that\n$$ax+\\pi y=1$$\n$$abx+\\pi by=b.$$\nSince $\\pi | abx$ and $\\pi|\\pi by$ then $\\pi|b,$ as desired. By Exercise 2.1.4, we have shown that $R$ is a unique factorization domain.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 2.1.7", "question": "If $R$ is a domain with a map $\\phi:R\\rightarrow\\mathbb{N}$, and given $a,b\\in R$, there exist $q, r\\in R$ such that $a=bq+r$ with $r=0$ or $\\phi(r)<\\phi(b)$, we call $R$ a Euclidean domain. Prove that if a ring $R$ is Euclidean, it is a principal ideal domain.", "solution": "Given an ideal $I\\subseteq R$ take an element $a$ of $I$ such that $\\phi(a)$ is minimal among elements of $I$. Then given $b\\in I$, we can find $q,r\\in R$ such that $b=qa+r$ where $r=0$ or $\\phi(r)<\\phi(a)$. But then $r=b-qa$, and so $r\\in I$ and $\\phi(a)$ is minimal among the norms of elements of $I$. So $r=0$, and given any element $b$ of $I$, $b=qa$ for some $q\\in R.$ Therefore $a$ is a generator for $I$, and $R$ is a principal ideal domain.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 2.1.9 (Gauss' Lemma)", "question": "If $R$ is a unique factorization domain, and $f(x)\\in R[x]$, define the content of $f$ to be the gcd of the coefficients of $f$, denoted by $\\mathcal{C}(f)$. Prove that for $f(x)$, $g(x)\\in R[x]$, $\\mathcal{C}(fg)=\\mathcal{C}(f)\\mathcal{C}(g)$.", "solution": "Consider two polynomials $f,g\\in R[x]$, with $\\mathcal{C}(f)=c$ and $\\mathcal{C}(g)=d.$ Then we can write\n$$f(x)=ca_{0}+ca_{1}x+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+ca_{n}x^{n}$$\nand\n$$g(x)=db_{0}+db_{1}x+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+db_{m}x^{m}$$\nwhere $c, d, a_i, b_{j}\\in R$, $a_n, b_{m}\\ne0$. We define a primitive polynomial to be a polynomial $f$ such that $\\mathcal{C}(f)=1$. Then $f=cf^{*}$ where $f^{*}=a_{0}+a_{1}x+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{n}x^{n}$, a primitive polynomial, and $g=dg^{*}$, with $g^{*}$ a primitive polynomial. Since $fg=cf^{*}dg^{*}=cd(f^{*}g^{*})$, it will suffice to prove that the product of two primitive polynomials is again primitive.\n\nLet\n$$f^{*}g^{*}=k_{0}+k_{1}x+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+k_{m+n}x^{m+n}$$\nand assume that this polynomial is not primitive. Then all the coefficients $k_{i}$ are divisible by some $\\pi\\in R$ with $\\pi$ irreducible. Since $f^{*}$ and $g^{*}$ are primitive, we know that there is at least one coefficient in each of $f^{*}$ and $g^{*}$ that is not divisible by $\\pi$. We let $a_{i}$ and $b_{j}$ be the first such coefficients in $f^{*}$ and $g^{*}$, respectively. Now,\n$$k_{i+j}=(a_{0}b_{i+j}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{i-1}b_{j+1})+a_{i}b_{j}+(a_{i+1}b_{j-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{i+j}b_{0}).$$\nWe know that $k_{i+j},a_{0},a_{1},...,a_{i-1},b_{0},b_{1},...,b_{j-1}$ are all divisible by $\\pi$, so $a_{i}b_{j}$ must also be divisible by $\\pi$. Since $\\pi$ is irreducible, then $\\pi|a_{i}$ or $\\pi|b_{j}$, but we chose these elements specifically because they were not divisible by $\\pi$. This contradiction proves that our polynomial $f^{*}g^{*}$ must be primitive. Then $fg=c~df^{*}g^{*}$ where $f^{*}g^{*}$ is a primitive polynomial, thus proving that $\\mathcal{C}(fg)=cd=\\mathcal{C}(f)\\mathcal{C}(g)$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 2.1.10", "question": "Show that if $R$ is a unique factorization domain, then $R[x]$ is a unique factorization domain.", "solution": "Let $k$ be the fraction field of $R$. Let us examine the polynomial ring $k[x]$. We know that $k[x]$ is a Euclidean domain, and thus a unique factorization domain.\n\nFirst notice that given any nonzero polynomial $f(x)\\in k[x]$, we can write this polynomial uniquely (up to multiplication by a unit) as $f(x)=cf^{*}(x)$, where $f^{*}(x)\\in R[x]$ and $f^{*}(x)$ is primitive. We do this by first finding a common denominator for all the coefficients of $f$ and factoring this out. If we denote this constant by $\\beta$, then we can write $f=f^{\\prime}/\\beta$, where $f^{\\prime}\\in R[x]$. We then find the content of $f^{\\prime}$ (which we will denote by $\\alpha$), and factor this out as well. We let $\\alpha/\\beta=c$ and write $f=cf^{*}$, noting that $f^{*}$ is primitive.\n\nWe must prove the uniqueness of this expression of $f$. If $f(x)=cf^{*}(x)=df^{\\prime}(x)$ with both $f^{*}(x)$ and $f^{\\prime}(x)$ primitive, then we can write $f^{\\prime}(x)=(c/d)f^{*}(x)=(a/b)f^{*}(x)$ where $gcd(a,b)=1$. Since the coefficients of $f^{\\prime}(x)$ are elements of $R$, then $b|a\\gamma_{i}$ for all $i$, where $\\gamma_{i}$ are the coefficients of $f^{*}$. But since $gcd(a,b)=1$, then $b|\\gamma_{i}$ for all $i$. Since $f^{*}$ is a primitive polynomial, then $b$ must be a unit of $R$. Similarly, we can write $f^{*}(x)=(b/a)f^{\\prime}(x)$, and by the same argument as above, $a$ must be a unit as well. This shows that $f^{*}(x)\\sim f^{\\prime}(x)$.\n\nLet us suppose that we have a polynomial $f(x)\\in R[x]$. Then we can factor this polynomial as $f(x)=g(x)h(x)$, with $g(x),h(x)\\in k[x]$ (because $k[x]$ is a unique factorization domain). We can also write $cf^{*}(x)=d_{1}g^{*}(x)d_{2}h^{*}(x)$, where $g^{*}(x),h^{*}(x)\\in R[x]$ and $g^{*}(x), h^{*}(x)$ are primitive. We showed above that the polynomial $g^{*}(x)h^{*}(x)$ is primitive, and we know that this decomposition $f(x)=cf^{*}(x)$ is unique. Therefore we can write $f^{*}(x)=g^{*}(x)h^{*}(x)$ and thus $f(x)=cg^{*}(x)h^{*}(x)$. But both $f(x)$ and $f^{*}(x)=g^{*}(x)h^{*}(x)$ have coefficients in $R$, and $f^{*}(x)$ is primitive. So $c$ must be an element of $R$. Thus, when we factored $f(x)\\in k[x]$ the two factors were also in $R[x]$. By induction, if we decompose $f$ into all its irreducible components in $k[x]$, each of the factors will be in $R[x]$, and we know that this decomposition will be essentially unique because $k[x]$ is a unique factorization domain. This shows that $R[x]$ is a unique factorization domain.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Example 2.3.5 (Part 1)", "question": "Let $\\lambda=1-\\rho,\\theta\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$. Show that if $\\theta$ is not divisible by $\\lambda$, then $\\theta^{3}\\equiv\\pm1$ (mod $\\lambda^{4})$.", "solution": "From previous results, we know that if $\\theta$ is not divisible by $\\lambda$ then $\\theta\\equiv\\pm1$ (mod $\\lambda$). Set $\\xi=\\theta$ or $-\\theta$ so that $\\xi\\equiv1$ (mod $\\lambda$). We write $\\xi$ as $1+d\\lambda$. Then\n$$\\pm(\\theta^{3}\\mp1)=\\xi^{3}-1$$\n$$=(\\xi-1)(\\xi-\\rho)(\\xi-\\rho^{2})$$\n$$=(d\\lambda)(d\\lambda+1-\\rho)(1+d\\lambda-\\rho^{2})=d\\lambda(d\\lambda+\\lambda)(d\\lambda-\\lambda\\rho^{2})$$\n$$=\\lambda^{3}d(d+1)(d-\\rho^{2})$$\nSince $\\rho^2 \\equiv 1$ (mod $\\lambda$), then $(d-\\rho^{2})\\equiv(d-1)\\pmod{\\lambda}$. We know that $\\lambda$ divides one of $d$, $d-1$, and $d+1$ (since $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]/(\\lambda) \\cong \\mathbb{Z}/3\\mathbb{Z}$), so we may conclude that $\\xi^3-1 \\equiv 0$ (mod $\\lambda^{4}$), so $\\xi^{3}\\equiv1$ (mod $\\lambda^{4}$) and $\\theta\\equiv\\pm1$ (mod $\\lambda^{4}$).", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Example 2.3.5 (Part 2)", "question": "Deduce that if $\\alpha$, $\\beta$, $\\gamma$ are coprime to $\\lambda$, then the equation $\\alpha^{3}+\\beta^{3}+\\gamma^{3}=0$ has no nontrivial solutions.", "solution": "We consider this equation mod $\\lambda^{4}$. Indeed, if such a solution were possible, then somehow the equation\n$$\\pm1\\pm1\\pm1\\equiv0\\pmod{\\lambda^{4}}$$\ncould be satisfied. The left side of this congruence gives $\\pm1$ or $\\pm3$; certainly $\\pm1$ is not congruent to 0 (mod $\\lambda^{4}$) since $\\lambda^{4}$ is not a unit. Also, $\\pm3$ is not congruent to 0 (mod $\\lambda^{4}$) since $\\lambda^{2}$ is an associate of 3, and thus $\\lambda^{4}$ is not. Thus, there is no solution to $\\alpha^{3}+\\beta^{3}+\\gamma^{3}=0$ if $\\alpha, \\beta, \\gamma$ are coprime to $\\lambda$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 2.3.6", "question": "Consider the equation\n$$\\alpha^{3}+\\beta^{3}+\\epsilon\\lambda^{3n}\\delta^{3}=0 \\quad (2.1)$$\nfor a unit $\\epsilon$. Show that any solution for $\\delta, \\alpha, \\beta$ coprime to $\\lambda$ must have $n\\ge2$, but if (2.1) can be solved with $n=m$, it can be solved for $n=m-1$. Deduce that there are no solutions to the above equation with $\\delta, \\alpha, \\beta$ coprime to $\\lambda$.", "solution": "We know that $n\\ge1$ from Example 2.3.5 (since if $n=0$ we are in the case of the previous example which has no solutions). Considering the equation mod $\\lambda^{4}$, we get that $\\pm1\\pm1+\\epsilon\\lambda^{3n}\\delta^{3} \\equiv 0$ (mod $\\lambda^{4}$). There are two possibilities: if $\\lambda^{3n}\\equiv\\pm2$ (mod $\\lambda^{4}$), then certainly $n$ cannot exceed 1; but if $n=1$, then our congruence implies that $\\lambda|2$ which is not true. The other possibility is that $\\lambda^{3n}\\equiv0$ (mod $\\lambda^{4}$), from which it follows that $n\\ge2.$ We may rewrite (2.1) as\n$$-\\epsilon\\lambda^{3n}\\delta^{3}=\\alpha^{3}+\\beta^{3}$$\n$$=(\\alpha+\\beta)(\\alpha+\\rho\\beta)(\\alpha+\\rho^{2}\\beta).$$\nWe will write these last three factors as $A_{1}$, $A_{2}$ and $A_{3}$ for convenience. We can see that $\\lambda^{6}$ divides the left side of this equation, since $n\\ge2$. Thus $\\lambda^{6}|A_{1}A_{2}A_{3}$ and $\\lambda^{2}|A_{i}$ for some $i$. Notice that\n$$A_{1}-A_{2}=\\lambda\\beta , \\quad A_{1}-A_{3}=\\lambda\\beta\\rho^{2}$$\nand\n$$A_{2}-A_{3}=\\lambda\\beta\\rho$$\nSince $\\lambda$ divides one of the $A_{i}$, it divides them all, since it divides their differences. Notice, though, that $\\lambda^{2}$ does not divide any of these differences, since $\\lambda$ does not divide $\\beta$ by assumption. Thus, the $A_{i}$ are inequivalent mod $\\lambda^{2}$ and only one of the $A_{i}$ is divisible by $\\lambda^{2}$. Since our equation is unchanged if we replace $\\beta$ with $\\rho\\beta$ or $\\rho^{2}\\beta$, then without loss of generality we may assume that $\\lambda^{2}|A_{1}$. In fact, we know that $\\lambda^{3n-2}|A_{1}$.\n\nNow we write\n$B_{1}=A_{1}/\\lambda$, $B_{2}=A_{2}/\\lambda$, $B_{3}=A_{3}/\\lambda$.\nWe notice that these $B_{i}$ are pairwise coprime, since if for some prime $p$, we had $p|B_{1}$ and $p|B_{2}$, then necessarily we would have\n$p|B_{1}-B_{2}=\\beta$ and $p|\\lambda B_{1}+B_{2}-B_{1}=\\alpha.$\nThis is only possible for a unit $p$ since $gcd(\\alpha,\\beta)=1$. Similarly, we can verify that the remaining pairs of $B_{i}$ are coprime. Since $\\lambda^{3n-2}|A_{1}$, we have $\\lambda^{3n-3}|B_{1}$. So we may rewrite (2.1) as\n$$-\\epsilon\\lambda^{3n-3}\\delta^{3}=B_{1}B_{2}B_{3}.$$\nFrom this equation we can see that each of the $B_{i}$ is an associate of a cube, since they are relatively prime, and we write\n$B_{1}=e_{1}\\lambda^{3n-3}C_{1}^{3}, \\quad B_{2}=e_{2}C_{2}^{3}, \\quad B_{3}=e_{3}C_{3}^{3}$\nfor units $e_{i}$, and pairwise coprime $C_{i}$. Now recall that\n$A_{1}=\\alpha+\\beta, \\quad A_{2}=\\alpha+\\rho\\beta, \\quad A_{3}=\\alpha+\\rho^{2}\\beta$.\nFrom these equations we have that\n$\\rho^{2}A_{3}+\\rho A_{2}+A_{1}=\\alpha(\\rho^{2}+\\rho+1)+\\beta(\\overline{\rho}^{2}+\\overline{\rho}+1) = 0$\nso we have that\n$0=\\rho^{2}\\lambda B_{3}+\\rho\\lambda B_{2}+\\lambda B_{1}$\nand\n$0=\\rho^{2}B_{3}+\\rho B_{2}+B_{1}$.\nWe can then deduce that\n$\\rho^{2}e_{3}C_{3}^{3}+\\rho e_{2}C_{2}^{3}+e_{1}\\lambda^{3n-3}C_{1}^{3}=0$\nso we can find units $e_{4}$, $e_{5}$ so that\n$C_{3}^{3}+e_{4}C_{2}^{3}+e_{5}\\lambda^{3n-3}C_{1}^{3}=0.$\nConsidering this equation mod $\\lambda^{3}$, and recalling that $n\\ge2$, we get that $\\pm1\\pm e_{4}\\equiv0$ (mod $\\lambda^{3}$) so $e_{4}=\\mp1$, and we rewrite our equation as\n$$C_{3}^{3}+(\\mp C_{2})^{3}+e_{5}\\lambda^{3(n-1)}C_{1}^{3}=0.$$\nThis is an equation of the same type as (2.1), so we can conclude that if there exists a solution for (2.1) with $n=m$, then there exists a solution with $n=m-1$. This establishes by descent that no nontrivial solution to (2.1) is possible in $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Example 2.4.1", "question": "Solve the equation $y^{2}+4=x^{3}$ for integers $x, y$.", "solution": "We first consider the case where $y$ is even. It follows that $x$ must also be even, which implies that $x^{3}\\equiv0$ (mod 8). Now, $y$ is congruent to 0 or 2 (mod 4). If $y\\equiv0$ (mod 4), then $y^{2}+4\\equiv4$ (mod 8), so we can rule out this case. However, if $y\\equiv2$ (mod 4), then $y^{2}+4\\equiv0$ (mod 8). Writing $y=2Y$ with $Y$ odd, and $x=2X$ we have $4Y^{2}+4=8X^{3},$ so that\n$$Y^{2}+1=2X^{3}$$\n$$(Y+i)(Y-i)=2X^{3}=(1+i)(1-i)X^{3}$$\nWe note that $Y^{2}+1\\equiv2\\pmod 4$ and so $X^{3}$ is odd. Now,\n$$X^{3}=\\frac{(Y+i)(Y-i)}{(1+i)(1-i)} = \\left(\\frac{1+Y}{2}+\\frac{1-Y}{2}i\\right)\\left(\\frac{1+Y}{2}-\\frac{1-Y}{2}i\\right) = \\left(\\frac{1+Y}{2}\\right)^{2}+\\left(\\frac{1-Y}{2}\\right)^{2}.$$\nWe shall write this last sum as $a^{2}+b^{2}$. Since $Y$ is odd, $a$ and $b$ are integers. Notice also that $a+b=1$ so that $gcd(a,b)=1$. We now have that\n$$X^{3}=(a+bi)(a-bi).$$\nWe would like to establish that $(a+bi)$ and $(a-bi)$ are relatively prime. We assume there exists some nonunit $d$ such that $d|(a+bi)$ and $d|(a-bi).$ But then $d|[(a+bi)+(a-bi)]=2a$ and $d|(a+bi)-(a-bi)=2bi.$ Since $gcd(a,b)=1$ then $d|2$, and thus $d$ must have even norm. But then it is impossible that $d|(a+bi)$ since the norm of $(a+bi)$ is $a^{2}+b^{2}=X^{3}$ which is odd. Thus $(a+bi)$ and $(a-bi)$ are relatively prime, and each is therefore a cube, since $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$ is a unique factorization domain. We write\n$$a+bi=(s+ti)^{3}=s^{3}-3st^{2}+(3s^{2}t-t^{3})i.$$\nComparing real and imaginary parts yields\n$$a=s^{3}-3st^{2}, \\quad b=3s^{2}t-t^{3}.$$\nAdding these two equations yields $a+b=s^{3}-3st^{2}+3s^{2}t-t^{3}$. But $a+b=1$, so we have\n$$1=s^{3}-3st^{2}+3s^{2}t-t^{3} = (s-t)(s^{2}+4st+t^{2})$$\nNow, $s, t \\in \\mathbb{Z}$ so $(s-t)=\\pm1$ and $(s^{2}+4st+t^{2})=\\pm1$. Subtracting the second equation from the square of the first we find that $-6st=0$ or 2. Since $s$ and $t$ are integers, we rule out the case $-6st=2$ and deduce that either $s=0$ or $t=0$. Thus either $a=1, b=0$ or $a=0, b=1$. It follows that $Y=\\pm1$, so the only solutions in $\\mathbb{Z}$ to the given equation with $y$ even are $x=2, y=\\pm2$.\n\nNext, we consider the case where $y$ is odd. We write $x^{3}=(y+2i)(y-2i).$ We can deduce that $(y+2i)$ and $(y-2i)$ are relatively prime since if $d$ divided both, $d$ would divide both their sum and their difference, i.e., we would have $d|2y$ and $d|4i$. But then $d$ would have even norm, and since $y$ is odd, $(y+2i)$ has odd norm; thus $d$ does not divide $(y+2i)$. Hence, $(y+2i)$ is a cube; we write\n$$y+2i=(q+ri)^{3}=q^{3}-3qr^{2}+(3q^{2}r-r^{3})i.$$\nComparing real and imaginary parts we have that $2=3q^{2}r-r^{3}$ so that $r|2$ and the only values $r$ could thus take are $\\pm1$ and $\\pm2$. We get that the only possible pairs $(q,r)$ we can have are (1, 1), (-1, 1), (1, -2), and $(-1,-2)$. Solving for $y$, and excluding the cases where $y$ is even, we find that $x=5, y=\\pm11$ is the only possible solution when $y$ is odd.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Example 2.4.4", "question": "Solve $y^{2}+1=x^{p}$ for an odd prime $p$, and $x, y\\in\\mathbb{Z}.$", "solution": "Notice that the equation $y^{2}+1=x^{3}$ from an earlier problem is a special case of the equation given here. To analyze the solutions of this equation, we first observe that for odd $y$, $y^{2}\\equiv1$ (mod 4). Thus $x$ would need to be even, but then if we consider the equation mod 4 we find that it cannot be satisfied; $y^{2}+1\\equiv2$ (mod 4), while $x^{p}\\equiv0$ (mod 4). Thus $y$ is even; it is easy to see that $x$ must be odd. If $y=0$ then $x=1$ is a solution for all $p$. We call this solution a trivial solution; we proceed to investigate solutions other than the trivial one.\n\nNow we write our equation as\n$$(y+i)(y-i)=x^{p}.$$\nIf $y\\ne0$ then we note that if some divisor $\\alpha$ were to divide both $(y+i)$ and $(y-i)$, then it would divide $2i$; if $\\alpha$ is not a unit, then $\\alpha$ will thus divide 2, and also $y$, since $y$ is even. But then it is impossible that $\\alpha$ also divide $y+i$ since $i$ is a unit. We conclude that $(y+i)$ and $(y-i)$ are relatively prime when $y\\ne0$. Thus $(y+i)$ and $(y-i)$ are both $p$-th powers, and we may write\n$$(y+i)=e(a+bi)^{p}$$\nfor some unit $e$ and integers $a$ and $b$. We have analyzed the units of $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$; they are all powers of $i$, so we write $(y+i)=i^{k}(a+bi)^{p}$ and $(y-i)=\\overline{(y+i)}=(-i)^{k}(a-bi)^{p}$.\nThus\n$$(y+i)(y-i)=i^{k}(a+bi)^{p}(-i)^{k}(a-bi)^{p}=(a^{2}+b^{2})^{p}=x^{p}$$\nand it follows that $x=(a^{2}+b^{2})$. We know that $x$ is odd, so one of $a$ and $b$ is even (but not both). We now have that\n$$(y+i)-(y-i)=2i = i^{k}(a+bi)^{p}-(-i)^{k}(a-bi)^{p}.$$\nWe consider two cases separately:\n\nCase 1. $k$ is odd.\nIn this case we use the binomial theorem to determine the imaginary parts of both sides of the above equation. We get\n$$2=Im[(i)^{k}((a+bi)^{p}+(a-bi)^{p})]=Im[(i)^{k}(\\sum_{j=0}^{p}a^{p-j}(bi)^{j}\\binom{p}{j}+\\sum_{j=0}^{p}a^{p-j}(-bi)^{j}\\binom{p}{j})]$$\n$$=2(-1)^{(k-1)/2}\\sum_{0\\le j<p, even}a^{p-j}(b)^{j}(-1)^{j/2}\\binom{p}{j}.$$\nThus\n$$1=(-1)^{(k-1)/2}\\sum_{0\\le j<p, even}a^{p-j}(b)^{j}(-1)^{j/2}\\binom{p}{j}.$$\nSince $a$ divides every term on the right-hand side of this equation, then $a|1$ and $a=\\pm1$. We observed previously that only one of $a, b$ is odd; thus $b$ is even. We now substitute $a=\\pm1$ into the last equation above to get\n$$\\pm1=\\sum_{0\\le j<p, even}(b)^{j}(-1)^{j/2}\\binom{p}{j} = 1-b^{2}\\binom{p}{2}+b^{4}\\binom{p}{4}-\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\pm b^{p-1}\\binom{p}{p-1}.$$\nIf the sign of 1 on the left-hand side of this equality were negative, we would have that $b^{2}|2$; $b$ is even and in particular $b\\ne\\pm1$, so this is impossible. Thus\n$$0=-b^{2}\\binom{p}{2}+b^{4}\\binom{p}{4}-\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\pm b^{p-1}\\binom{p}{p-1} = -\\binom{p}{2}+b^{2}\\binom{p}{4}-\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\pm b^{p-3}\\binom{p}{p-1}$$\nNow we notice that $2|b$ so $2 | \\binom{p}{2}$. If $p\\equiv3$ (mod 4), then we are finished because $2 \\nmid \\binom{p}{2}$. Suppose in fact that $2^{q}$ is the largest power of 2 dividing $\\binom{p}{2}$. We shall show that $2^{q+1}$ will then divide every term in $b^{2}\\binom{p}{4}-\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\pm b^{p-3}\\binom{p}{p-1}$, and this will establish that no $b$ will satisfy our equation. We consider one of these terms given by $(b)^{j-2}\\binom{p}{j}$, for an even value of $j$; we rewrite this as $b^{2m-2}\\binom{p}{2m}$. We see that\n$$\\binom{p}{2m}=\\binom{p-2}{2m-2}\\frac{(p)(p-1)}{2m(2m-1)} = \\binom{p-2}{2m-2}\\binom{p}{2}\\frac{1}{m(2m-1)},$$\nso we are considering a term\n$$\\binom{p-2}{2m-2}\\binom{p}{2}\\frac{b^{2m-2}}{m(2m-1)}$$\nNow, $2^{q}|\\binom{p}{2}$ by assumption. Recall that $b$ is even; thus $2^{2m-2}|b^{2m-2}$. Now $m\\ge2$; it is easy to see then that $2m-2\\ge m$, so $2^{2m-2}$ does not divide $m$. Thus when we reduce the fraction\n$$\\frac{b^{2m-2}}{m(2m-1)}$$\nto lowest terms, the numerator is even and the denominator is odd. Therefore, $2(2^{q})|\\binom{p-2}{2m-2}\\binom{p}{2}\\frac{b^{2m-2}}{m(2m-1)}.$ Thus $2^{q+1}$ divides every term in $b^{2}\\binom{p}{4}-\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\pm\\binom{p}{p-1}b^{p-3}$ and we deduce that no value of $b$ can satisfy our equation.\n\nCase 2. $k$ is even.\nThis case is almost identical to the first case; we mention only the relevant differences. When we expand\n$$(y+i)-(y-i)=2i=i^{k}(a+bi)^{p}-(-i)^{k}(a-bi)^{p}$$\nand consider imaginary parts, we get\n$$1=(-1)^{k/2}\\sum_{0<j\\le p, odd}a^{p-j}(b)^{j}(-1)^{(j-1)/2}\\binom{p}{j}.$$\nWe are able to deduce that $b=\\pm1$ substituting we get the equation\n$$\\pm1=\\sum_{0<j\\le p, odd}a^{p-j}(b)^{j}(-1)^{(j-1)/2}\\binom{p}{j} = 1-a^{2}\\binom{p}{2}+a^{4}\\binom{p}{4}-\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\pm\\binom{p}{p-1}a^{p-1},$$\nwhich we can see is identical to the equation we arrived at in Case 1, with $b$ replaced by $a$. Thus we can reproduce the proof of Case 1, with $b$ replaced by $a,$ to establish that there are no nontrivial solutions with $k$ even. We conclude that the equation $y^{2}+1=x^{p}$ has no nontrivial solution with $x,y\\in\\mathbb{Z}$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.1.2", "question": "Let $D$ be squarefree. Consider $R=\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{D}]$. Show that every element of $R$ can be written as a product of irreducible elements.", "solution": "We define a map $n:R\\rightarrow\\mathbb{N}$ such that for $a+b\\sqrt{D}\\in R,$\n$$n(a+b\\sqrt{D})=|a^{2}-Db^{2}|$$\nWe must check that this map satisfies conditions (i) and (ii) from the previous example.\n(i) For $a+b\\sqrt{D},c+d\\sqrt{D}\\in R$\n$$n[(a+b\\sqrt{D})(c+d\\sqrt{D})]=n[(ac+bdD)+(ad+bc)\\sqrt{D}]$$\n$$=|(ac+bdD)^{2}-(ad+bc)^{2}D|$$\n$$=|(a^{2}-b^{2}D)(c^{2}-d^{2}D)|$$\n$$=n(a+b\\sqrt{D})n(c+d\\sqrt{D}),$$\nso condition (i) is satisfied.\n(ii) If $r=a+b\\sqrt{D}$ is a unit in $R$, then $\\exists s=c+d\\sqrt{D}\\in R$ such that $rs=1$. But by condition (i), since $1=n(1)$, $1=n(r)n(s)$. Since our map $n$ only takes on values in the positive integers, then $n(r)=n(s)=1$ for all units of $R$. The converse is clear.\nSince we have found a map $n$ which satisfies the conditions of Example 2.1.1, we can deduce that every element of $R$ can be written as a product of irreducible elements.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.1.3", "question": "Let $R=\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-5}]$. Show that $2,3,1+\\sqrt{-5},$ and $1-\\sqrt{-5}$ are irreducible in $R$, and that they are not associates.", "solution": "We define a map $n:R\\rightarrow\\mathbb{N}$ such that $n(a+b\\sqrt{-5})=a^{2}+5b^{2}$.\nIf 2 is not irreducible, then there are elements $r,s\\in R$ such that $rs=2$, with $r,s$ not units. But then $n(r)n(s)=n(2)=4$, and since $r,s$ are not units, it must be that $n(r)=n(s)=2.$ Then we must find integers $a, b$ such that $a^{2}+5b^{2}=2$, which is clearly impossible, so 2 must be irreducible.\nIf 3 is not irreducible then we can find $r,s\\in R$ with $rs=3$ and $r,s$ not units. Since $n(3)=9$, we must have $n(r)=n(s)=3$. But by the same argument as above, we see that this is impossible.\n$n(1+\\sqrt{-5})=6$. The only proper divisors of 6 are 2 and 3, and so if $1+\\sqrt{-5}$ is not irreducible, then we can find $r\\in R,$ $r$ not a unit and $r|(1+\\sqrt{-5})$ with either $n(r)=2$ or $n(r)=3$. But we showed above that this is not possible, so $1+\\sqrt{-5}$ is irreducible. Since $n(1-\\sqrt{-5})=6$, then $1-\\sqrt{-5}$ must also be irreducible.\nIf two elements of $R$ are associates, then they must have the same norm, a fact which follows immediately from the condition that all units have norm 1. If $a+b\\sqrt{-5}$ is a unit, then $a^{2}+5b^{2}=1$. This will only occur when $a=\\pm1$, and so the only units of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-5}]$ are 1 and -1. Of $2,3,1 \\pm \\sqrt{-5}$, we see that the only two which could possibly be associates are $1+\\sqrt{-5}$ and $1-\\sqrt{-5}$ because they have the same norm. However, if we multiply $1+\\sqrt{-5}$ by either of the units of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-5}]$, we will not get $1-\\sqrt{-5}$, and so they cannot be associates.\nWe conclude that 2, 3, $1+\\sqrt{-5}$ and $1-\\sqrt{-5}$ are all irreducible and are not associates.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.1.4", "question": "Let $R$ be a domain satisfying condition (i): every element of $R$ can be written as a product of irreducibles. Show that condition (ii): this factorization is essentially unique, is equivalent to $(ii^{*})$: if $\\pi$ is irreducible and $\\pi$ divides $ab$, then $\\pi|a$ or $\\pi|b.$", "solution": "Suppose $R$ satisfies both (i) and (ii) above. Let $\\pi\\in R$ be an irreducible element, and suppose that $\\pi|ab$, where\n$$a=\\tau_{1}\\tau_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\tau_{r}$$\n$$b=\\gamma_{1}\\gamma_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\gamma_{s}$$\nand $\\tau_{i}$, $\\gamma_{j}$ are irreducible. We know that $\\pi|ab=\\tau_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\tau_{r}\\gamma_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\gamma_{s},$ so it follows that $ab=\\pi\\lambda_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\lambda_{n}$ where each $\\lambda_{i}$ is irreducible. By condition (ii), $\\pi\\sim\\tau_{i}$ for some $i$, or $\\pi\\sim\\gamma_{j}$ for some $j$. Thus, if $\\pi|ab$ then $\\pi|a$ or $\\pi|b.$\nNow suppose that $R$ is a domain satisfying conditions (i) and $(ii^{*})$ above, and suppose that we have an element $a$ which has two different factorizations into irreducibles: $a=\\tau_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\tau_{r}$ and $a=\\pi_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\pi_{s}$. Consider $\\tau_{1}$. We know that $\\tau_{1}|a$, and so $\\tau_{1}|\\pi_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\pi_{s}$. By $(ii^{*})$ we know that $\\tau_{1}|\\pi_{i}$ for some $i$, and since both are irreducible, they must be associates. We can now remove both $\\tau_{1}$ and $\\pi_{i}$ from our factorization of $a$. We next consider $\\tau_{2}$. Following the same process, we can pair up $\\tau_{2}$ with its associate, and we can continue to do this until we have paired up each of the irreducible factors $\\tau_{i}$ with its associate $\\pi_{j}$. It is clear that if we continue in this fashion, we must have $r=s$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.1.5", "question": "Show that if $\\pi$ is an irreducible element of a principal ideal domain, then $(\\pi)$ is a maximal ideal (where $(\\pi)$ denotes the ideal generated by the element $\\pi$).", "solution": "We define $gcd(a,b)$, the greatest common divisor of $a, b\\in R$, to be an element $d$ such that the ideal $(a, b)$ equals the ideal $(d)$. It is unique up to units. For a unique factorization domain, this definition coincides with the usual one. We note that $d$ must divide both $a$ and $b$ since they are in the ideal $(d)$.\nIf $\\pi$ is irreducible, we consider the ideal $(\\pi, \\alpha)$ where $\\alpha$ is any element not in $(\\pi)$. Since $\\alpha$ is not a multiple of $\\pi$, and $\\pi$ is irreducible, then the only common divisors of $\\alpha$ and $\\pi$ will be units. Then $gcd(\\pi,\\alpha)=1$. In other words, the ideal generated by $\\pi$ is a maximal ideal.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.1.8", "question": "If $F$ is a field, prove that $F[x]$, the ring of polynomials in $x$ with coefficients in $F$, is Euclidean.", "solution": "We define a map $\\phi:F[x]\\rightarrow\\mathbb{N}$ such that for $f\\in F[x],$ $\\phi(f)=deg(f)$. Now consider any two polynomials $f(x)$, $g(x)\\in F[x]$. If $deg(g)>deg(f)$, then we can certainly write $f(x)=0\\cdot g(x)+f(x)$, which satisfies the Euclidean condition. Then we can assume that $m=deg(g)\\le deg(f)=n$ and write $f(x)=a_{0}+a_{1}x+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{n}x^{n}$, and $g(x)=b_{0}+b_{1}x+b_{2}x^{2}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+b_{m}x^{m}$, where $a_n, b_{m}\\ne0$ and $m\\le n$. We proceed by induction on the degree of $f$. That is, we will prove by induction on the degree of $f$ that we can write $f(x)=q(x)g(x)+r(x)$, where $r=0$ or $deg(r)<deg(g)$.\nDefine a new polynomial\n$$h(x)=a_{n}b_{m}^{-1}g(x)x^{n-m}.$$\nObserve that the leading term of $h(x)$ is $a_{n}b_{m}^{-1}b_{m}x^{m}x^{n-m}=a_{n}x^{n}$ which is the leading term of $f(x)$, so that if $f_{1}(x)=f(x)-h(x)$, either $f_{1}(x)=0$ or $deg(f_{1})<deg(f)$. The theorem holds for $f_{1}(x)$, so we can write $f_{1}(x)=f(x)-h(x)=q(x)g(x)+r(x)$, where $r=0$ or $deg(r)<deg(g)=m.$ Now $f(x)=q(x)g(x)+h(x)+r(x)$ and since $h(x)$ is a multiple of $g(x)$, the result follows.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.2.1", "question": "Show that $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$ is Euclidean.", "solution": "We define a map $\\phi:\\mathbb{Z}[i]\\rightarrow\\mathbb{N}$ such that $\\phi(a+bi)=a^{2}+b^{2}$. Now, given any two elements of $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$, say $\\alpha=a+bi$ and $\\gamma=c+di,$ can we find $q,r\\in\\mathbb{Z}[i]$ such that $a+bi=q(c+di)+r$, where $r=0$ or $\\phi(r)<\\phi(c+di)$?\nSince we cannot divide $\\alpha$ and $\\gamma$ in the ring $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$, we move temporarily to the ring $\\mathbb{Q}[i]=\\{r+si|r,s\\in\\mathbb{Q}\\}$. In this ring,\n$$\\frac{\\alpha}{\\gamma}=\\frac{(a+bi)}{(c+di)}=\\frac{(ac+bd)}{(c^{2}+d^{2})}+\\frac{(bc-ad)}{(c^{2}+d^{2})}i=r+si,$$\nwith $r,s\\in\\mathbb{Q}$. We can now choose $m, n\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ such that $|r-m|\\le1/2$ and $|s-n|\\le1/2.$ We set $q=m+ni$. Then $q\\in\\mathbb{Z}[i]$, and $\\alpha=q\\gamma+r$ for some suitable $r,$ with\n$$\\phi(r)=\\phi(\\alpha-q\\gamma)=\\phi(\\alpha/\\gamma-q)\\phi(\\gamma)$$\n$$=[(r-m)^{2}+(s-n)^{2}]\\phi(\\gamma)$$\n$$ \\le(\\frac{1}{4}+\\frac{1}{4})\\phi(\\gamma)=\\frac{1}{2}\\phi(\\gamma)<\\phi(\\gamma).$$\nWe have shown that our map $\\phi$ satisfies the properties specified above, and so $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$ is Euclidean.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.2.2", "question": "Prove that if $p$ is a positive prime, then there is an element $x\\in\\mathbb{F}_{p}:=\\mathbb{Z}/p\\mathbb{Z}$ such that $x^{2}\\equiv-1$ (mod $p$) if and only if either $p=2$ or $p\\equiv1$ (mod 4). (Hint: Use Wilson's theorem, Exercise 1.4.10.)", "solution": "If $p=2$, then $1\\equiv-1$ (mod 2), so $1^{2}=1\\equiv-1$ (mod 2). Hence we can take $x=1$. Conversely, if $1\\equiv-1$ (mod $p$), we can see that $p=2$ since $1=ap-1$ for some integer $a$ which implies $ap=2$.\nWe will show that in any field $\\mathbb{F}_{p}$ where 1 is not congruent to -1 (mod $p$), $x^{2}\\equiv-1$ (mod $p$) for an element $x$ if and only if $x$ has order 4 in the group of units of the field. Suppose that $x^{2}\\equiv-1$ (mod $p$). Then the first four powers of $x$ are $x, -1, -x, 1$. Hence $x$ has order 4. Conversely, suppose that $x$ has order 4. Then, $x^{4}=(x^{2})^{2}\\equiv1(mod~p)$, so $(x^{2})^{2}-1\\equiv0$ (mod $p$). Hence $(x^2 + 1)(x^{2}-1)\\equiv0(mod~p).$ Since $x$ is an element of a field, $x^{2}+1\\equiv0$ (mod $p$) or $x^{2}-1\\equiv0$ (mod $p$). However, if $x^{2}-1\\equiv0$ (mod $p$), $x$ has order 2. Hence $x^{2}\\equiv-1$ (mod $p$).\nIf $p\\ne2$, then $\\mathbb{F}_{p}$ is a field where 1 is not congruent to -1 (mod $p$). Hence the existence of an element $x$ such that $x^{2}\\equiv-1$ (mod $p$) is equivalent to the existence of an element of order 4 in the group of units of $\\mathbb{F}_{p}$. Let $U_{p}$ be the group of units of $\\mathbb{F}_{p}$. Then $|U_{p}|=p-1$, and since the order of any element divides the order of the group, if $U_{p}$ has an element of order 4, then we have $4|p-1$ or, equivalently, $p\\equiv1$ (mod 4). Conversely, if we suppose that $p\\equiv1$ (mod 4), then we can write $p=4k+1$ where $k$ is an integer and $U_{p}$ is a cyclic group of order $p-1=4k$. If $g$ is a generator of $U_{p}$, then $g$ has order $4k$. So $g^{k}$ has order 4. Hence we can see that if 1 is not congruent to 1 mod $p$, $x^{2}\\equiv-1$ (mod $p$) occurs if and only if $x$ has order 4 in the group of units of the field, which occurs if and only if $p \\equiv 1$ (mod 4).\nAlternate Solution: Wilson's theorem gives $(p-1)! \\equiv -1$ (mod $p$). We can pair up $k$ and $(p-k)$ in the product above so that $k(p-k)\\equiv-k^{2}$ (mod $p$) implies $(-1)^{(p-1)/2}(\\frac{p-1}{2})!^{2}\\equiv-1$ (mod $p$). Thus, if $p\\equiv1$ (mod 4), there is an $x\\in\\mathbb{F}_{p}$ so that $x^{2}\\equiv-1$ (mod $p$). The converse follows from Fermat's little Theorem: $1\\equiv(x^{2})^{(p-1)/2}\\equiv(-1)^{(p-1)/2}(mod~p)$ so that $(p-1)/2$ is even. That is, $p\\equiv1$ (mod 4).", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.2.3", "question": "Find all integer solutions to $y^{2}+1=x^{3}$ with $x, y\\ne0$.", "solution": "If $y$ is even, then $x^{3}\\equiv0$ (mod 8), which implies in turn that $y^{2}\\equiv7$ (mod 8). However, if $y\\equiv1,3,5,7$ (mod 8), then $y^{2}\\equiv1$ (mod 8). So $x$ must be odd, and $y$ even.\nWe can factor this equation in the ring $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$ to obtain $(y+i)(y-i)=x^{3}$. If $\\exists\\delta$ such that $\\delta|(y+i)$ and $\\delta|(y-i)$ then $\\delta|2i$, which implies that $\\delta|2$. But this would mean that $\\delta$ is divisible by 2, which we know is not true. Therefore, we know that $(y+i)$ and $(y-i)$ are relatively prime in $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$, and that they must both be cubes. We know that we can write $y+i=e_{1}(a+bi)^{3}$ and $y-i=e_{2}(c+di)^{3}$ where $a, b, c, d\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ and $e_{1}$, $e_{2}$ are units in $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$. However, the only units of $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$ are $\\pm1$ and $\\pm i,$ and these are all cubes, so without loss, assume that $e_{1}=e_{2}=1$.\nNext, we expand our factorization for $y+i$ to get\n$$y+i=a^{3}+3a^{2}bi+3ab^{2}-b^{3}i.$$\nComparing the imaginary parts, we get $1=3a^{2}b-b^{3}=b(3a^{2}-b^{2})$, with $a,b\\in\\mathbb{Z}$. The only integers which multiply together to give 1 are $\\pm1$, so we know that $b=\\pm1$. If $b=1$, then we have $1=3a^{2}-1$, implying $3a^{2}=2$, which has no integer solutions, so $b\\ne1$. If $b=-1$ then we get $1=-3a^{2}+1$, and so $3a^{2}=0$, and $a$ must be 0. However, if we substitute $a=0$ back into our original equation for $y+i,$ we find that $y=0$ which we did not allow, and so $b\\ne-1$. We conclude that the equation $y^{2}+1=x^{3}$ has no integer solutions with $x,y\\ne0$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.2.4", "question": "If $\\pi$ is an element of $R$ such that when $\\pi|ab$ with $a, b\\in R$, then $\\pi|a$ or $\\pi|b$, then we say that $\\pi$ is prime. What are the primes of $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$?", "solution": "Given $\\pi=(a+bi)\\in\\mathbb{Z}[i]$ we define the complex conjugate of $\\pi$ to be the element $\\overline{\\pi}=(a-bi)$. We note that $n(\\pi)=a^{2}+b^{2}=\\pi\\overline{\\pi},$ and so given any prime $\\pi$ in $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$, we know that $\\pi$ divides $n(\\pi)$. Using this information, we observe that we can find all the Gaussian primes by examining the irreducible factors of the primes of $\\mathbb{Z}$. For, let $n(\\pi)=p_{1}p_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{k}$ be the prime decomposition of $n(\\pi)$. We know that $\\pi|n(\\pi)$, so $\\pi|p_{i}$ for some $i$. If $\\pi|p_{i}$ and $\\pi|p_{j}$, with $p_{i}\\ne p_{j}$, then $\\pi|1$, since $gcd(p_{i},p_{j})=1$. But then $\\pi$ would be a unit, and thus not irreducible. So, by examining all of the divisors of the primes in $\\mathbb{Z}$, we will discover all of the primes of $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$ once and only once each.\nWe let $\\pi$ be a prime in $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$, and $p$ the prime in $\\mathbb{Z}$ such that $\\pi|p.$ By the properties of the map $n$, $n(\\pi)|n(p)=p^{2}$ so $n(\\pi)=p$ or $n(\\pi)=p^{2}$. If we let $\\pi=a+bi$, then $a^{2}+b^{2}=p$ or $a^{2}+b^{2}=p^{2}$. All the primes of $\\mathbb{Z}$ are congruent to 1, 2 or 3 (mod $p$), and we will examine these cases separately.\nCase 1. $p\\equiv3$ (mod 4). We just proved that if $\\pi=a+bi$ is prime, then either $a^{2}+b^{2}=p$, or $a^{2}+b^{2}=p^{2}$ for some integer prime $p$. Let us assume that the first of these possibilities is true. We know that $p$ is odd, so one of $a, b$ is even. Let us say that $a$ is even, and $b$ odd, so that $a=2x$ and $b=2y+1$ for some $x,y\\in\\mathbb{Z}$. Then $a^{2}+b^{2}=4x^{2}+4y^{2}+4y+1 = 4(x^{2}+y^{2}+y)+1 \\equiv1$ (mod 4). Since we had assumed that $p\\equiv3$ (mod 4), we have a contradiction. So $a^{2}+b^{2}=p^{2}$, which means that $n(\\pi)=n(p)$, and so $p$ and $\\pi$ must be associates. Therefore, primes in $\\mathbb{Z}$ that are congruent to 3 (mod 4) and their associates are prime in the ring $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$.\nCase 2. $p\\equiv2$ (mod 4). There is, of course, only one such integer prime: 2. Assume we have a prime $\\pi$ which divides 2. Since $2=(1+i)(1-i)$, then $\\pi|(1+i)$ or $\\pi|(1-i)$. But $n(1+i)=n(1-i)=2$ and it is easy to show that $(1+i)$ and $(1-i)$ are irreducible in $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$ and so they are prime. So, if $\\pi|2$, then $\\pi\\sim(1+i)$ or $\\pi\\sim(1-i)$.\nCase 3. $p\\equiv1$ (mod 4). We recall Wilson's Theorem, Exercise 1.4.10, which states that if $p$ is a prime, then $(p-1)!\\equiv-1$ (mod $p$). We will in fact be using a corollary of this theorem, which states that if $p$ is a prime number of the form $1+4m$, then $p|(n^{2}+1)$, where $(2m)!=n$. (We can also apply Exercise 2.2.2.) If $p|(n^{2}+1)=(n+i)(n-i)$ and $\\pi|p$, then $\\pi|(n+i)$ or $\\pi|(n-i)$. If $p$ were to divide $(n\\pm i)$, then $p|n$ and $p|1$ which is clearly not the case since $p$ is not a unit. We conclude that $p$ and $\\pi$ are not associates, so $n(\\pi)\\ne n(p)$, which implies that $n(\\pi)=a^{2}+b^{2}=p$. Thus, if $p\\equiv1$ (mod 4), then $p$ does not remain prime in $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$. We can deduce that if $\\pi=a\\pm bi$ and $a^{2}+b^{2}=p$ then $\\pi$ is prime in $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.2.5", "question": "A positive integer $a$ is the sum of two squares if and only if $a=b^{2}c$ where $c$ is not divisible by any positive prime $p\\equiv3$ (mod 4).", "solution": "Suppose that $a$ is the sum of two squares. Let $a=s^{2}+t^{2}$ and let $(s,t)=b$. Then $a=(bx)^{2}+(by)^{2}=b^{2}(x^{2}+y^{2})$ where $(x,y)=1$. Let $c=x^{2}+y^{2}$. Then we have $a=b^{2}c$ where $c$ is the sum of two relatively prime squares. By Exercise 2.2.2, $c$ is not divisible by any prime $p\\equiv3$ (mod 4). In fact, suppose that $p|x^{2}+y^{2}$. Then, $x^{2}+y^{2}\\equiv0$ (mod $p$), $x^{2}\\equiv-y^{2}$ (mod $p$) and so $((y^{-1})^{2}\\cdot x^{2})=(y^{-1}\\cdot x)^{2}\\equiv-1$ (mod $p$). By Exercise 2.2.2, either $p=2$ or $p\\equiv1$ (mod 4). Hence $c$ is not divisible by any prime $p\\equiv3$ (mod 4).\nNow suppose that we have an integer $a$ which we can write as $a=b^{2}c,$ and suppose that $c$ is not divisible by any positive prime $p\\equiv3$ (mod 4). Then $c$ is a product of primes each of which, by Exercise 2.2.4, is a sum of two squares. Then $b^{2}=n(b)$ and $c=n(t+ri)$ where $t$ and $r$ are integers. Then\n$$b^{2}\\cdot c=n(b(t+ri))=n(bt+bri)=b^{2}\\cdot t^{2}+b^{2}\\cdot r^{2}=(bt)^{2}+(br)^{2}.$$\nHence $a=b^{2}c$ is written as the sum of two squares.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.3.1", "question": "Show that $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$ is a ring.", "solution": "First observe that $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$ is a subset of the complex numbers, so associativity, distributivity, and commutativity are immediate for addition and multiplication. Also, $0,1\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$, so we have additive and multiplicative identities. If $a+b\\rho\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$, then $-a-b\\rho\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$, so we have additive inverses. It remains to verify closure under addition and multiplication; if $a, b, c, d \\in \\mathbb{Z}$, then $(a+b\\rho)+(c+d\\rho)=(a+c)+(b+d)\\rho\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$, so we have closure under addition. Also $(a+b\\rho)(c+d\\rho)=ac+(ad+bc)\\rho+bd\\rho^{2}$. We will therefore have closure under multiplication if $\\rho^{2}\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$. But $\\rho^{2}=-1-\\rho,$ so $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$ is a commutative ring with unit.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.3.2 (a)", "question": "Show that $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$ is Euclidean.", "solution": "Define $\\phi:\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]\\rightarrow\\mathbb{N}$ so that $\\phi(a+b\\rho)=a^{2}-ab+b^{2}=\\alpha\\overline{\\alpha}$ for $\\alpha\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$. We consider $\\alpha,\\beta\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$, $\\beta\\ne0$. We have $\\beta\\overline{\beta}=\\phi(\\beta)$. Now $\\beta\\overline{\beta}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ and $\\alpha\\overline{\beta}\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$, so\n$$\\frac{\\alpha}{\\beta}=\\frac{\\alpha\\overline{\beta}}{\\beta\\overline{\beta}}=\\frac{\\alpha\\overline{\beta}}{\\beta\\overline{\beta}}=s+t\\rho$$\nfor some $s, t\\in\\mathbb{Q}$. We set $m$ and $n$ to be the integers closest to $s$ and $t$, respectively, i.e., choose $m$ and $n$ so $|m-s|\\le1/2$ and $|n-t|\\le1/2$. We set $q=m+n\\rho$. Now,\n$$\\phi(\\frac{\\alpha}{\\beta}-q)=(s-m)^{2}-(s-m)(t-n)+(t-n)^{2}\\le\\frac{1}{4}+\\frac{1}{4}+\\frac{1}{4}<1.$$\nSo, writing $r=\\alpha-q\\beta$ then if $r\\ne0$, $\\phi(r)=\\phi(\\beta)\\phi(\\alpha/\\beta-q)<\\phi(\\beta)$, and with the map $\\phi$, for any $\\alpha,\\beta\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$, we can write $\\alpha=q\\beta+r$ where $r=0$ or $\\phi(r)<\\phi(\\beta)$. Thus, $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$ is Euclidean.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.3.2 (b)", "question": "Show that the only units in $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$ are $\\pm1$, $\\pm\\rho,$ and $\\pm\\rho^{2}$.", "solution": "Observe that $\\phi$ is a multiplicative map into the natural numbers, so that if $\\eta$ is a unit of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$, then $\\phi(\\eta)=1$. We thus see immediately that $\\pm1,\\pm\\rho,\\pm\\rho^{2}$ are all units (it is easy to see that they are distinct). Suppose $\\eta=a+b\\rho$ were a unit of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$. Then $a^{2}-ab+b^{2}=1$ and $(2a-b)^{2}+3b^{2}=4.$ From this equation it is clear that $b=0$ or $\\pm1$ are the only possible integer values $b$ could take, since $3b^{2}$ must be less than 4. To each solution for $b$ there are two corresponding solutions for $a$, and thus at most six distinct pairs $(a,b)$ in total. By the pigeonhole principle the list given above includes all the units of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.3.3", "question": "Let $\\lambda=1-\\rho$. Show that $\\lambda$ is irreducible, so we have a factorization of 3 (unique up to unit).", "solution": "We have that $\\phi(\\lambda)=3$. If $d|\\lambda$, then $\\phi(d)|3$, i.e., $\\phi(d)=1$ or 3, so $d$ is either a unit or an associate of $\\lambda$, and $\\lambda$ is irreducible.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.3.4", "question": "Show that $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]/(\\lambda)$ has order 3.", "solution": "Suppose $\\alpha\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$, so that $\\alpha=a+b\\rho$ for integers $a, b$. Then $\\alpha=a+b-b(1-\\rho)=a+b-b\\lambda\\equiv a+b$ (mod $\\lambda$). Considered mod 3, $a+b$ could have residues 0, 1, or 2. Since $\\lambda|3$ (see Exercise 2.3.3, above), then $a$ will have one of these residues mod $\\lambda$. Since $\\phi(\\lambda)$ does not divide $\\phi(1)=1$, or $\\phi(2)=4$, none of these classes are equivalent mod $\\lambda$, and so we have three distinct residue classes, which we may denote by 0 and $\\pm1$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.4.2", "question": "Show that $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-2}]$ is Euclidean.", "solution": "We define a norm $\\phi:\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-2}]\\rightarrow\\mathbb{N}$ by $\\phi(a+b\\sqrt{-2})=a^{2}+2b^{2}.$ For $\\alpha, \\beta\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-2}]$, we consider $\\alpha/\\beta=\\alpha\\overline{\\beta}/\\beta\\overline{\beta}.$ Notice that $\\beta\\overline{\beta}=\\phi(\\beta)$ so $\\beta\\overline{\beta}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$. Also, $\\overline{\\beta}\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-2}]$, so $\\alpha\\overline{\\beta}\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-2}]$, so $\\alpha/\\beta=\\alpha\\overline{\\beta}/\\beta\\overline{\beta}=c+d\\sqrt{-2}$ for some $c, d\\in\\mathbb{Q}$. We choose $m$ and $n$ as the closest integers to $c$ and $d$, i.e., so that $|m-c|\\le1/2$ and $|n-d|\\le1/2$. We write $q=m+n\\sqrt{-2}$. We have that $\\phi(\\alpha/\\beta-q)=(c-m)^{2}+2(d-n)^{2}\\le1/4+1/2<1$. So we write $\\alpha=q\\beta+r$ and $r=\\alpha-q\\beta$. If $r\\ne0$ then $\\phi(r)=\\phi(\\beta)\\phi(\\alpha/\\beta-q)<\\phi(\\beta)$. We conclude that $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-2}]$ is Euclidean.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.4.3", "question": "Solve $y^{2}+2=x^{3}$ for $x,y\\in\\mathbb{Z}$", "solution": "Write $(y+\\sqrt{-2})(y-\\sqrt{-2})=x^{3}$. If $y$ were even, then $x$ would be also, but if $y$ is even, then $x^{3}\\equiv0$ (mod 8) whereas 8 does not divide $y^{2}+2$. So $y$ and $x$ are both odd. Observe that $(y+\\sqrt{-2})$ and $(y-\\sqrt{-2})$ are relatively prime, since if $d$ divided both, then $d$ would divide $2\\sqrt{-2}$ and would thus have even norm, which is not possible since $y$ is odd. Thus $(y+\\sqrt{-2})$ is a cube multiplied by a unit. The only units of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-2}]$ are 1 and -1, which are both cubes. Without loss, assume that the unit in question is 1. We write\n$$(y+\\sqrt{-2})=(a+b\\sqrt{-2})^{3}=a^{3}-6ab^{2}+(3a^{2}b-2b^{3})\\sqrt{-2}.$$\nComparing real and imaginary parts, we find that\n$$y=a^{3}-6ab^{2}, \\quad 1=(3a^{2}b-2b^{3})=b(3a^{2}-2b^{2}).$$\nThus, $b|1$ so $b=\\pm1$. It follows that $a=\\pm1$. Substituting into the equation for $y$, we find that $y=\\pm5$. Thus, the only solution to the given equation is $x=3,$ $y=\\pm5$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.4.5", "question": "Show that $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{2}]$ is Euclidean.", "solution": "We define a norm $\\phi:\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{2}]\\rightarrow\\mathbb{N}$ by $\\phi(a+b\\sqrt{2})=|a^{2}-2b^{2}|$. Let $\\alpha, \\beta\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{2}]$. We write $\\beta=c+d\\sqrt{2}$ and consider\n$$\\frac{\\alpha}{\\beta}=\\frac{\\alpha(c-d\\sqrt{2})}{\\beta(c-d\\sqrt{2})}.$$\nNotice that $|\\beta(c-d\\sqrt{2})|=\\phi(\\beta)$ so $\\beta(c-d\\sqrt{2})\\in\\mathbb{Z}.$ Also, $(c-d\\sqrt{2})\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{2}]$, so $\\alpha(c-d\\sqrt{2})\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{2}]$, so\n$$\\frac{\\alpha}{\\beta}=\\frac{\\alpha(c-d\\sqrt{2})}{\\beta(c-d\\sqrt{2})}=t+u\\sqrt{2}$$\nfor some $t, u\\in\\mathbb{Q}$. We choose $m$ and $n$ as the closest integers to $t$ and $u$, i.e. so that $|m-t|\\le1/2$ and $|n-u|\\le1/2.$ We write $q=m+n\\sqrt{2}$. We have that\n$$\\phi(\\alpha/\\beta-q)=|(t-m)^{2}-2(u-n)^{2}|\\le|(t-m)^{2}|+|2(u-n)^{2}|\\le\\frac{1}{4}+\\frac{1}{2}<1.$$\nWe write $\\alpha=q\\beta+r$, so $r=\\alpha-q\\beta.$ If $r\\ne0$, then $\\phi(r)=\\phi(\\beta)\\phi(\\alpha/\\beta-q)<\\phi(\\beta)$. We conclude that $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{2}]$ is Euclidean.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.4.6", "question": "Let $\\epsilon=1+\\sqrt{2}.$ Write $\\epsilon^{n}=u_{n}+v_{n}\\sqrt{2}.$ Show that $u_{n}^{2}-2v_{n}^{2}=\\pm1$.", "solution": "Since $\\phi$ is multiplicative and we have $\\phi(\\epsilon)=|-1|$ then\n$$\\phi(\\epsilon^{n})=|(-1)^{n}|=|u_{n}^{2}-2v_{n}^{2}|=1.$$\nThis gives infinitely many solutions to $x^{2}-2y^{2}=\\pm1$. It is easy to see that all of these solutions are distinct: $\\epsilon\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{2}]$ and $\\epsilon>1$ so $\\epsilon^{n+1}>\\epsilon^{n}$ for all positive $n$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.4.7", "question": "Show that there is no unit $\\eta$ in $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{2}]$ such that $1<\\eta<1+\\sqrt{2}$. Deduce that every unit (greater than zero) of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{2}]$ is a power of $\\epsilon=1+\\sqrt{2}$.", "solution": "Since 1 is a unit, for any unit $\\xi$, $-\\xi$ is also a unit, and negative and positive units are in one-to-one correspondence; we shall only consider the positive units of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{2}]$. We write $\\eta$ as $a+b\\sqrt{2}.$ Since $\\eta$ is a unit, $\\phi(\\eta)=(a+b\\sqrt{2})(a-b\\sqrt{2})=\\pm1$. By assumption $(a+b\\sqrt{2})>1$ and $|(a+b\\sqrt{2})(a-b\\sqrt{2})|=1$, so it follows that $-1<(a-b\\sqrt{2})<1$. Also, by assumption, $1<a+b\\sqrt{2}<1+\\sqrt{2}.$ So, adding these two inequalities gives $0<2a<2+\\sqrt{2}.$ Since $a\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ this implies that $a=1$. Notice now that there is no integer $b$ such that $1<1+b\\sqrt{2}<1+\\sqrt{2}.$ If any unit, $\\psi$, did exist which was not some power of $\\epsilon$, then by our Euclidean algorithm we would be able to divide by $(1+\\sqrt{2})^{k}$, where $k$ is chosen so that $(1+\\sqrt{2})^{k}<\\psi<(1+\\sqrt{2})^{k+1}$ and this would produce a new unit $\\psi^{\\prime}$ where $1<\\psi^{\\prime}<1+\\sqrt{2}$. So the only positive units of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{2}]$ are those of the form $(1+\\sqrt{2})^{n}$; there are infinitely many.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.5.1", "question": "Show that $R=\\mathbb{Z}[(1+\\sqrt{-7})/2]$ is Euclidean.", "solution": "Given $\\alpha,\\beta\\in R$, we want to find $\\gamma, \\delta\\in R$ such that $\\alpha=\\beta\\gamma+\\delta,$ with $N(\\delta)<N(\\beta)$. This is equivalent to showing that we can find a $\\gamma$ with $N(\\alpha/\\beta-\\gamma)<1$. Now, $\\alpha/\\beta=x+y\\sqrt{-7}$ with $x,y\\in\\mathbb{Q}$. Let $\\gamma=(u+v\\sqrt{-7})/2$ with $u,v\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ and $u\\equiv v$ (mod 2). We want\n$$N(x+y\\sqrt{-7}-(\\frac{u+v\\sqrt{-7}}{2}))=(x-\\frac{u}{2})^{2}+7(y-\\frac{v}{2})^{2}<1$$\nor, equivalently, $(2x-u)^{2}+7(2y-v)^{2}<4$. First consider $2y$. Choose for $v$ either $[2y]$ or $[2y]+1$, so that $2y-v\\le1/2$. Now choose for $u$ either $[2x]$ or $[2x]+1$, whichever has the same parity as $v$. Then $2x-u\\le1$. Then\n$$(2x-u)^{2}+7(2y-v)^{2}\\le1+\\frac{7}{4}=\\frac{11}{4}<4.$$\nWe have found a $\\gamma$ which works, and proved that $\\mathbb{Z}[(1+\\sqrt{-7})/2]$ is Euclidean.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.5.2", "question": "Show that $\\mathbb{Z}[(1+\\sqrt{-11})/2]$ is Euclidean.", "solution": "Proceed as in Exercise 2.5.1. Given $\\alpha, \\beta$, we wish to find $\\gamma$ such that $N(\\alpha/\\beta-\\gamma)<1$. Let $\\alpha/\\beta=x+y\\sqrt{-11},x,y\\in\\mathbb{Q},$ and $\\gamma=(u+v\\sqrt{-11})/2$ with $u, v\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ and $u\\equiv v$ (mod 2). We want\n$$N(x+y\\sqrt{-11}-(\\frac{u+v\\sqrt{-11}}{2}))<1$$\nor $(2x-u)^{2}+11(2y-v)^{2}<4$. As in the previous exercise, choose $v$ first to be the integer which is closest to $2y$, and then choose $u$ to be the integer closest to $2x$ which also has the same parity as $v$. Then $(2x-u)\\le1$ and $(2y-v)\\le1/2$ so\n$$(2x-u)^{2}+11(2y-v)^{2}\\le1+\\frac{11}{4}=\\frac{15}{4}<4.$$\nTherefore $\\mathbb{Z}[(1+\\sqrt{-11})/2]$ is Euclidean.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.5.3", "question": "Find all integer solutions to the equation $x^{2}+11=y^{3}$.", "solution": "In the ring $\\mathbb{Z}[(1+\\sqrt{-11})/2].$ we can factor the equation as\n$$(x-\\sqrt{-11})(x+\\sqrt{-11})=y^{3}.$$\nNow, suppose that $\\delta|(x-\\sqrt{-11})$ and $\\delta|(x+\\sqrt{-11})$ (which implies that $\\delta|y)$. Then $\\delta|2x$ and $\\delta|2\\sqrt{-11}$ which means that $\\delta|2$ because otherwise, $\\delta|\\sqrt{-11}$ meaning that $11$ and $11|y$, which we can see is not true by considering congruences mod $11^{2}$. Then $\\delta=1$ or 2, since 2 has no factorization in this ring. We will consider these cases separately.\nCase 1. $\\delta=1$. Then the two factors of $y^{3}$ are coprime and we can write $(x+\\sqrt{-11})=\\epsilon(\\frac{a+b\\sqrt{-11}}{2})^{3};$ where $a, b\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ and $a\\equiv b$ (mod 2). Since the units of $\\mathbb{Z}[(1+\\sqrt{-11})/2]$ are $\\pm1$, which are cubes, then we can bring the unit inside the brackets and rewrite the above without $\\epsilon$. We have\n$$8(x+\\sqrt{-11})=(a+b\\sqrt{-11})^{3}=a^{3}+3ab^{2}\\sqrt{-11}-33ab^{2}-11b^{3}\\sqrt{-11}$$\nand so, comparing real and imaginary parts, we get\n$$8x=a^{3}-33ab^{2}=a(a^{2}-33b^{2}), \\quad 8=3a^{2}b-11b^{3}=b(3a^{2}-11b^{2}).$$\nThis implies that $b|8$ and so we have 8 possibilities: $b=\\pm1,\\pm2,\\pm4,\\pm8.$ Substituting these back into the equations to find $a, x$, and $y$, and remembering that $a\\equiv b$ (mod 2) and that $a, x, y\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ will give all solutions to the equation.\nCase 2. $\\delta=2$. If $\\delta=2.$ then $y$ is even and $x$ is odd. We can write $y=2y_{1},$ which gives the equation\n$$(\\frac{x+\\sqrt{-11}}{2})(\\frac{x-\\sqrt{-11}}{2})=2y_{1}^{3}.$$\nSince 2 divides the right-hand side of this equation, it must divide the left-hand side, so $2|(\\frac{x+\\sqrt{-11}}{2})$ or $2|(\\frac{x-\\sqrt{-11}}{2})$. However, since $x$ is odd, 2 divides neither of the factors above. We conclude that $\\delta\\ne2$, and thus we found all the solutions to the equation in our discussion of Case 1.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.5.4", "question": "Prove that $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{3}]$ is Euclidean.", "solution": "Given $\\alpha,\\beta\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{3}]$ we want to find $\\gamma,\\delta\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{3}]$ such that $\\alpha=\\beta\\gamma+\\delta$, with $N(\\delta)<N(\\beta)$. Put another way, we want to show that $N(\\alpha/\\beta-\\gamma)<1$. Let $\\alpha/\\beta=x+y\\sqrt{3},x,y\\in\\mathbb{Q}$. Let $\\gamma=u+v\\sqrt{3}$ with $u,v\\in\\mathbb{Z}.$ Now, $N(\\alpha/\\beta-\\gamma)=|(x-u)^{2}-3(y-v)^{2}|$. This will be maximized when $(x-u)$ is small and $(y-v)$ is large. Choose for $u$ and $v$ the closest integers to $x$ and $y$, respectively. Then the minimum value for $(x-u)$ is 0, while the maximum value for $(y-v)$ is $1/2$. Then $N(\\alpha/\\beta-\\gamma)\\le|-3/4|<1$. The conclusion follows.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.5.5", "question": "Prove that $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{6}]$ is Euclidean.", "solution": "Assume that $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{6}]$ is not Euclidean. This means that there is at least one $x+y\\sqrt{6}\\in\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{6})$ such that there is no $\\gamma=u+v\\sqrt{6}\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{6}]$ such that $|(x-u)^{2}-6(y-v)^{2}|<1$. Without loss, we can suppose that $0\\le x\\le1/2$, and $0\\le y\\le1/2$. We assert that there exist such a pair $(x, y)$ such that $(x-u)^{2}\\ge1+6(y-v)^{2}$ or $6(y-v)^{2}\\ge1+(x-u)^{2}$ for every $u, v\\in\\mathbb{Z}.$ In particular, we will use the following inequalities:\n(2.1) either (a) $x^{2}\\ge1+6y^{2}$ or (b) $6y^{2}\\ge1+x^{2}$,\n(2.2) either (a) $(1-x)^{2}\\ge1+6y^{2}$ or (b) $6y^{2}\\ge1+(1-x)^{2}$,\n(2.3) either (a) $(1+x)^{2}\\ge1+6y^{2}$ or (b) $6y^{2}\\ge1+(1+x)^{2}$.\nIf $x=y=0$, then both first inequalities fail, so we can rule out this case. Next, we look at the first two inequalities on the left. Since $x^{2}$, $(1-x)^{2}\\le1$ and $1+6y^{2}\\ge1$ and $x, y$ are not both 0, these two inequalities fail so (2.1 (b)) and (2.2 (b)) must be true. Now consider (2.3 (a)). If $(1+x)^{2}\\ge1+6y^{2}$ and $6y^{2}\\ge1+(1-x)^{2}$ as we just showed, then $(1+x)^{2}\\ge1+6y^{2}\\ge2+(1-x)^{2}$ which implies that $4x\\ge2$ and since $x\\le1/2,$ we conclude that $x=1/2.$ Substituting this into the previous inequalities, we get that $\\frac{9}{4}\\ge1+6y^{2}\\ge\\frac{9}{4}$ so $6y^{2}=\\frac{5}{4}$. Let $y=r/s$ with $gcd(r,s)=1$. We now have that $24r^{2}=5s^{2}$. If $r|s$ then $r^{2}|5$, so $r=1$. But then $24=5s^{2}$ a contradiction. Therefore, (2.3 (b)) is true, which implies that $6y^{2}\\ge1+(1+x)^{2}\\ge2.$ However, since $y\\le1/2$, $6y^{2}\\ge2$ implies that $6\\ge8$, a contradiction. Then neither (2.3 (a)) nor (2.3 (b)) are true, so $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{6}]$ must be Euclidean.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.5.6", "question": "Show that $\\mathbb{Z}[(1+\\sqrt{-19})/2]$ is not Euclidean for the norm map.", "solution": "If a ring $R$ is Euclidean, then given any $\\alpha,\\beta\\in R$ we can find $\\gamma, \\delta$ such that $\\alpha=\\beta\\gamma+\\delta$ with $\\delta=0$ or $N(\\delta)<N(\\beta)$. Another way of describing this condition is to say that given any $\\beta\\in R$ we can find a representative for each nonzero residue class of $R/(\\beta)$ such that the representative has norm less than the norm of $\\beta$. We will try to find an element of $R=\\mathbb{Z}[(1+\\sqrt{-19})/2]$ for which this is not true.\nConsider $\\beta=2$. $N(2)=4$. We want to find all other elements of $R$ with norm strictly less than 4.\n$$N(\\frac{a+b\\sqrt{-19}}{2})=\\frac{a^{2}+19b^{2}}{4}<4, \\Rightarrow a^{2}+19b^{2}<16.$$\nFirst note that if $b>0,$ there are no solutions to this inequality. For $b=0$, we can have $a=0, \\pm2$, since $a\\equiv b$ (mod 2). Thus, there are just three elements with norm less than 4. However, there are more than three residue classes of $R/(2)$ (check this!). Therefore, the ring $R=\\mathbb{Z}[(1+\\sqrt{-19})/2]$ is non-Euclidean with respect to the norm map.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.5.7", "question": "Prove that $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-10}]$ is not a unique factorization domain.", "solution": "Consider the elements $2+\\sqrt{-10},2-\\sqrt{-10},2,7.$ Show that they are all irreducible and are not associates. Then note that\n$$(2+\\sqrt{-10})(2-\\sqrt{-10})=14$$\n$$2\\cdot7=14$$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.5.8", "question": "Show that there are only finitely many rings $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{d}]$ with $d\\equiv2$ or 3 (mod 4) which are norm Euclidean.", "solution": "If $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{d}]$ is Euclidean for the norm map, then for any $\\delta\\in\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})$, we can find $\\alpha\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{d}]$ such that $|N(\\delta-\\alpha)|<1$. Write $\\delta=r+s\\sqrt{d},$ $\\alpha=a+b\\sqrt{d},$ $a,b\\in\\mathbb{Z}$, $r,s\\in\\mathbb{Q}$. Then $|(r-a)^{2}-d(s-b)^{2}|<1.$ In particular, take $r=0$, $s=t/d$ where $t$ is an integer to be chosen later. Then $|a^{2}-d(b-\\frac{t}{d})^{2}|<1$ so that $|(bd-t)^{2}-da^{2}|<d.$ Since $(bd-t)^{2}-da^{2}\\equiv t^{2}$ (mod $d$), there are integers $x$ and $z$ such that $z^{2}-dx^{2}\\equiv t^{2}$ (mod $d$), with $|z^{2}-dx^{2}|<d.$\nIn case $d\\equiv3$ (mod 4), we choose an odd integer $t$ such that $5d<t^{2}<6d$, which we can do if $d$ is sufficiently large. Then $z^{2}-dx^{2}=t^{2}-5d$ or $t^{2}-6d$. Then one of the equations $z^{2}-t^{2}=d(x^{2}-5)$ or $z^{2}-t^{2}=d(x^{2}-6)$ is true. We consider this modulo 8. Then $t^{2}\\equiv1$ (mod 8) since $t$ is odd. Also, $x^{2}, z^{2}\\equiv0,1$ or 4 (mod 8) and $d\\equiv3$ or 7 (mod 8). We are easily led to $t^{2}-z^{2}\\equiv0,1,$ or 5 (mod 8). This means $d(x^{2}-5)\\equiv5,4,$ or 1 (mod 8) or $d(x^{2}-6)\\equiv6,5,2$, or 1 (mod 8). All of these congruences are impossible. In case $d\\equiv2$ (mod 4), we choose $t$ odd satisfying $2d<t^{2}<3d$ and proceed as above. (The case $d\\equiv1$ (mod 4) is more difficult and has been handled by Heilbronn who was the first to show that there are only finitely many real quadratic fields which are norm-Euclidean.) A more general and analogous result for imaginary quadratic fields will be proved in Exercise 4.5.21 in Chapter 4.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.5.9", "question": "Find all integer solutions of $y^{2}=x^{3}+1$.", "solution": "We will determine all integer solutions of $y^{2}-1=x^{3}$. From $(y-1)(y+1)=x^{3}$, we see that if $(y-1,y+1)=1$, then $y-1=u^{3}$, $y+1=v^{3}$ (say). Thus, $2=v^{3}-u^{3}=(v-u)(v^{2}+vu+u^{2})$ from which we deduce that $v-u=\\pm1, v^{2}+vu+u^{2}=\\pm2$ or $v-u=\\pm2, v^{2}+vu+u^{2}=\\pm1$. This gives rise to four cases. The only case that leads to a solution is $v-u=2$ and $v^{2}+vu+u^{2}=1.$ This yields the solution $(x,y)=(-1,0)$.\nNow suppose $(y-1,y+1)=2.$ This gives rise to two cases $y-1=2u^{3}, y+1=4v^{3}$ and $y-1=4u^{3}, y+1=2v^{3}$. In the first case, we are led to $u^{3}+1=2v^{3}$ and in the second case, we get $2u^{3}+1=v^{3}$. As 1 is a cube, both equations are covered if we can determine all integer solutions of $x^{3}+y^{3}=2z^{3}$. We will use a \"descent\" argument to determine all coprime solutions. To this end, we consider the ring of Eisenstein integers $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$ where $\\rho^{2}+\\rho+1=0$. It is well-known that this is a Euclidean domain for the norm map given by $N(a+b\\rho)=a^{2}+ab+b^{2}$. Its unit group is $\\{\\pm1,\\pm\\rho,\\pm\\rho^{2}\\}$. It is also easily checked that 1, $\\rho$, $\\rho^{2}$ represent all the distinct coprime residue classes modulo $2\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$. We see that the cube of every coprime residue class is 1 (modulo 2). If $u$ is a unit $\\equiv 1$ (mod 2), then $u=\\pm1$. Now we claim that any coprime solution $(x,y,z)$ of $x^{3}+y^{3}=2uz^{3}$ in $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$ satisfies $N(xyz)=1$. Suppose not. Let $(x, y, z)$ be such that $N(xyz)$ is minimal and $\\ge2$. We may let $A=x+y$, $B=\\rho x+\\rho^{2}y$, $C=\\rho^{2}x+\\rho y$ so that $ABC=2uz^{3}$, $A+B+C=0$. Let $d=(A,B,C)$ so that the above equation becomes $\\frac{A}{d}\\frac{B}{d}\\frac{C}{d}=2u(\\frac{z}{d})^{3}$. Now 2 is an irreducible element in $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$ and $A/d, B/d, C/d$ are mutually coprime (as their sum is zero) so it can divide only one of them, say $C/d$ without any loss of generality. Thus, we may write $A/d=u_{1}\\alpha^{3}$, $B/d=u_{2}\\beta^{3}$, $C/d=-2u_{3}\\gamma^{3}$, with $u_{1}$, $u_{2}$, $u_{3}$ units. Also, $\\alpha\\beta\\gamma\\ne0$ for otherwise, $z=0$ and $x=\\pm y$, which are not coprime solutions. Hence, $u_{1}\\alpha^{3}+u_{2}\\beta^{3}=2u_{3}\\gamma^{3}$ and dividing by the unit $u_{1}$ gives the equation $\\alpha^{3}+u^{\\prime}\\beta^{3}=2u_{4}\\gamma^{3}$ for some units $u^{\\prime}$ and $u_{4}$. Observe that $(\\beta,2)=1$ for otherwise, $2|\\alpha$ and $2|\\gamma$ which implies that $\\alpha, \\beta, \\gamma$ are not coprime, a contradiction. Reducing the above equation mod 2 shows that $u^{\\prime}$ is a cube mod 2, and by our remark above $u^{\\prime}$ must be $\\pm1$. Thus $u^{\\prime}$ is a cube and we have $\\alpha^{3}+\\beta^{3}=2u\\gamma^{3}$. Notice that by our choice of $(x,y,z)$, $N(xyz)^{3}\\le N(\\alpha\\beta\\gamma)^{3}=N(ABC/d^{3})=N(z)^{3}/N(d)^{3}$ which means that $N(xyd)^{3}\\le1$. Thus, $x, y, d$ are units. Hence, $x^{3}=\\pm1$ and $y^{3}=\\pm1$ and $z$ is also a unit. Thus, $N(xyz)=1$ contrary to our choice. This proves our claim. Therefore, the only solution for $u^{3}+1=2v^{3}$ is $u^{3}=\\pm1$. This leads to the solutions $(x,y)=(2,3),(1,0)$ for the equation $y^{2}-1=x^{3}$. In the other case of $2u^{3}+1=v^{3}$, we have $v=\\pm1$ which leads to (0,1), (2, -3). We get a final set of five integer solutions for $y^{2}-1=x^{3}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 2.5.10", "question": "Let $x_{1},...,x_{n}$ be indeterminates. Evaluate the determinant of the $n\\times n$ matrix whose $(i, j)$-th entry is $x_{i}^{j-1}$. (This is called the Vandermonde determinant.)", "solution": "Let $V(x_{1},...,x_{n})$ denote the value of the determinant. If we fix $x_{2},...,x_{n}$ we may view the determinant as a polynomial in $x_{1}$ of degree $n-1$. Since the determinant is zero if $x_{1}=x_{i}$ for $i\\ge2$, the roots of the polynomial are $x_{2},...,x_{n}$. It is easy to see that the leading coefficient is $(-1)^{n-1}V(x_{2},...,x_{n})$ so that the determinant is $(-1)^{n-1}V(x_{2},...,x_{n})\\prod_{j=2}^{n}(x_{1}-x_{j}).$ By induction, we see that $V(x_{1},...,x_{n})=(-1)^{\\binom{n}{2}}\\prod_{j>i}(x_{i}-x_{j}).$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Example 3.1.1", "question": "Show that $\\sqrt{2}/3$ is an algebraic number but not an algebraic integer.", "solution": "Consider the polynomial $f(x)=9x^{2}-2$, which is in $\\mathbb{Q}[x]$. Since $f(\\sqrt{2}/3)=0$, we know that $\\sqrt{2}/3$ is an algebraic number.\nAssume $\\sqrt{2}/3$ is an algebraic integer. Then there exists a monic polynomial in $\\mathbb{Z}[x]$, say $g(x)=x^{n}+b_{n-1}x^{n-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+b_{0}$ which has $\\alpha=\\sqrt{2}/3$ as a root. So\n$$g(\\alpha)=(\\frac{\\sqrt{2}}{3})^{n}+b_{n-1}(\\frac{\\sqrt{2}}{3})^{n-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+b_{0}=0,$$\n$$\\Rightarrow (\\sqrt{2})^{n}+b_{n-1}(\\sqrt{2})^{n-1}(3)+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+b_{0}(3)^{n}=0.$$\nIf $i$ is odd, $(\\sqrt{2})^{i}$ is not an integer. So we can separate our equation into two smaller equations:\n$$\\sum_{i~odd}b_{i}\\sqrt{2}^{i}3^{n-i}=0\\Rightarrow\\sqrt{2}\\sum_{i~odd}b_{i}2^{(i-1)/2}3^{n-i}=0$$\nand\n$$\\sum_{i~even}b_{i}\\sqrt{2}^{i}3^{n-i}=0$$\nfor $i=0,...,n.$ Since $3|0$ each sum above must be divisible by 3. In particular, because each summand containing $b_{i},i\\ne n$ has a factor of 3, 3 divides the summand containing $b_{n}=1$. This tells us that $3|2^{(n-1)/2}$ if $n$ is odd, and $2^{n/2}$ if $n$ is even. In either case, this is false and hence we can conclude that $\\sqrt{2}/3$ is not an algebraic integer.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 3.1.4", "question": "Let $\\alpha$ be an algebraic number. Show that there exists a unique polynomial $p(x)$ in $\\mathbb{Q}[x]$ which is monic, irreducible and of smallest degree, such that $p(\\alpha)=0$. Furthermore, show that if $f(x)\\in\\mathbb{Q}[x]$ and $f(\\alpha)=0$, then $p(x)|f(x)$.", "solution": "Consider the set of all polynomials in $\\mathbb{Q}[x]$ for which $\\alpha$ is a root and pick one of smallest degree, say $p(x)$. If $p(x)$ is not irreducible, it can be written as a product of two lower degree polynomials in $\\mathbb{Q}[x]$: $p(x)=a(x)b(x)$. However, $p(\\alpha)=a(\\alpha)b(\\alpha)=0$ and since $\\mathbb{C}$ is an integral domain, either $a(\\alpha)=0$ or $b(\\alpha)=0$. But this contradicts the minimality of $p(x)$, so $p(x)$ must be irreducible.\nSuppose there were two such polynomials, $p(x)$ and $q(x)$. By the division algorithm,\n$$p(x)=a(x)q(x)+r(x),$$\nwhere $a(x)$, $r(x)\\in\\mathbb{Q}[x]$, and either $deg(r)=0$ or $deg(r)<deg(q)$. But $p(\\alpha)=a(\\alpha)q(\\alpha)+r(\\alpha)=0$ and $q(\\alpha)=0$ together imply that $r(\\alpha)=0$. Because $p(x)$ and $q(x)$ are the smallest degree polynomials with $\\alpha$ as a root, $r=0$. So $p(x)=a(x)q(x)$ and $a(x)\\in\\mathbb{Q}^{*}$ (the set of all nonzero elements of $\\mathbb{Q}$), since $deg(p)=deg(q)$. Thus $p(x)$ is unique up to a constant and so we may suppose its leading coefficient is 1.\nNow suppose $f(x)$ is a polynomial in $\\mathbb{Q}[x]$ such that $f(\\alpha)=0$. If $p(x)$ does not divide $f(x)$ then, since $p(x)$ is irreducible, $gcd(p(x), f(x)) = 1$. So we can find $a(x), b(x)\\in\\mathbb{Q}[x]$ such that $a(x)p(x)+b(x)f(x)=1$. However, putting $x=\\alpha$ yields a contradiction. Thus, $p(x)|f(x)$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Example 3.1.5", "question": "Show that the set of algebraic numbers is countable (and hence the set of transcendental numbers is uncountable).", "solution": "All polynomials in $\\mathbb{Q}[x]$ have a finite number of roots. The set of rational numbers, $\\mathbb{Q}$, is countable and so the set $\\mathbb{Q}[x]$ is also countable. The set of algebraic numbers is the set of all roots of a countable number of polynomials, each with a finite number of roots. Hence the set of algebraic numbers is countable. Since algebraic numbers and transcendental numbers partition the set of complex numbers, $\\mathbb{C}$, which is uncountable, it follows that the set of transcendental numbers is uncountable.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 3.2.1 (Liouville)", "question": "Given $\\alpha$, a real algebraic number of degree $n\\ne1$, show that there is a positive constant $c=c(\\alpha)$ such that for all rational numbers $p/q$, $(p,q)=1$ and $q>0$, the inequality $|\\alpha-\\frac{p}{q}|>\\frac{c(\\alpha)}{q^{n}}$ holds.", "solution": "Let $f(x)=a_{n}x^{n}+a_{n-1}x^{n-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{0}\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x]$ whose degree equals that of $\\alpha$ and for which $\\alpha$ is a root. ($So~deg(f)\\ge2$). Notice that\n$$|f(\\alpha)-f(\\frac{p}{q})|=|f(\\frac{p}{q})|$$\n$$=|a_{n}(\\frac{p}{q})^{n}+a_{n-1}(\\frac{p}{q})^{n-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{0}|$$\n$$=|\\frac{a_{n}p^{n}+a_{n-1}p^{n-1}q+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{0}q^{n}}{q^{n}}| \\ge\\frac{1}{q^{n}}.$$\nIf $\\alpha=\\alpha_{1},...,\\alpha_{n}$ are the roots of $f$, let $M$ be the maximum of the values $|\\alpha_{i}|$, $1\\le i\\le n$. If $|p/q|$ is greater than $2M$, then\n$$|\\alpha-\\frac{p}{q}|\\ge M\\ge\\frac{M}{q^{n}}.$$\nIf $|p/q|\\le M$ then $|\\alpha_{i}-\\frac{p}{q}|\\le3M$ so that\n$$|\\alpha-\\frac{p}{q}|\\ge\\frac{1}{|a_{n}|q^{n}\\prod_{j=2}^{n}|\\alpha_{j}-p/q|}\\ge\\frac{1}{|a_{n}|(3M)^{n-1}q^{n}}.$$\nHence, the theorem holds with $c(\\alpha)=min(M,\\frac{1}{|a_{n}|(3M)^{n-1}})$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Example 3.2.2", "question": "Show that $\\sum_{n=0}^{\\infty}\\frac{1}{10^{n!}}$ is transcendental.", "solution": "Suppose not, and call the sum $\\alpha$. Look at the partial sum $\\sum_{n=0}^{k}\\frac{1}{10^{n!}}=\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}},$ with $q_{k}=10^{k!}$. Thus,\n$$|\\alpha-\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}}|=|\\sum_{n=k+1}^{\\infty}\\frac{1}{10^{n!}}|$$\n$$=\\frac{1}{10^{(k+1)!}}+(\\frac{1}{10^{(k+1)!}})^{k+2}+(\\frac{1}{10^{(k+1)!}})^{(k+2)(k+3)}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot$$\n$$\\le\\frac{1}{10^{(k+1)!}}[1+\\frac{1}{10^{2}}+\\frac{1}{10^{3}}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot] =(\\frac{1}{10^{(k+1)!}})S,$$\nwhere $S=1+1/10^{2}+1/10^{3}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot,$ an infinite geometric series which has a finite sum. So\n$$|\\sum_{n=k+1}^{\\infty}\\frac{1}{10^{n!}}|\\le\\frac{S}{10^{(k+1)!}}=\\frac{S}{q_{k}^{k+1}}.$$\nIf $\\alpha$ were algebraic of degree of $n$ then, by Liouville's theorem, there exists a constant $c(\\alpha)$ such that $|\\alpha-\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}}|\\ge\\frac{c(\\alpha)}{q_{k}^{n}},$ so we have $\\frac{S}{q_{k}^{k+1}}\\ge\\frac{c(\\alpha)}{q_{k}^{n}}.$ However, we can choose $k$ to be as large as we want to obtain a contradiction. So $\\alpha$ is transcendental.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Example 3.2.3", "question": "Let $f(x,y)$ be an irreducible polynomial of binary form of degree $n\\ge3$. Assuming Thue's theorem, show that $f(x,y)=m$ for any fixed $m\\in\\mathbb{Z}^{*}$ has only finitely many solutions.", "solution": "Suppose $f(x,y)=m$ has infinitely many solutions, and write it in the form\n$$f(x,y)=\\prod_{i=1}^{n}(x-\\alpha_{i}y)=m,$$\nwhere $\\alpha_{i}$ is an algebraic number of degree $\\ge3$ $\\forall i=1,...,n.$ Without loss of generality, we can suppose that for an infinite number of pairs $(x, y)$, we have\n$$|\\frac{x}{y}-\\alpha_{1}|\\le|\\frac{x}{y}-\\alpha_{i}| \\text{ for } i=2,...,n.$$\nFurther, by the triangle inequality,\n$$|\\frac{x}{y}-\\alpha_{i}|\\ge\\frac{1}{2}(|\\frac{x}{y}-\\alpha_{i}|+|\\frac{x}{y}-\\alpha_{1}|) \\ge\\frac{1}{2}|\\alpha_{i}-\\alpha_{1}| \\text{ for } i=2,...,n$$\nHence,\n$$|f(x,y)|=|y^{n}||\\frac{x}{y}-\\alpha_{1}|\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot|\\frac{x}{y}-\\alpha_{n}|$$\n$$|m|\\ge k|y|^{n}|\\frac{x}{y}-\\alpha_{1}|$$\nwhere $k=\\frac{1}{2^{n-1}}\\prod_{i=2}^{n}|\\alpha_{i}-\\alpha_{1}|.$ So $\\frac{|m|}{k|y|^{n}}\\ge|\\frac{x}{y}-\\alpha_{1}|$.\nHowever, by Thue's theorem, this implies\n$$\\frac{c}{y^{n/2+1}}\\le\\frac{m}{ky^{n}}\\Leftrightarrow\\frac{1}{y^{n/2+1}}\\le\\frac{m(ck)^{-1}}{y^{n}}$$\nHowever, for $n\\ge3$ this holds for only finitely many $(x, y)$, contradicting our assumption. Thus $f(x,y)$ has only finitely many solutions.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Example 3.3.1", "question": "Let $\\alpha$ be an algebraic number and define $\\mathbb{Q}[\\alpha]=\\{f(\\alpha):f\\in\\mathbb{Q}[x]\\}$ a subring of $\\mathbb{C}$. Show that $\\mathbb{Q}[\\alpha]$ is a field.", "solution": "Let $f$ be the minimal polynomial of $\\alpha$, and consider the map $\\phi:\\mathbb{Q}[x]\\rightarrow\\mathbb{Q}[\\alpha]$ such that $\\sum_{i=0}^{n}a_{i}x^{i}\\rightarrow\\sum_{i=0}^{n}a_{i}\\alpha^{i}.$ Notice that\n$$\\phi(g)+\\phi(h)=\\sum_{i=0}^{n}a_{i}\\alpha^{i}+\\sum_{i=0}^{m}b_{i}\\alpha^{i}=\\phi(g+h)$$\nand\n$$\\phi(g)\\phi(h)=(\\sum_{i=0}^{n}a_{i}\\alpha^{i})(\\sum_{j=0}^{m}b_{j}\\alpha^{j})=\\sum_{0\\le i+j\\le n+m}a_{i}b_{j}\\alpha^{i+j}=\\phi(gh).$$\nSo $\\phi$ is a homomorphism. Furthermore, it is clear that ker $\\phi=(f)$, the ideal generated by $f$ (see Theorem 3.1.4). Thus, by the ring homomorphism theorems, $\\mathbb{Q}[x]/(f)\\simeq\\mathbb{Q}[\\alpha]$.\nLet $g$ be a polynomial in $\\mathbb{Q}[x]$ such that $f$ does not divide $g$. From Chapter 2, we know that $\\mathbb{Q}[x]$ is a Euclidean domain and is therefore also a PID. We also learned in Chapter 2 that the ideal generated by any irreducible element in a PID is a maximal ideal. Since $f$ is irreducible, $\\mathbb{Q}[x]/(f)$ is a field and so $\\mathbb{Q}[\\alpha]$ is a field, as desired.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 3.3.2 (Theorem of the Primitive Element)", "question": "Show that if $\\alpha$ and $\\beta$ are algebraic numbers, then $\\exists\\theta$, an algebraic number, such that $\\mathbb{Q}(\\alpha,\\beta)=\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$.", "solution": "Let $f$ be the minimal polynomial of $\\alpha$ and let $g$ be the minimal polynomial of $\\beta$. We want to show that we can find $\\lambda\\in\\mathbb{Q}$ such that $\\theta=\\alpha+\\lambda\\beta$ and $\\mathbb{Q}(\\alpha,\\beta)=\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$. We will denote $\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$ by $L$. Clearly $L=\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)\\subseteq\\mathbb{Q}(\\alpha,\\beta)$.\nDefine $\\phi(x)=f(\\theta-\\lambda x)\\in L[x]$. Notice that $\\phi(\\beta)=f(\\theta-\\lambda\\beta)=f(\\alpha)=0$. So $\\beta$ is a root of $\\phi$. Choose $\\lambda\\in\\mathbb{Q}$ in such a way that $\\beta$ is the only common root of $\\phi$ and $g$. This can be done since only a finite number of choices of $\\lambda$ are thus ruled out. So $gcd(\\phi(x),g(x))=c(x-\\beta)$, $c\\in\\mathbb{C}^{*}$. Then $c(x-\\beta)\\in L[x]$ which implies that $c, c\\beta\\in L$, and so $\\beta\\in L$.\nNow, $\\theta=\\alpha+\\lambda\\beta\\in L$ which means that $\\alpha\\in L$. So $\\mathbb{Q}(\\alpha,\\beta)\\subseteq L=\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$. Thus, we have the desired equality: $\\mathbb{Q}(\\alpha,\\beta)=\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 3.3.9", "question": "Prove that the following statements are equivalent:\n(a) $\\alpha$ is an algebraic integer.\n(b) The minimal polynomial of $\\alpha$ is monic $\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x]$.\n(c) $\\mathbb{Z}[\\alpha]$ is a finitely generated $\\mathbb{Z}$-module.\n(d) There exists a finitely generated $\\mathbb{Z}$-submodule $M\\ne\\{0\\}$ of $\\mathbb{C}$ such that $\\alpha M\\subseteq M.$", "solution": "$(a)\\Rightarrow(b)$ Let $f(x)$ be a monic polynomial in $\\mathbb{Z}[x]$ such that $f(\\alpha)=0$. Let $\\phi(x)$ be the minimal polynomial of $\\alpha$. Recall the definition of primitive polynomials given in Chapter 2: a polynomial $f(x)=a_{n}x^{n}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{0}\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x]$ is said to be primitive if the gcd of the coefficients of $f$ is 1. In particular, a monic polynomial is primitive. By Theorem 3.1.4, we know $f(x)=\\phi(x)\\psi(x)$, for some $\\psi(x)\\in\\mathbb{Q}[x]$. By the proof of Theorem 2.1.10, we know we can write $\\phi(x)=\\frac{a}{b}\\phi_{1}(x)$, $\\phi_{1}(x)$ primitive, $a, b\\in\\mathbb{Z}$, and $\\psi(x)=\\frac{c}{d}\\psi_{1}(x)$, $\\psi_{1}(x)$ primitive, $c, d\\in\\mathbb{Z}$. So $bdf(x)=ac\\phi_{1}(x)\\psi_{1}(x)$. But by Gauss' lemma (see Theorem 2.1.9), $\\phi_{1}(x)\\psi_{1}(x)$ is primitive, and $f(x)$ is primitive, so $bd=\\pm ac$ and $f(x)=\\pm\\phi_{1}(x)\\psi_{1}(x)$. Thus the leading term of both $\\phi_{1}(x)$ and $\\psi_{1}(x)$ is $\\pm1$. Further, $\\phi(\\alpha)=0\\Rightarrow\\phi_{1}(\\alpha)=0$. So in fact $\\phi(x)=\\pm\\phi_{1}(x)$ which is monic in $\\mathbb{Z}[x]$.\n$(b)\\Rightarrow(c)$ Let $\\phi(x)=x^{n}+a_{n-1}x^{n-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{0}\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x]$ be the minimal polynomial of $\\alpha$. Recall $\\mathbb{Z}[\\alpha]=\\{f(\\alpha):f(x)\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x]\\}$. In order to prove (c), it is enough to find a finite basis for $\\mathbb{Z}[\\alpha]$. Claim: $\\{1,\\alpha,...,\\alpha^{n-1}\\}$ generates $\\mathbb{Z}[\\alpha]$ (as a $\\mathbb{Z}$-module). Proof: It suffices to show that $\\alpha^{N}$ for any $N\\in\\mathbb{Z}^{+}$, is a linear combination of $\\{1,\\alpha,...,\\alpha^{n-1}\\}$ with coefficients in $\\mathbb{Z}$. We proceed inductively. Clearly this holds for $N\\le n-1$. For $N\\ge n$, suppose this holds $\\forall\\alpha^{j}$, $j<N$. $\\alpha^{N}=\\alpha^{N-n}\\alpha^{n}=\\alpha^{N-n}[-(a_{0}+a_{1}\\alpha+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{n-1}\\alpha^{n-1})] =(-\\alpha^{N-n}a_{0})1+(-\\alpha^{N-n}a_{1})\\alpha+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+(-\\alpha^{N-n}a_{n-1})\\alpha^{n-1}$. By our inductive hypothesis, $-\\alpha^{N-n}a_{i}\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\alpha]\\forall i=0,1,...,n-1.$ Then $\\mathbb{Z}[\\alpha]$ is a $\\mathbb{Z}$-module generated by $\\{1,\\alpha,...,\\alpha^{n-1}\\}$.\n$(c)\\Rightarrow(d)$ Let $M=\\mathbb{Z}[\\alpha]$. Clearly $\\alpha\\mathbb{Z}[\\alpha]\\subseteq\\mathbb{Z}[\\alpha]$.\n$(d)\\Rightarrow(a)$ Let $x_1,...,x_r$ generate $M$ over $\\mathbb{Z}$. So $M\\subseteq\\mathbb{Z}x_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}x_{r}$. By assumption $\\alpha x_{i}\\in M\\forall i=1,...,r.$ It follows that there exists a set of $c_{ij}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ such that $\\alpha x_{i}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}c_{ij}x_{j}\\forall i=1,...,r$. Let $C=(c_{ij})$. Then $(C-\\alpha I)(\\begin{matrix}x_{1}\\\\ \\vdots\\\\ x_{r}\\end{matrix})=0.$ Since not all of $x_{1},...,x_{r}$ can vanish, $det(C-\\alpha I)=0$. In other words,\n$$\\begin{bmatrix}c_{11}-x&c_{12}&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&c_{1n}\\\\ c_{21}&c_{22}-x&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&c_{2n}\\\\ \\vdots&&&&\\vdots\\\\ c_{n1}&c_{n2}&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&c_{nn}-x\\end{bmatrix}=0 \\text{ when } x=\\alpha$$\nThis is a polynomial equation in $\\mathbb{Z}[x]$ of degree $n$ whose leading coefficient is $(-1)^{n}$. Take $f(x)=det(C-xI)$ for $n$ even, and $-det(C-xI)$ for $n$ odd. Then $f(x)$ is a monic polynomial in $\\mathbb{Z}[x]$ such that $f(\\alpha)=0$. Thus $\\alpha$ is an algebraic integer.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Example 3.3.10", "question": "Let $K$ be an algebraic number field. Let $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ be the set of all algebraic integers in $K$. Show that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ is a ring.", "solution": "From the above theorem, we know that for $\\alpha, \\beta$, algebraic integers, $\\mathbb{Z}[\\alpha]$, $\\mathbb{Z}[\\beta]$ are finitely generated $\\mathbb{Z}$-modules. Thus $M=\\mathbb{Z}[\\alpha,\\beta]$ is also a finitely generated $\\mathbb{Z}$-module. Moreover, $(\\alpha\\pm\\beta)M\\subseteq M$, and $(\\alpha\\beta)M\\subseteq M.$ So $\\alpha\\pm\\beta$ and $\\alpha\\beta$ are algebraic integers; i.e., $\\alpha\\pm\\beta$ and $\\alpha\\beta$ are in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. So $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ is a ring.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.1.2", "question": "Show that $r\\in\\mathbb{Q}$ is an algebraic integer, then $r\\in\\mathbb{Z}$.", "solution": "Let $r=c/d$, $(c,d)=1$ be an algebraic integer. Then $r$ is the root of a monic polynomial in $\\mathbb{Z}[x]$, say $f(x)=x^{n}+b_{n-1}x^{n-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+b_{0}$. So\n$$f(r)=(\\frac{c}{d})^{n}+b_{n-1}(\\frac{c}{d})^{n-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+b_{0}=0$$\n$$c^{n}+b_{n-1}c^{n-1}d+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+b_{0}d^{n}=0$$\nThis implies that $d|c^n$, which is true only when $d=\\pm1$. So $r=\\pm c\\in\\mathbb{Z}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.1.3", "question": "Show that if $4|(d+1)$, then $\\frac{-1\\pm\\sqrt{-d}}{2}$ is an algebraic integer.", "solution": "Consider the monic polynomial\n$$x^{2}+x+\\frac{d+1}{4}\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x]$$\nwhen $4|d+1$. The roots of this polynomial, which by definition are algebraic integers, are\n$$x=\\frac{-1\\pm\\sqrt{1-4\\frac{d+1}{4}}}{2}=\\frac{-1\\pm\\sqrt{-d}}{2}.$$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.1.6", "question": "Find the minimal polynomial of $\\sqrt{n}$ where $n$ is a squarefree integer.", "solution": "If $n=1$, the minimal polynomial is $x-1$. If $n\\ne1$ then $x^{2}-n$ is irreducible and has $\\sqrt{n}$ as a root. Thus, the minimal polynomial is either linear or quadratic. If it is linear, we obtain that $\\sqrt{n}$ is rational, a contradiction. Thus, $x^{2}-n$ is the minimal polynomial of $\\sqrt{n}$ when $n\\ne1$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.1.7", "question": "Find the minimal polynomial of $\\sqrt{2}/3$.", "solution": "It is $x^{2}-2/9$ since $\\sqrt{2}/3$ is a root, and $\\sqrt{2}/3$ is not rational.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.2.4", "question": "Show that $\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}2^{-3^{n}}$ is transcendental.", "solution": "Suppose that\n$$\\alpha=\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{1}{2^{3^{n}}}$$\nis algebraic. We proceed as in Example 3.2.2 and consider the partial sum:\n$$\\sum_{n=1}^{k}\\frac{1}{2^{3^{n}}}=\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}},$$\nwith $q_{k}=2^{3^{k}}$. As before,\n$$|\\alpha-\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}}|=|\\sum_{n=k+1}^{\\infty}\\frac{1}{2^{3^{n}}}|\\le\\frac{S}{2^{3^{k+1}}}.$$\nBut since $\\alpha$ is algebraic, by Roth's theorem we have the inequality\n$$\\frac{S}{q_{k}^{3}}\\ge\\frac{c(\\alpha)}{q_{k}^{2+\\epsilon}}.$$\nBut again we can choose $k$ to be as large as we want, and so for $\\epsilon$ sufficiently small, this inequality does not hold. Thus, $\\alpha$ is transcendental.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.2.5", "question": "Show that, in fact, $\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}2^{-f(n)}$ is transcendental when\n$$lim_{n\\rightarrow\\infty}\\frac{f(n+1)}{f(n)}>2.$$", "solution": "Suppose\n$$\\alpha=\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{1}{2^{f(n)}}$$\nis algebraic. Following the same argument as above, we get the inequalities\n$$\\frac{S}{q_{k+1}}\\ge|\\alpha-\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}}|\\ge\\frac{c(\\alpha)}{q_{k}^{2+\\epsilon}},$$\nwhere $q_{k}=2^{f(k)}$. Now, for $k$ sufficiently large,\n$$\\frac{f(k+1)}{f(k)}>2+\\delta\\Rightarrow f(k+1)>(2+\\delta)f(k).$$\nSo, for large $k$,\n$$\\frac{q_{k+1}}{q_{k}}=\\frac{2^{f(k+1)}}{2^{f(k)}}>2^{(1+\\delta)f(k)}=q_{k}^{(1+\\delta)}$$\nwhich implies that $q_{k+1}>q_{k}^{2+\\delta}$. By Roth's theorem, we can deduce that\n$$\\frac{c(\\alpha)}{q_{k}^{2+\\epsilon}}\\le\\frac{S}{q_{k+1}} \\Rightarrow \\frac{c(\\alpha)}{q_{k}^{2+\\epsilon}}\\le\\frac{S}{q_{k}^{2+\\delta}},$$\n$$q_{k}^{\\delta}\\le\\frac{S}{c(\\alpha)}q_{k}^{\\epsilon}$$\nAs $q_{k}\\rightarrow\\infty$ this implies $\\delta\\le\\epsilon$, a contradiction for $\\epsilon<\\delta/2$ (say).", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.3.3", "question": "Let $\\alpha$ be an algebraic number and let $p(x)$ be its minimal polynomial. Show that $p(x)$ has no repeated roots.", "solution": "Suppose $\\alpha$ is a repeated root of $p(x)$. Then we can write\n$$p(x)=(x-\\alpha)^{2}g(x),$$\nfor some polynomial $g(x)\\in\\mathbb{C}[x]$, and\n$$p^{\\prime}(x)=2(x-\\alpha)g(x)+(x-\\alpha)^{2}g^{\\prime}(x).$$\nSo $p^{\\prime}(\\alpha)=0$ and from Theorem 3.1.4, $p(x)|p^{\\prime}(x)$. But $deg(p^{\\prime})<deg(p)$, and we have a contradiction. If $\\beta$ is a repeated root of $p(x)$ then by the following exercise, $\\beta$ has the same minimal polynomial and repeating the above argument with $\\beta$ leads to a contradiction. Thus $p$ has no repeated roots.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.3.4", "question": "Let $\\alpha, \\beta$ be algebraic numbers such that $\\beta$ is conjugate to $\\alpha$. Show that $\\beta$ and $\\alpha$ have the same minimal polynomial.", "solution": "Let $p(x)$ be the minimal polynomial of $\\alpha$, and let $q(x)$ be the minimal polynomial of $\\beta$. By the definition of conjugate roots, $\\beta$ is a common root of $p(x)$ and $q(x)$.\nUsing the division algorithm, we can write $p(x)=a(x)q(x)+r(x)$ for some $a(x)$, $r(x)\\in\\mathbb{Q}[x]$ and either $r=0$ or $deg(r)<deg(q)$. But\n$$p(\\beta)=a(\\beta)q(\\beta)+r(\\beta)=0$$\nand $q(\\beta)=0$ so $r(\\beta)$ must also be 0. Since $q$ is the minimal polynomial for $\\beta$, $r=0$. Thus $p(x)=a(x)q(x)$, but, by Theorem 3.1.4, $p$ is irreducible, and both $p(x)$ and $q(x)$ are monic, so $p(x)=q(x)$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.3.6", "question": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$ be of degree $n$ over $\\mathbb{Q}$. Let $\\omega_{1},...,\\omega_{n}$ be a basis of $K$ as a vector space over $\\mathbb{Q}$. Show that the matrix $\\Omega=(\\omega_{i}^{(j)})$ is invertible.", "solution": "$$\\Omega=(\\begin{matrix}\\omega_{1}&\\omega_{1}^{(2)}&...&\\omega_{1}^{(n)}\\\\ \\omega_{2}&\\omega_{2}^{(2)}&...&\\omega_{2}^{(n)}\\\\ \\vdots&\\vdots&\\vdots\\\\ \\omega_{n}&\\omega_{n}^{(2)}&...&\\omega_{n}^{(n)}\\end{matrix}).$$\nSince $\\theta$ is an algebraic number of degree $n$, $\\alpha_{1}=1,\\alpha_{2}=\\theta,...,\\alpha_{n}=\\theta^{n-1}$ also forms a basis for $K$ over $\\mathbb{Q}$. Let $A=(\\alpha_{i}^{(j)})$. Then,\n$$det~A=|\\begin{matrix}1&1&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&1\\\\ \\theta&\\theta^{(2)}&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&\\theta^{(n)}\\\\ \\vdots&&&\\vdots\\\\ \\theta^{n-1}&\\theta^{(2)n-1}&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&\\theta^{(n)n-1}\\end{matrix}|$$\nwhich is the Vandermonde determinant. So $A$ is invertible. Further,\n$$\\omega_{i}^{(j)}=\\sum_{k=1}^{n}(b_{ik}\\alpha_{k})^{(j)}=\\sum_{k=1}^{n}b_{ik}\\alpha_{k}^{(j)},$$\nwhere $1\\le i, j\\le n$ and $b_{ik}\\in\\mathbb{Q}$. Since the set $\\{\\omega_{1},...,\\omega_{n}\\}$, as well as the set $\\{\\alpha_{1},...,\\alpha_{n}\\}$, are linearly independent sets, it follows that both the rows and columns of the matrix $B=(b_{ik})$ are linearly independent. Hence $B$ is invertible and $\\Omega=BA$ and from elementary linear algebra, det $\\Omega=$ det $B$ det $A\\ne0$. Thus $\\Omega$ is invertible.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.3.7", "question": "Let $\\alpha$ be an algebraic number. Show that there exists $m\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ such that $m\\alpha$ is an algebraic integer.", "solution": "Let $p(x)\\in\\mathbb{Q}[x]$ be the minimal polynomial of $\\alpha$. So,\n$$p(\\alpha)=\\alpha^{n}+a_{n-1}\\alpha^{n-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{1}\\alpha+a_{0}=0.$$\nChoose $m\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ so that $ma_{0},ma_{1},...,ma_{n-1}$ are all integers. Now,\n$$m^{n}\\alpha^{n}+m^{n}a_{n-1}\\alpha^{n-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+m^{n}a_{1}\\alpha+m^{n}a_{0}=0,$$\n$$\\Rightarrow(m\\alpha)^{n}+ma_{n-1}(m\\alpha)^{n-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+m^{n-1}a_{1}(m\\alpha)+m^{n}a_{0}=0.$$\nLet $g(x)=x^{n}+ma_{n-1}x^{n-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+m^{n-1}a_{1}x+m^{n}a_{0}$, then $g(x)$ is a monic polynomial in $\\mathbb{Z}[x]$ and $g(m\\alpha)=0$. Thus $m\\alpha$ is an algebraic integer.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.3.8", "question": "Show that $\\mathbb{Z}[x]$ is not (a) Euclidean or (b) a PID.", "solution": "(a) Consider the elements 2, $x\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x]$. Clearly there is no way to write $x=a(x)2+r(x)$ where both the conditions (i) $a(x),r(x)\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x]$ and (ii) $deg(r)<deg(2)=0$ or $r=0$ are satisfied.\n(b) Again consider the two polynomials 2, $x\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x]$. Clearly $(x)\\not\\subseteq(2)$ and $(2)\\not\\subseteq(x)$. Now, if $(x,2)=(\\alpha)$ for some $\\alpha\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x]$, then $\\alpha|2$ and $\\alpha|x.$ But if $\\alpha|2$, then $\\alpha\\in\\mathbb{Z}$, so $\\alpha=\\pm1$ or $\\alpha=\\pm2$. However, $\\pm1\\notin(x,2)$ and $\\pm2\\nmid x$. So the ideal generated by $x$ and 2 is not generated by a single element in $\\mathbb{Z}[x]$. $\\mathbb{Z}[x]$ is not a PID.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.3.11", "question": "Let $f(x)=x^{n}+a_{n-1}x^{n-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{1}x+a_{0}$, and assume that for $p$ prime $p|a_{i}$ for $0\\le i<k$ and $p^{2}\\nmid a_{0}$. Show that $f(x)$ has an irreducible factor of degree at least $k$. (The case $k=n$ is referred to as Eisenstein's criterion for irreducibility.)", "solution": "We will prove this by induction on $n$, the degree of $f(x)$. The case when $n=1$ is trivial, so let us assume that the above statement is true for any polynomial of degree less than $n$.\nIf $f(x)$ is irreducible, there is nothing to prove, so assume that $f(x)$ is not irreducible. Then we can write\n$$f(x)=g(x)h(x)=(b_{0}+b_{1}x+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+b_{r}x^{r})(c_{0}+c_{1}x+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+c_{t}x^{t}).$$\nSince $p|a_{0}$ and $p^{2}\\nmid a_{0}$, and $a_{0}=b_{0}c_{0}$, we deduce $p|b_{0}$ or $p|c_{0}$ but not both. Suppose, without loss of generality, that $p|b_{0}$. We next consider $a_{1}=b_{0}c_{1}+b_{1}c_{0}.$ Since $p|a_{1}$ and $p|b_{0}$, but $p\\nmid c_{0}$ then $p|b_{1}$. Continuing in this fashion, we get that $p|b_{i}$ for $0\\le i<k$. If $r<k,$ then we can factor out a $p$ from each of the coefficients in $g(x)$, but this is absurd since then $p$ would divide every coefficient in $f(x)$, and $f$ is monic. Therefore $k\\le r$, $p|b_{i},0\\le i<k,p^{2}\\nmid b_{0}$. Also $b_{r}c_{t}=1$ implies that $g(x)$ or $-g(x)$ is monic. In any event, we have another polynomial which satisfies the conditions set out above but which has degree less than $n$. Thus, by induction, $g(x)$ has an irreducible factor of degree greater than or equal to $k$, and this factor is also an irreducible factor of $f(x)$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.3.12", "question": "Show that $f(x)=x^{5}+x^{4}+3x^{3}+9x^{2}+3$ is irreducible over $\\mathbb{Q}$.", "solution": "By applying Exercise 3.3.11 to $f(x)$ with $p=3$, we deduce that if $f(x)$ is not irreducible, then we can factor it into the product of a polynomial of degree 4 and a polynomial of degree 1, and so $f(x)$ has a rational root. However, we showed in Exercise 3.1.2 that if $r\\in\\mathbb{Q}$ is an algebraic integer, then $r\\in\\mathbb{Z}$. Thus, $f(x)$ must have an integral root, and this root must divide the constant term which is 3. The only choices are then $\\pm1$, $\\pm3$, and it is easy to check that these are not roots of the polynomial in question. We conclude that $f(x)$ is irreducible since it has no rational root.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.4.1", "question": "Show that $\\sum_{n=0}^{\\infty}\\frac{1}{a^{n!}}$ is transcendental for $a\\in\\mathbb{Z}$, $a\\ge2.$", "solution": "Suppose it is algebraic, and call the sum $\\alpha$. Look at the partial sum\n$$\\alpha_{k}=\\sum_{n=0}^{k}\\frac{1}{a^{n!}}=\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}},$$\nwith $q_{k}=a^{k!}$. Then\n$$|\\alpha-\\alpha_{k}|=|\\sum_{n=k+1}^{\\infty}\\frac{1}{a^{n!}}|\\le\\frac{1}{a^{(k+1)!}}M;$$\nwhere $M=1+\\frac{1}{a^{k+2}}+(\\frac{1}{a^{k+2}})^{2}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot,$ an infinite geometric series with a finite sum. Thus,\n$$|\\sum_{n=k+1}^{\\infty}\\frac{1}{a^{n!}}|\\le\\frac{M}{q_{k}^{k+1}}.$$\nIf $\\alpha$ is algebraic of degree $n$, then Liouville's theorem tells us that we can find a constant $c(\\alpha)$ such that\n$$\\frac{M}{q_{k}^{k+1}}\\ge|\\alpha-\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}}|\\ge\\frac{c(\\alpha)}{q_{k}^{n}}.$$\nHowever, we can choose $k$ as large as we wish to obtain a contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.4.2", "question": "Show that $\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{1}{a^{3^{n}}}$ is transcendental for $a\\in\\mathbb{Z}$, $a\\ge2$.", "solution": "Suppose that\n$$\\alpha=\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{1}{a^{3^{n}}}$$\nis algebraic. Consider the partial sum\n$$\\alpha_{k}=\\sum_{n=1}^{k}\\frac{1}{a^{3^{n}}}=\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}},$$\nwith $q_{k}=a^{3^{k}}$. We have\n$$|\\alpha-\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}}|=|\\sum_{n=k+1}^{\\infty}\\frac{1}{a^{3^{n}}}|\\le\\frac{S}{a^{3^{k+1}}},$$\nwhere $S=1+1/a+1/a^{2}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot.$ Then by Roth's theorem,\n$$\\frac{S}{q_{k}^{3}}\\ge\\frac{c(\\alpha,\\epsilon)}{q_{k}^{2+\\epsilon}}$$\nBut, we can choose $k$ to be as large as we want to produce a contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.4.3", "question": "Show that $\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{1}{a^{f(n)}}$ is transcendental when $lim_{n\\rightarrow\\infty}\\frac{f(n+1)}{f(n)}>2.$", "solution": "Suppose that\n$$\\alpha=\\sum_{n=1}^{\\infty}\\frac{1}{a^{f(n)}}$$\nis algebraic. Following the same argument as in the previous exercise, we get\n$$\\frac{S}{q_{k+1}}\\ge|\\alpha-\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}}|\\ge\\frac{c(\\alpha)}{q_{k}^{2+\\epsilon}},$$\nwhere $q_{k}=a^{f(k)}$. For $k$ sufficiently large,\n$$\\frac{f(k+1)}{f(k)}>2+\\delta,$$\nand so\n$$\\frac{q_{k+1}}{q_{k}}=\\frac{a^{f(k+1)}}{a^{f(k)}}>a^{(1+\\delta)f(k)}=q_{k}^{(1+\\delta)}.$$\nThis implies that $q_{k+1}>q_{k}^{2+\\delta}$. By Roth's theorem, we can deduce that\n$$\\frac{c(\\alpha)}{q_{k}^{2+\\epsilon}}\\le\\frac{S}{q_{k+1}}\\Rightarrow\\frac{c(\\alpha)}{q_{k}^{2+\\epsilon}}\\le\\frac{S}{q_{k}^{2+\\delta}} \\Rightarrow q_{k}^{\\delta}\\le\\frac{S}{c(\\alpha)}q_{k}^{\\epsilon}.$$\nAs $q_{k}\\rightarrow\\infty$ we find $\\delta\\le\\epsilon$, a contradiction for sufficiently small $\\epsilon$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.4.4", "question": "Prove that $f(x)=x^{6}+7x^{5}-12x^{3}+6x+2$ is irreducible over $\\mathbb{Q}$.", "solution": "By Exercise 3.3.11, since $2|a_{i}$ for $0\\le i<5$ then $f(x)$ has a factor of degree at least 5. This means that the polynomial is either irreducible or it has a rational root. We showed earlier that if a polynomial in $\\mathbb{Z}[x]$ has a rational root, then the root is actually an integer. We also know that any roots of a polynomial will divide its constant term, which in this case is 2. It suffices to check that $\\pm1$, $\\pm2,$ are not roots to deduce that $f(x)$ is irreducible.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.4.5", "question": "Using Thue's theorem, show that $f(x,y)=x^{6}+7x^{5}y-12x^{3}y^{3}+6xy^{5}+8y^{6}=m$ has only a finite number of solutions for $m\\in\\mathbb{Z}^{*}$.", "solution": "Use the previous exercise to prove that the polynomial is irreducible. The result follows from Thue's theorem and Example 3.2.3.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.4.6", "question": "Let $\\zeta_{m}$ be a primitive mth root of unity. Show that $\\prod_{0\\le i,j\\le m-1}(\\zeta_{m}^{i}-\\zeta_{m}^{j})=(-1)^{m-1}m^{m}.$", "solution": "Since\n$$x^{m}-1=\\prod_{i=0}^{m-1}(x-\\zeta_{m}^{i}),$$\nwe see that the constant term is\n$$(-1)^{m}\\prod_{i=0}^{m-1}\\zeta_{m}^{i}=-1.$$\nDifferentiating $x^{m}-1$ above via the product rule, and setting $x=\\zeta_{m}^{j}$ we see that\n$$m\\zeta_{m}^{j(m-1)}=\\prod_{i\\ne j}^{m-1}(\\zeta_{m}^{j}-\\zeta_{m}^{i}).$$\nTaking the product over $j$ gives the result.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.4.7", "question": "Let $\\phi_{m}(x)=\\prod_{\\substack{1\\le i\\le m\\\\ (i,m)=1}}(x-\\zeta_{m}^{i})$ denote the mth cyclotomic polynomial. Prove that $x^{m}-1=\\prod_{d|m}\\phi_{d}(x).$", "solution": "Every mth root of unity is a primitive dth root of unity for some $d|m$. Conversely, every dth root of unity is also an mth root of unity for $d|m$. The result is now immediate.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.4.8", "question": "Show that $\\phi_{m}(x)\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x]$.", "solution": "We induct on $m$. Form $m=1$, this is clear. Suppose we have proved it true for $\\phi_{r}(x)$ with $r<m$. Then setting\n$$v(x)=\\prod_{d|m}\\phi_{d}(x),$$\nwe have by induction $v(x)\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x]$. Since $v(x)$ is monic, and $v(x)|(x^{m}-1),$ we find by long division that $(x^{m}-1)/v(x)=\\phi_{m}(x)\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x]$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.4.9", "question": "Show that $\\phi_{m}(x)$ is irreducible in $\\mathbb{Q}[x]$ for every $m\\ge1$.", "solution": "Let $f(x)$ be the minimal polynomial of $\\zeta_{m}$ and suppose $\\phi_{m}(x)=f(x)g(x)$ with $f(x),g(x)\\in\\mathbb{Q}[x]$. By Gauss' lemma (see Theorem 2.1.9) we may suppose that $f(x),g(x)\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x]$. Let $p$ be coprime to $m$. Then $\\zeta_{m}^{p}$ is again a primitive mth root of unity. Thus\n$$f(\\zeta_{m}^{p})g(\\zeta_{m}^{p})=0$$\nSuppose $f(\\zeta_{m}^{p})\\ne0$. Then $g(\\zeta_{m}^{p})=0$. Since $g(x^{p})\\equiv g(x)^{p}$ (mod $p$) we deduce that $g(x)$ and $f(x)$ have a common root in $\\mathbb{F}_{p}$, a contradiction since $x^{m}-1$ has no multiple roots in $\\overline{\\mathbb{F}_{p}}$. Thus, $f(\\zeta_{m}^{p})=0$ for any $(p,m)=1$. It follows that $f(\\zeta_{m}^{i})=0$ for any $(i,m)=1$. Therefore $deg(f)=\\varphi(m)=deg(\\phi_{m})$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.4.10", "question": "Let $I$ be a subset of the positive integers $\\le m$ which are coprime to $m$. Set $f(x)=\\prod_{i\\in I}(x-\\zeta_{m}^{i})$. Suppose that $f(\\zeta_{m})=0$ and $f(\\zeta_{m}^{p})\\ne0$ for some prime $p$. Show that $p|m$. (This observation gives an alternative proof for the irreducibility of $\\phi_{m}(x).$)", "solution": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m})$. Then $f(\\zeta_{m}^{p})$ divides\n$$\\prod_{0\\le i\\le m-1}(\\zeta_{m}^{p}-\\zeta_{m}^{i})$$\nin the ring $\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$. Hence $N_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(f(\\zeta_{m}^{p}))$ divides $m$ by Exercise 3.4.6 above. Since\n$$f(x)^{p}-f(x^{p})\\in p\\mathbb{Z}[x],$$\nwe see upon setting $x=\\zeta_{m}$ that $p|f(\\zeta_{m}^{p})$ and hence $p|m$ as desired.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.4.11", "question": "Consider the equation $x^{3}+3x^{2}y+xy^{2}+y^{3}=m.$ Using Thue's theorem, deduce that there are only finitely many integral solutions to this equation.", "solution": "To use Thue's theorem, we must show that $f(x,y)=x^{3}+3x^{2}+xy^{2}+y^{3}$ is irreducible. If this polynomial is reducible, then so is the polynomial $f(x,1)=x^{3}+3x^{2}+x+1.$ However, since $f(x,1)$ has degree 3, then if it reduces it will have a factor of degree 1, a rational root. We have already shown that all rational roots of a monic polynomial in $\\mathbb{Z}[x]$ are actually integers, and all roots must divide the constant term of a polynomial. The only possibilities for such a root are $x=\\pm1$. A quick calculation shows that neither of these two are in fact a root of $f(x,1)$ and so $f(x,1)$ is irreducible, implying that $f(x,y)$ is irreducible. We can now apply the results of Example 3.2.3.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.4.12", "question": "Assume that $n$ is an odd integer, $n\\ge3$. Show that $x^{n}+y^{n}=m$ has only finitely many integral solutions.", "solution": "If $(x_{0},y_{0})$ is a solution to $x^{n}+y^{n}=m$ then $(x_{0}+y_{0})|m$ since $x^{n}+y^{n}=(x+y)(x^{n-1}-x^{n-2}y+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+y^{n-1})$. Suppose $|x|\\ge m$. Then the distance between $x^{n}$ and the nearest nth power will be greater than $m$, and $x$ cannot satisfy the above equation. We then have a bound on the size of $x$ along with the constraint that $x+y|m$. There can only be a finite number of pairs which satisfy these two constraints.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.4.13", "question": "Let $\\zeta_{m}$ denote a primitive mth root of unity. Show that $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m})$ is normal over $\\mathbb{Q}$.", "solution": "$\\zeta_{m}$ is a root of the mth cyclotomic polynomial, which we have shown to be irreducible. Thus, the conjugate fields are $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m}^{j})$ where $(j,m)=1$ and these are identical with $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m})$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 3.4.14", "question": "Let $a$ be squarefree and greater than 1, and let $p$ be prime. Show that the normal closure of $\\mathbb{Q}(a^{1/p})$ is $\\mathbb{Q}(a^{1/p},\\zeta_{p})$.", "solution": "The polynomial $x^{p}-a$ is irreducible (by Eisenstein's criterion). The conjugates of $a^{1/p}$ are $\\zeta_{p}^{j}a^{1/p}$. If $K$ is the normal closure of $\\mathbb{Q}(a^{1/p})$, it must contain all the pth roots of unity. The result is now immediate.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Lemma 4.1.1", "question": "If $K$ is an algebraic number field of degree $n$ over $\\mathbb{Q}$, and $\\alpha\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ its ring of integers, then $Tr_{K}(\\alpha)$ and $N_{K}(\\alpha)$ are in $\\mathbb{Z}$.", "solution": "We begin by writing $\\alpha\\omega_{i}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}a_{ij}\\omega_{j}\\forall i$. Then we have\n$$\\alpha^{(k)}\\omega_{i}^{(k)}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}a_{ij}\\omega_{j}^{(k)}\\forall i,k,$$\nwhere $\\alpha^{(k)}$ is the kth conjugate of $\\alpha$. We rewrite the above by introducing the Kronecker delta function to get\n$$\\sum_{j=1}^{n}\\delta_{jk}\\alpha^{(j)}\\omega_{i}^{(j)}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}a_{ij}\\omega_{j}^{(k)},$$\nwhere\n$$\\delta_{ij}=\\begin{cases}0&if~i\\ne j,\\\\ 1&if~i=j.\\end{cases}$$\nNow, if we define the matrices\n$$A_{0}=(\\alpha^{(i)}\\delta_{ij}), \\quad \\Omega=(\\omega_{i}^{(j)}), \\quad A=(a_{ij}),$$\nthe preceding statement tells us that $\\Omega A_{0}=A\\Omega$ or $A_{0}=\\Omega^{-1}A\\Omega,$ so we conclude that $TrA=TrA_{0}$ and $det A=det~A_{0}$. But $TrA_{0}$ is just the sum of the conjugates of $\\alpha$ and is thus (up to sign) the coefficient of the $x^{n-1}$ term in the minimal polynomial for $\\alpha$; similarly, $det A_{0}$ is just the product of the conjugates of $\\alpha$ and is thus equal (up to sign) to the constant term in the minimal polynomial for $\\alpha$. Thus $Tr_{K}(\\alpha)$ and $N_{K}(\\alpha)$ are in $\\mathbb{Z}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Lemma 4.1.4", "question": "The bilinear pairing given by $B(x,y):K\\times K\\rightarrow\\mathbb{Q}$ such that $(x,y)\\rightarrow Tr_{K}(xy)$ is nondegenerate.", "solution": "We recall that if $V$ is a finite-dimensional vector space over a field $F$ with basis $e_{1},e_{2},...,e_{n}$ and $B:V\\times V\\rightarrow F$ is a bilinear map, we can associate a matrix to $B$ as follows. Write\n$$v=\\sum a_{i}e_{i} \\text{ with } a_{i}\\in F, \\quad u=\\sum b_{i}e_{i} \\text{ with } b_{i}\\in F.$$\nThen\n$$B(v,u)=\\sum_{i}B(a_{i}e_{i},u)=\\sum_{i}a_{i}B(e_{i},u)=\\sum_{i,j}a_{i}b_{j}B(e_{i},e_{j})$$\nand we associate to $B$ the matrix $(B(e_{i},e_{j}))$. $B$ is said to be nondegenerate if the matrix associated to it is nonsingular. This definition is independent of the choice of basis.\nNow, if $\\omega_{1},\\omega_{2},...,\\omega_{n}$ is a $\\mathbb{Q}$-basis for $K$, then the matrix associated to $B(x,y)$ with respect to this basis is just\n$$(B(\\omega_{i},\\omega_{j}))=(Tr_{K}(\\omega_{i}\\omega_{j})),$$\nbut $Tr_{K}(\\omega_{i}\\omega_{j})=\\sum\\omega_{i}^{(k)}\\omega_{j}^{(k)}$ and thus we see that\n$$(B(\\omega_{i},\\omega_{j}))=\\Omega\\Omega^{T},$$\nwhere $\\Omega=(\\omega_{i}^{(j)})$, is nonsingular because $\\omega_{1},\\omega_{2},...,\\omega_{n}$ form a basis for $K$. Thus $B(x,y)$ is indeed nondegenerate.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 4.2.2", "question": "Let $\\alpha_{1},\\alpha_{2},...,\\alpha_{n}$ be a set of generators for a finitely generated $\\mathbb{Z}$-module $M$, and let $N$ be a submodule.\n(a) $\\exists\\beta_{1},\\beta_{2},...,\\beta_{m}$ in $N$ with $m\\le n$ such that\n$$N=\\mathbb{Z}\\beta_{1}+\\mathbb{Z}\\beta_{2}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}\\beta_{m}$$\nand $\\beta_{i}=\\sum_{j\\ge i}p_{ij}\\alpha_{j}$ with $1\\le i\\le m$ and $p_{ij}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$.\n(b) If $m=n$, then $[M:N]=p_{11}p_{22}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{nn}$.", "solution": "(a) We will proceed by induction on the number of generators of a $\\mathbb{Z}$-module. This is trivial when $n=0$. We can assume that we have proved the above statement to be true for all $\\mathbb{Z}$-modules with $n-1$ or fewer generators, and proceed to prove it for $n$. We define $M^{\\prime}$ to be the submodule generated by $\\alpha_{2},\\alpha_{3},...,\\alpha_{n}$ over $\\mathbb{Z}$, and define $N^{\\prime}$ to be $N\\cap M^{\\prime}.$ Now, if $n=1$, then $M^{\\prime}=0$ and there is nothing to prove. If $N=N^{\\prime}$, then the statement is true by our induction hypothesis. So we assume that $N\\ne N^{\\prime}$ and consider $A$, the set of all integers $k$ such that $\\exists k_{2},k_{3},...,k_{n}$ with $k\\alpha_{1}+k_{2}\\alpha_{2}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+k_{n}\\alpha_{n}\\in N$. Since $N$ is a submodule, we deduce that $A$ is a subgroup of $\\mathbb{Z}$. All additive subgroups of $\\mathbb{Z}$ are of the form $m\\mathbb{Z}$ for some integer $m$, and so $A=k_{11}\\mathbb{Z}$ for some $k_{11}$. Then let $\\beta_{1}=k_{11}\\alpha_{1}+k_{12}\\alpha_{2}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+k_{1n}\\alpha_{n}\\in N.$ If we have some $\\alpha\\in N$ then\n$$\\alpha=\\sum_{i=1}^{n}h_{i}\\alpha_{i},$$\nwith $h_{i}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ and $h_{1}\\in A$ so $h_{1}=ak_{11}$. Therefore, $\\alpha-a\\beta_{1}\\in N^{\\prime}$. By the induction hypothesis, there exist $\\beta_{i}=\\sum_{j\\ge i}k_{ij}\\alpha_{j};$ $i=2,3...,m$, which generate $N^{\\prime}$ over $\\mathbb{Z}$ and which satisfy all the conditions above. It is clear that adding $\\beta_{1}$ to this list gives us a set of generators of $N$.\n(b) Consider $\\alpha$, an arbitrary element of $M$. Then $\\alpha=\\sum c_{i}\\alpha_{i}$. Recalling that $\\beta_{i}=\\sum_{j\\ge i}p_{ij}\\alpha_{j}$ we write $c_{1}=p_{11}q_{1}+r_{1}$, with $0\\le r_{1}<p_{11}$. Then $\\alpha-q_{1}\\beta_{1}=\\sum c_{i}^{\\prime}\\alpha_{i}$ where $0\\le c_{1}^{\\prime}<p_{11}$. Note that $\\alpha\\equiv\\alpha-q_{1}\\beta_{1} \\pmod N$. Next we write $c_{2}^{\\prime}=p_{22}q_{2}+r_{2}$, where $0\\le r_{2}<p_{22}$, and note that $\\alpha\\equiv\\alpha-q_{1}\\beta_{1}-q_{2}\\beta_{2}\\pmod N.$ It is clear by induction that we can continue this process to arrive at an expression $\\alpha^{\\prime}=\\sum k_{i}\\alpha_{i}$ with $0\\le k_{i}<p_{ii}$ and $\\alpha\\equiv\\alpha^{\\prime} \\pmod N$. It remains only to show that if we have $\\alpha=\\sum c_{i}\\alpha_{i}$ and $\\beta=\\sum d_{i}\\alpha_{i}$ where $c_{i}\\ne d_{i}$ for at least one $i$ and $0\\le c_{i}, d_{i}<p_{ii}$, then $\\alpha$ and $\\beta$ are distinct mod $N$. Suppose that this is not true, and that $\\sum c_{i}\\alpha_{i}\\equiv\\sum d_{i}\\alpha_{i}\\pmod N$ where $c_{i}\\ne d_{i}$ for at least one $i$. Suppose $c_{i}=d_{i}$ for $i<r$ and $c_{r}\\ne d_{r}$. Then $\\sum(c_{i}-d_{i})\\alpha_{i}\\in N$ so\n$$\\sum_{i\\ge r}(c_{i}-d_{i})\\alpha_{i}=\\sum_{i\\ge r}k_{i}\\beta_{i}=\\sum_{i\\ge r}k_{i}(\\sum_{j\\ge i}p_{ij}\\alpha_{j})$$\nSince $c_{r}$, $d_{r}$ are both less than $p_{rr}$ we have $c_{r}=d_{r}$ a contradiction. Thus, each coset in $M/N$ has a unique representative $\\alpha=\\sum c_{i}\\alpha_{i}$ with $0\\le c_{i}<p_{ii}$, and there are $p_{11}p_{22}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{nn}$ of them. So $[M:N]=p_{11}p_{22}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{nn}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Example 4.3.1", "question": "Suppose that the minimal polynomial of $\\alpha$ is Eisensteinian with respect to a prime $p$, i.e., $\\alpha$ is a root of the polynomial $x^{n}+a_{n-1}x^{n-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{1}x+a_{0}$, where $p|a_{i}$, $0\\le i\\le n-1$ and $p^{2}\\nmid a_{0}$. Show that the index of $\\alpha$ is not divisible by $p$.", "solution": "Let $M=\\mathbb{Z}+\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha^{n-1}$. First observe that since $\\alpha^{n}+a_{n-1}\\alpha^{n-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{1}\\alpha+a_{0}=0$ then $\\alpha^{n}/p\\in M\\subseteq\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Also, $|N_{K}(\\alpha)|=a_{0}\\not\\equiv0\\pmod{p^{2}}.$ We will proceed by contradiction. Suppose $p|[\\mathcal{O}_{K}:M]$. Then there is an element of order $p$ in the group $\\mathcal{O}_{K}/M$ meaning $\\exists\\xi\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ such that $\\xi\\notin M$ but $p\\xi\\in M$. Then\n$$p\\xi=b_{0}+b_{1}\\alpha+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+b_{n-1}\\alpha^{n-1};$$\nwhere not all the $b_{i}$ are divisible by $p$, for otherwise $\\xi\\in M$. Let $j$ be the least index such that $p\\nmid b_{j}$. Then\n$$\\eta=\\xi-(\\frac{b_{0}}{p}+\\frac{b_{1}}{p}\\alpha+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\frac{b_{j-1}}{p}\\alpha^{j-1}) =\\frac{b_{j}}{p}\\alpha^{j}+\\frac{b_{j+1}}{p}\\alpha^{j+1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\frac{b_{n}}{p}\\alpha^{n}$$\nis in $\\mathcal{O}_{K},$ since both $\\xi$ and $\\frac{b_{0}}{p}+\\frac{b_{1}}{p}\\alpha+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\frac{b_{n}}{p}\\alpha^{j-1}$ are in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. If $\\eta\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ then of course $\\eta\\alpha^{n-j-1}$ is also in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, and\n$$\\eta\\alpha^{n-j-1}=\\frac{b_{j}}{p}\\alpha^{n-1}+\\frac{\\alpha^{n}}{p}(b_{j+1}+b_{j+2}\\alpha+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+b_{n}\\alpha^{n-j-2}).$$\nSince both $\\alpha^{n}/p$ and $(b_{j+1}+b_{j+2}\\alpha+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+b_{n}\\alpha^{n-j-2})$ are in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, we conclude that $(b_{j}\\alpha^{n-1})/p\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. We know from Lemma 4.1.1 that the norm of an algebraic integer is always a rational integer, so\n$$N_{K}(\\frac{b_{j}}{p}\\alpha^{n-1})=\\frac{b_{j}^{n}N_{K}(\\alpha)^{n-1}}{p^{n}}=\\frac{b_{j}^{n}a_{0}^{n-1}}{p^{n}}$$\nmust be an integer. But $p$ does not divide $b_{j}$, and $p^{2}$ does not divide $a_{0}$, so this is impossible. This proves that we do not have an element of order $p,$ and thus $p\\nmid[\\mathcal{O}_{K}:M]$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Example 4.3.4", "question": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{D})$ with $D$ a squarefree integer. Find an integral basis for $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "solution": "An arbitrary element $\\alpha$ of $K$ is of the form $\\alpha=r_{1}+r_{2}\\sqrt{D}$ with $r_{1},r_{2}\\in\\mathbb{Q}$. Since $[K:\\mathbb{Q}]=2$, $\\alpha$ has only one conjugate: $r_{1}-r_{2}\\sqrt{D}$. From Lemma 4.1.1 we know that if $\\alpha$ is an algebraic integer, then $Tr_{K}(\\alpha)=2r_{1}$ and $N_{K}(\\alpha)=(r_{1}+r_{2}\\sqrt{D})(r_{1}-r_{2}\\sqrt{D}) =r_{1}^{2}-Dr_{2}^{2}$ are both integers. We note also that since $\\alpha$ satisfies the monic polynomial $x^{2}-2r_{1}x+r_{1}^{2}-Dr_{2}^{2}$ if $Tr_{K}(\\alpha)$ and $N_{K}(\\alpha)$ are integers, then $\\alpha$ is an algebraic integer.\nIf $2r_{1}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ where $r_{1}\\in\\mathbb{Q}$, then the denominator of $r_{1}$ can be at most 2. We also need $r_{1}^{2}-Dr_{2}^{2}$ to be an integer, so the denominator of $r_{2}$ can be no more than 2. Then let $r_{1}=g_{1}/2$, $r_{2}=g_{2}/2$ where $g_{1}, g_{2}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$. The second condition amounts to $\\frac{g_{1}^{2}-Dg_{2}^{2}}{4}\\in\\mathbb{Z},$ which means that $g_{1}^{2}-Dg_{2}^{2}\\equiv0 \\pmod 4$, or $g_{1}^{2}\\equiv Dg_{2}^{2} \\pmod 4$. We will discuss two cases:\nCase 1. $D\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$. If $D\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$, and $g_{1}^{2}\\equiv Dg_{2}^{2} \\pmod 4$, then $g_{1}$ and $g_{2}$ are either both even or both odd. So if $\\alpha=r_{1}+r_{2}\\sqrt{D}$ is an algebraic integer of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{D})$, then either $r_{1}$ and $r_{2}$ are both integers, or they are both fractions with denominator 2. We recall from Chapter 3 that if $4|(-D+1)$, then $(1+\\sqrt{D})/2$ is an algebraic integer. This suggests that we use $1, (1+\\sqrt{D})/2$ as a basis; it is clear from the discussion above that this is in fact an integral basis.\nCase 2. $D\\equiv2,3 \\pmod 4$. If $g_{1}^{2}\\equiv Dg_{2}^{2} \\pmod 4$, then both $g_{1}$ and $g_{2}$ must be even. Then a basis for $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ is $1, \\sqrt{D}$; again it is clear that this is an integral basis.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Example 4.3.6", "question": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\alpha)$ where $\\alpha=r^{1/3}$, $r=ab^{2}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ where $ab$ is squarefree. If $3|r$ assume that $3\\nmid a, 3\\nmid b$. Find an integral basis for $K$.", "solution": "The minimal polynomial of $\\alpha$ is $f(x)=x^{3}-r$ and $\\alpha$'s conjugates are $\\alpha$, $\\omega\\alpha$, and $\\omega^{2}\\alpha$ where $\\omega$ is a primitive cube root of unity. By Exercise 4.3.3, $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\alpha)=-\\prod_{i=1}^{3}f^{\\prime}(\\alpha^{(i)})=-3^{3}r^{2}.$ So $-3^{3}r^{2}=m^{2}d_{K}$ where $m=[\\mathcal{O}_{K}:\\mathbb{Z}+\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha+\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha^{2}]$. We note that $f(x)$ is Eisensteinian for every prime divisor of $a$ so by Example 4.3.1 if $p|a,$ $p\\nmid m$. Thus if $3|a,27a^{2}|d_{K}$, and if $3\\nmid a$, then $3a^{2}|d_{K}$. We now consider $\\beta=\\alpha^{2}/b$, which is a root of the polynomial $x^{3}-a^{2}b.$ This polynomial is Eisensteinian for any prime which divides $b$. Therefore $b^{2}|d_{K}$. We conclude that $d_{K}=-3^{n}(ab)^{2}$ where $n=3$ if $3|r$ and $n=1$ or 3 otherwise. We will consider three cases: $r\\not\\equiv1,8 \\pmod 9$, $r\\equiv1 \\pmod 9$ and $r\\equiv8 \\pmod 9$.\nCase 1. If $r\\not\\equiv1,8 \\pmod 9$, then $r^{3}\\not\\equiv r \\pmod 9$. Then the polynomial $(x+r)^{3}-r$ is Eisensteinian with respect to the prime 3. A root of this polynomial is $\\alpha-r$ and $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\alpha-r)=d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\alpha)=-27r^{2}$. This implies that $3\\nmid m$ and so $m=b$. We can choose as our integral basis $1, \\alpha, \\alpha^2/b$, all of which are algebraic integers. We verify that this is an integral basis by checking the index of $\\mathbb{Z}+\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha+\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha^{2}$ in $\\mathbb{Z}+\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha+\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha^{2}/b$, which is clearly $b$. Thus $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}+\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha+\\mathbb{Z}\\frac{\\alpha^{2}}{b}$.\nCase 2. If $r\\equiv1 \\pmod 9$, then $c=(1+\\alpha+\\alpha^{2})/3$ is an algebraic integer. In fact, since $Tr_{K}(\\alpha)=Tr_{K}(\\alpha^{2})=0$ then $Tr_{K}(c)=1\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ and $N_{K}(c)=\\frac{N_{K}(1+\\alpha+\\alpha^{2})}{27}=\\frac{N_{K}(\\alpha^{3}-1)}{27N_{K}(\\alpha-1)}=\\frac{(r-1)^{2}}{27}$ because the minimal polynomial for $1-\\alpha$ is $x^{3}+3x^{2}+3x+1-r$. The other coefficient for the minimal polynomial of $c$ is $(1-r)/3$ which is an integer. If $c$ is in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, then $\\mathcal{O}_{K}/(\\mathbb{Z}+\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha+\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha^{2})$ has an element of order 3, and so $3|m$. Then $d_{K}=-3(ab)^{2}$, so $m=3b$. We will choose as our integral basis $\\alpha, \\alpha^{2}/b, c$, noting that since $1=3c-\\alpha-b\\frac{\\alpha^{2}}{b}$, $\\alpha=0+\\alpha+0$, $\\alpha^{2}=0+0+b\\frac{\\alpha^{2}}{b}$ then Theorem 4.2.2 tells us that the index of $\\mathbb{Z}+\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha+\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha^{2}$ in $\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha+\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha^{2}/b+\\mathbb{Z}c$ is $3b$. Therefore $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha+\\mathbb{Z}\\frac{\\alpha^{2}}{b}+\\mathbb{Z}\\frac{1+\\alpha+\\alpha^{2}}{3}$.\nCase 3. If $r\\equiv8 \\pmod 9$, consider $d=(1-\\alpha+\\alpha^{2})/3$. This is an algebraic integer. $Tr_{K}(d)=1,N_{K}(d)=(1+r)^{2}/27\\in\\mathbb{Z}$, and the remaining coefficient for the minimal polynomial of $d$ is $(1+r)/3\\in\\mathbb{Z}.$ By the same reasoning as above, we conclude that $3|m$ and so $m=3b.$ We choose $\\alpha, \\alpha^{2}/b, d$ as an integral basis, noting that $1=3d+\\alpha-b\\frac{\\alpha^{2}}{b}$, $\\alpha=0+\\alpha+0$, $\\alpha^{2}=0+0+b\\frac{\\alpha^{2}}{b};$ so that the index of $\\mathbb{Z}+\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha+\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha^{2}$ in $\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha+\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha^{2}/b+\\mathbb{Z}d$ is $3b$. We conclude that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha+\\mathbb{Z}\\frac{\\alpha^{2}}{b}+\\mathbb{Z}\\frac{1-\\alpha+\\alpha^{2}}{b}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.1.2", "question": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(i)$. Show that $i\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ and verify that $Tr_{K}(i)$ and $N_{K}(i)$ are integers.", "solution": "We know that $i$ is a root of the irreducible polynomial $x^{2}+1$, and so its conjugates are $i,-i.$ Thus, $Tr_{K}(i)=i-i=0\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ and $N_{K}(i)=i(-i)=1\\in\\mathbb{Z}.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.1.3", "question": "Determine the algebraic integers of $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-5})$.", "solution": "We first note that $1,\\sqrt{-5}$ form a $\\mathbb{Q}$-basis for $K$. Thus any $\\alpha\\in K$ looks like $\\alpha=r_{1}+r_{2}\\sqrt{-5}$ with $r_{1},r_{2}\\in\\mathbb{Q}$. Since $[K:\\mathbb{Q}]=2$, we can deduce that the conjugates of $\\alpha$ are $r_{1}+r_{2}\\sqrt{-5}$ and $r_{1}-r_{2}\\sqrt{-5}$. Then $Tr_{K}(\\alpha)=2r_{1}$ and $N_{K}(\\alpha)=(r_{1}+r_{2}\\sqrt{-5})(r_{1}-r_{2}\\sqrt{-5}) =r_{1}^{2}+5r_{2}^{2}$. By Lemma 4.1.1, if $\\alpha\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, then the trace and norm are integers. Also, $\\alpha$ is a root of the monic polynomial $x^{2}-2r_{1}x+r_{1}^{2}+5r_{2}^{2}$ which is in $\\mathbb{Z}[x]$ when the trace and norm are integers. We conclude that for $\\alpha=r_{1}+r_{2}\\sqrt{-5}$ to be in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, it is necessary and sufficient that $2r_{1}$ and $r_{1}^{2}+5r_{2}^{2}$ be integers. This implies that $r_{1}$ has a denominator at most 2, which forces the same for $r_{2}$. Then by setting $r_{1}=g_{1}/2$ and $r_{2}=g_{2}/2$ we must have $(g_{1}^{2}+5g_{2}^{2})/4\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ or, equivalently, $g_{1}^{2}+5g_{2}^{2}\\equiv0 \\pmod 4$. Thus, as all squares are congruent to 0 or 1 (mod 4), we conclude that $g_{1}$ and $g_{2}$ are themselves even, and thus $r_{1}, r_{2}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$. We conclude then that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}+\\mathbb{Z}\\sqrt{-5}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.1.5", "question": "Show that the definition of nondegeneracy above is independent of the choice of basis.", "solution": "If $f_{1},...,f_{n}$ is another basis and $A=(B(f_{i},f_{j}))$, then $A=P^{T}BP$ where $P$ is the change of basis matrix from $e_{1},...,e_{n}$ to $f_{1},...,f_{n}$. Since $P$ is nonsingular, $det A\\ne0$ if and only if $det B\\ne0$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.2.1", "question": "Show that $\\exists\\omega_{1}^{*},\\omega_{2}^{*},...,\\omega_{n}^{*}\\in K$ such that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}\\subseteq\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{1}^{*}+\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{2}^{*}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{n}^{*}.$", "solution": "Let $\\omega_{1},\\omega_{2},...,\\omega_{n}$ be a $\\mathbb{Q}$-basis for $K$, and recall from Exercise 3.3.7 that for any $\\alpha\\in K$ there is a nonzero integer $m$ such that $m\\alpha\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Thus we can assume that $\\omega_{1},\\omega_{2},...,\\omega_{n}$ are in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Now, as the bilinear pairing $B(x,y)$ defined previously was nondegenerate, we can find a dual basis $\\omega_{1}^{*},\\omega_{2}^{*},...,\\omega_{n}^{*}$ satisfying $B(\\omega_{i},\\omega_{j}^{*})=\\delta_{ij}$. If we write $\\omega_{j}^{*}=\\sum c_{kj}\\omega_{k}$ we have $\\delta_{ij}=Tr_{K}(\\omega_{i}{\\omega_{j}}^{*}) =Tr_{K}(\\omega_{i}\\sum c_{kj}\\omega_{k}) =\\sum c_{kj}Tr_{K}(\\omega_{i}\\omega_{k})$. If we introduce now the matrices, $C=(c_{ij}), \\Omega=(\\omega_i^{(j)})$, then the above becomes $I_{n}=\\Omega\\Omega^{T}C\\Rightarrow C^{-1}=\\Omega\\Omega^{T}$. We conclude that $C$ is nonsingular and that ${\\omega_{1}}^{*},{\\omega_{2}}^{*},...,{\\omega_{n}}^{*}$ forms a basis for $K$. Let $\\alpha$ be an arbitrary element of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. We write $\\alpha=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}a_{j}\\omega_{j}^{*}$ with $a_{j}\\in\\mathbb{Q}$. So $\\alpha\\omega_{i}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}a_{j}\\omega_{i}\\omega_{j}^{*}$ and $Tr_{K}(\\alpha\\omega_{i})=\\sum a_{j}Tr_{K}(\\omega_{i}\\omega_{j}^{*})=a_{i} \\forall i.$ But $\\alpha\\omega_{i}\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ implies the left-hand side above is in $\\mathbb{Z}$, and thus $a_{i}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ for all $i$. It follows then that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}\\subseteq\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{1}^{*}+\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{2}^{*}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{n}^{*}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.2.3", "question": "Show that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ has an integral basis.", "solution": "We apply the results of Theorem 4.2.2 with $M=\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{1}^{*}+\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{2}^{*}+ ...+\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{n}^{*}$ and $N=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. It follows directly from the theorem that there exist $\\omega_{1},\\omega_{2},...,\\omega_{n}\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ such that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{1}+\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{2}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{n}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.2.4", "question": "Show that $det(Tr(\\omega_{i}\\omega_{j}))$ is independent of the choice of integral basis.", "solution": "Let $\\omega_{1},\\omega_{2},...,\\omega_{n}$ and $\\theta_{1},\\theta_{2},...,\\theta_{n}$ be two distinct integral bases for an algebraic number field $K$. We can write $\\omega_{i}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}c_{ij}\\theta_{j}, \\quad \\theta_{i}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}d_{ij}\\omega_{j}$ for all $i$, where $c_{ij}$ and $d_{ij}$ are all integers. Then $(c_{ij})$ and $(c_{ij})^{-1}$ both have entries in $\\mathbb{Z}$. So $det(c_{ij})$, $det(c_{ij})^{-1}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$, meaning that $det(c_{ij})=\\pm1$. Then\n$$Tr(\\omega_{i}\\omega_{j})=Tr((\\sum_{l}c_{il}\\theta_{l})(\\sum_{m}c_{jm}\\theta_{m}))=\\sum_{l,m}c_{il}c_{jm}Tr(\\theta_{l}\\theta_{m}).$$\nNow if we define $\\Omega=(\\omega_{i}^{(j)})$, $C=(c_{ij}),\\Theta=(\\theta_{i}^{(j)})$, then we can write the above as the matrix equation $\\Omega^{T}\\Omega=C(\\Theta^{T}\\Theta)C^{T}$ from which it follows that the determinants of $\\Omega^{T}\\Omega$ and $\\Theta^{T}\\Theta$ are equal, up to sign. Hence, $det(\\Theta^{T}\\Theta)=det(\\Omega^{T}\\Omega)$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.2.5", "question": "Show that the discriminant is well-defined. In other words, show that given $\\omega_{1},\\omega_{2},...,\\omega_{n}$ and $\\theta_{1},\\theta_{2},...,\\theta_{n}$ two integral bases for $K$, we get the same discriminant for $K$.", "solution": "Just as above, we have $\\Omega^{T}\\Omega=C(\\Theta^{T}\\Theta)C^{T}$ for some matrix $C$ with determinant $\\pm1$. Then $d_{K}=(det~\\Omega)^{2}=(det~\\Theta)^{2}(det~C)^{2}=(det~\\Theta)^{2}$. This proves that the discriminant does not depend upon the choice of integral basis.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.2.6", "question": "Show that $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(1,a,...,a^{n-1})=\\prod_{i>j}(\\sigma_{i}(a)-\\sigma_{j}(a))^{2}.$ We denote $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(1,a,...,a^{n-1})$ by $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(a)$.", "solution": "First we note that $\\sigma_{i}(a)$ takes $a$ to its $i$th conjugate, $a^{(i)}$. Define the matrix $\\Omega=(\\sigma_{i}(a^{j}))$. Then it is easy to see that\n$$\\Omega=(\\begin{matrix}1&a&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&a^{n-1}\\\\ \\vdots&\\vdots&&\\\\ 1&a^{(n)}&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&a^{(n)n-1}\\end{matrix}),$$\nwhich is a Vandermonde matrix, and so $det~\\Omega=\\prod_{i>j}(a^{(i)}-a^{(j)})=\\prod_{i>j}(\\sigma_{i}(a)-\\sigma_{j}(a))$. It follows that $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(a)=[det(\\sigma_{i}(a^{j}))]^{2} =\\prod_{i<j}(\\sigma_{i}(a)-\\sigma_{j}(a))^{2}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.2.7", "question": "Suppose that $u_{i}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}a_{ij}v_{j}$ with $a_{ij}\\in\\mathbb{Q}$, $v_{j}\\in K$. Show that $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(u_{1},u_{2},...,u_{n})=(det(a_{ij}))^{2}d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(v_{1},v_{2},...,v_{n})$.", "solution": "By definition, $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(u_{1},u_{2},...,u_{n})=[det(\\sigma_{i}(u_{j}))]^{2}.$ Since $\\sigma_{i}(u_{j})=\\sigma_{i}(\\sum_{k=1}^{n}a_{jk}v_{k})=\\sum_{k=1}^{n}a_{jk}\\sigma_{i}(v_{k}).$ If we define the matrices $U=(\\sigma_{i}(u_{j})), A=(a_{ij}), V=(\\sigma_{i}(v_{j}))$, then it is clear that $U=VA^{T}$ and so $(det~U)^{2}=(det~VA^{T})^{2},$ and we get the desired result: $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(u_{1},u_{2},...,u_{n})=(det(a_{ij}))^{2}d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(v_{1},v_{2},...,v_{n})$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.2.8", "question": "Let $a_{1},a_{2},...,a_{n}\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ be linearly independent over $\\mathbb{Q}$. Let $N=\\mathbb{Z}a_{1}+\\mathbb{Z}a_{2}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}a_{n}$ and $m=[\\mathcal{O}_{K}:N]$. Prove that $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(a_{1},a_{2},...,a_{n})=m^{2}d_{K}$.", "solution": "Let $\\alpha_{1},\\alpha_{2},...,\\alpha_{n}$ be an integral basis of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Theorem 4.2.2 says that $N$ has a basis $\\beta_{1},\\beta_{2},...,\\beta_{n}$ such that $\\beta_{i}=\\sum_{j\\ge i}p_{ij}\\alpha_{j}$. Then from Exercise 4.2.7,\n$$d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\beta_{1},...,\\beta_{n})=(det(p_{ij}))^{2}d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\alpha_{1},...,\\alpha_{n}) =m^{2}d_{K}.$$\nReasoning as in Exercise 4.2.5, we deduce $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\beta_{1},...,\\beta_{n})=d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(a_{1},...,a_{n})$ which proves the result.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.3.2", "question": "Let $m\\in\\mathbb{Z}$, $\\alpha\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Prove that $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\alpha+m)=d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\alpha)$.", "solution": "By definition, $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\alpha)=\\prod_{i<j}(\\alpha^{(i)}-\\alpha^{(j)})^{2}.$ We note that the $i$th conjugate of $\\alpha+m$ is simply $\\alpha^{(i)}+m$, and so\n$$d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\alpha+m)=\\prod_{i<j}(\\alpha^{(i)}+m-(\\alpha^{(j)}+m))^{2} =\\prod_{i<j}(\\alpha^{(i)}-\\alpha^{(j)})^{2} =d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\alpha),$$\nas desired.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.3.3", "question": "Let $\\alpha$ be an algebraic integer, and let $f(x)$ be the minimal polynomial of $\\alpha$. If $f$ has degree $n$, show that $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\alpha)=(-1)^{\\binom{n}{2}}\\prod_{i=1}^{n}f^{\\prime}(\\alpha^{(i)})$.", "solution": "Let $f(x)$ be the minimal polynomial of $\\alpha$. Then if $\\alpha^{(1)},...,\\alpha^{(n)}$ are the conjugates of $\\alpha$, $f(x)=\\prod_{k=1}^{n}(x-\\alpha^{(k)})$. Then\n$$f^{\\prime}(x)=\\sum_{k=1}^{n}\\frac{f(x)}{(x-\\alpha^{(k)})}$$\nand $f^{\\prime}(\\alpha^{(i)})=\\prod_{k\\ne i}(\\alpha^{(i)}-\\alpha^{(k)}).$ Therefore\n$$\\prod_{i=1}^{n}f^{\\prime}(\\alpha^{(i)})=\\prod_{i=1}^{n}\\prod_{k\\ne i}(\\alpha^{(i)}-\\alpha^{(k)}) =\\prod_{i<k}[-(\\alpha^{(i)}-\\alpha^{(k)})^{2}] =(-1)^{\\binom{n}{2}}d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\alpha).$$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.3.5", "question": "If $D\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$, show that every integer of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{D})$ can be written as $(a+b\\sqrt{D})/2$ where $a\\equiv b \\pmod 2$.", "solution": "By Example 4.3.4, an integral basis is given by $1, (1+\\sqrt{D})/2.$ Thus every integer is of the form\n$$c+d(\\frac{1+\\sqrt{D}}{2})=\\frac{(2c+d)+d\\sqrt{D}}{2}=\\frac{a+b\\sqrt{D}}{2}.$$\nThen we see that $a=2c+d, b=d$ satisfies $a\\equiv b \\pmod 2$. Conversely, if $a\\equiv b \\pmod 2$, writing $d=b$ and $a=2c+d$ for some $c$, we find $\\frac{a+b\\sqrt{D}}{2}=c+d(\\frac{1+\\sqrt{D}}{2})$ is an integer of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{D})$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.3.7", "question": "Let $\\zeta$ be any primitive $p$th root of unity, and $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta)$. Show that $1,\\zeta,...,\\zeta^{p-2}$ form an integral basis of $K$.", "solution": "The minimal polynomial of $\\zeta$ is the $p$th cyclotomic polynomial, $\\Phi(x)=\\frac{x^{p}-1}{x-1}=1+x+x^{2}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+x^{p-1}.$ We want to show that this is irreducible. Consider instead the polynomial $F(x)=\\Phi(x+1)$. Clearly $F$ will be irreducible over $\\mathbb{Q}$ if and only if $\\Phi$ is.\n$$F(x)=\\frac{(x+1)^{p}-1}{x}=x^{p-1}+px^{p-2}+\\binom{p}{2}x^{p-3}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\binom{p}{p-2}x+p.$$\nThis is Eisensteinian with respect to $p$ and so $F(x)$ (and thus $\\Phi(x))$ is irreducible. The conjugates of $\\zeta$ are $\\zeta,\\zeta^{2},...,\\zeta^{p-1}$. We can deduce that $[K:\\mathbb{Q}]=p-1$. Now, $\\Phi^{\\prime}(x)=\\frac{px^{p-1}(x-1)-(x^{p}-1)}{(x-1)^{2}}=\\frac{px^{p-1}-(1+x+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+x^{p-1})}{x-1}$ and so $\\Phi^{\\prime}(\\zeta^{k})=\\frac{p\\zeta^{-k}}{\\zeta^{k}-1}.$ Using Exercise 4.3.3, we can compute\n$$d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\zeta)=\\pm\\prod_{k=1}^{p-1}\\frac{p\\zeta^{-k}}{\\zeta^{k}-1} =\\pm p^{p-1}\\frac{1}{\\prod_{k=1}^{p-1}(\\zeta^{k}-1)} =\\pm p^{p-1}\\frac{1}{\\prod_{k=1}^{p-1}(1-\\zeta^{k})} =\\pm p^{p-2},$$\nsince $\\prod_{k=1}^{p-1}(1-\\zeta^{k})=\\Phi(1)=p$. We know that $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\zeta)=p^{p-2}=m^{2}d_{K}$ and also that $p\\nmid m$ because $F$, the minimal polynomial for $\\zeta-1$ is $p$-Eisensteinian, and $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\zeta-1)=d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\zeta)$. Then $m$ must be 1, meaning that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[1,\\zeta,...,\\zeta^{p-2}]$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.4.1", "question": "Let $\\mathfrak{a}$ be a nonzero ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Show that $\\mathfrak{a}\\cap\\mathbb{Z}\\ne\\{0\\}$.", "solution": "Let $\\alpha$ be a nonzero algebraic integer in $\\mathfrak{a}$ satisfying the minimal polynomial $x^{r}+a_{r-1}x^{r-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{0}=0$ with $a_{i}\\in\\mathbb{Z} \\forall i$ and $a_{0}$ not zero. Then $a_{0}=-(\\alpha^{r}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{1}\\alpha)$. The left-hand side of this equation is in $\\mathbb{Z}$, while the right-hand side is in $\\mathfrak{a}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.4.2", "question": "Show that $\\mathfrak{a}$ has an integral basis.", "solution": "Let $\\mathfrak{a}$ be an ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, and let $\\omega_{1},\\omega_{2},...,\\omega_{n}$ be an integral basis for $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Note that for any $\\omega_{i}$ in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, $a_{0}\\omega_{i}=-(\\alpha^{r}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{1}\\alpha)\\omega_{i}\\in\\mathfrak{a}.$ Therefore $\\mathfrak{a}$ has finite index in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ and $\\mathfrak{a}\\subseteq\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{1}+\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{2}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{n}$ has maximal rank. Then since $\\mathfrak{a}$ is a submodule of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, by Theorem 4.2.2 there exists an integral basis for $\\mathfrak{a}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.4.3", "question": "Show that if $\\mathfrak{a}$ is a nonzero ideal in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, then $\\mathfrak{a}$ has finite index in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "solution": "Surely, if $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{1}+\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{2}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{n}$ then by the preceding two exercises we can pick a rational integer $a$ such that\n$$a\\mathcal{O}_{K}=a\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{1}+a\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{2}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{n}\\subset\\mathfrak{a}\\subset\\mathcal{O}_{K}.$$\nBut $a\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ obviously has index $a^{n}$ in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Thus, the index of $\\mathfrak{a}$ in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ must be finite.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.4.4", "question": "Show that every nonzero prime ideal in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ contains exactly one integer prime.", "solution": "If $\\wp$ is a prime ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, then certainly it contains an integer, from Exercise 4.4.1. By the definition of a prime ideal, if $ab\\in\\wp,$ either $a\\in\\wp$ or $b\\in\\wp$. So $\\wp$ must contain some rational prime. Now, if $\\wp$ contained two distinct rational primes $p, q$, say, then it would necessarily contain their greatest common denominator which is 1. But this contradicts the assumption of nontriviality. So every prime ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ contains exactly one integer prime.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.4.5", "question": "Let $\\mathfrak{a}$ be an integral ideal with basis $\\alpha_{1},...,\\alpha_{n}$. Show that $[det(\\alpha_{i}^{(j)})]^{2}=(N\\mathfrak{a})^{2}d_{K}$.", "solution": "Since $\\mathfrak{a}$ is a submodule of index $N\\mathfrak{a}$ in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, this is immediate from Exercise 4.2.8.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.1", "question": "Let $K$ be an algebraic number field. Show that $d_{K}\\in\\mathbb{Z}.$", "solution": "By definition $d_{K}=det(\\omega_{i}^{(j)})^{2}=det(Tr(\\omega_{i}\\omega_{j}))$, where $\\omega_{1},...,\\omega_{n}$ is an integral basis of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Since $Tr(\\omega_{i}\\omega_{j})\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ the determinant is an integer.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.2", "question": "Let $K/\\mathbb{Q}$ be an algebraic number field of degree $n$. Show that $d_{K}\\equiv0$ or 1 (mod 4). This is known as Stickelberger's criterion.", "solution": "Let $\\omega_{1},...,\\omega_{n}$ be an integral basis of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. By definition, $d_{K}=det(\\sigma_{i}(\\omega_{j}))^{2}$, where $\\sigma_{1},...,\\sigma_{n}$ are the distinct embeddings of $K$ into $\\overline{\\mathbb{Q}}$. Now write $det(\\sigma_{i}(\\omega_{j}))=P-N$ where $P$ is the contribution arising from the even permutations and $N$ the odd permutations in the definition of the determinant. Then $d_{K}=(P-N)^{2}=(P+N)^{2}-4PN.$ Since $\\sigma_{i}(P+N)=P+N$ and $\\sigma_{i}(PN)=PN$ we see that $P+N$ and $PN$ are integers. Reducing mod 4 gives the result.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.3", "question": "Let $f(x)=x^{n}+a_{n-1}x^{n-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{1}x+a_{0}$ with $a_{i}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ be the minimal polynomial of $\\theta$. Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$. If for each prime $p$ such that $p^{2}|d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\theta)$ we have $f(x)$ Eisensteinian with respect to $p$, show that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]$.", "solution": "By Example 4.3.1, the index of $\\theta$ is not divisible by $p$ for any prime $p$ satisfying $p^{2}|d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\theta)$. By Exercise 4.2.8, $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\theta)=m^{2}d_{K}$ where $m=[\\mathcal{O}_{K}:\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]]$. Hence $m=1$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.4", "question": "If the minimal polynomial of $\\alpha$ is $f(x)=x^{n}+ax+b$ show that for $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\alpha)$, $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\alpha)=(-1)^{\\binom{n}{2}}(n^{n}b^{n-1}+a^{n}(1-n)^{n-1})$.", "solution": "By Exercise 4.3.3, $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\alpha)=(-1)^{\\binom{n}{2}}\\prod_{i=1}^{n}f^{\\prime}(\\alpha^{(i)}).$, where $\\alpha^{(1)},...,\\alpha^{(n)}$ are the conjugates of $\\alpha$. Now $f^{\\prime}(x)=nx^{n-1}+a=\\frac{1}{x}(nx^{n}+ax)$ so that $f^{\\prime}(\\alpha^{(i)})=\\frac{(-n(a\\alpha^{(i)}+b)+a\\alpha^{(i)})}{\\alpha^{(i)}}$. Hence\n$$\\prod_{i=1}^{n}f^{\\prime}(\\alpha^{(i)})=(-1)^{n}b^{-1}\\prod_{i=1}^{n}(a(1-n)\\alpha^{(i)}-nb) =b^{-1}a^{n}(1-n)^{n}f(\\frac{nb}{a(1-n)})$$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.5", "question": "Determine an integral basis for $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$ where $\\theta^{3}+2\\theta+1=0.$", "solution": "By applying the previous exercise, the discriminant of $\\theta$ is -59, which is squarefree. Therefore $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.6 (a)", "question": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$ where $\\theta^{3}-\\theta^{2}-2\\theta-8=0$. Show that $f(x)=x^{3}-x^{2}-2x-8$ is irreducible over $\\mathbb{Q}$.", "solution": "Note that if (a) is not true, then $f$ has a linear factor and by the rational root theorem, this factor must be of the form $x-a$ where $a|8$. A systematic check rules out this possibility.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.6 (b)", "question": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$ where $\\theta^{3}-\\theta^{2}-2\\theta-8=0$. Consider $\\beta=(\\theta^{2}+\\theta)/2$. Show that $\\beta^{3}-3\\beta^{2}-10\\beta-8=0$. Hence $\\beta$ is integral.", "solution": "(b) can be checked directly.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.6 (c)", "question": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$ where $\\theta^{3}-\\theta^{2}-2\\theta-8=0$. Show that $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\theta)=-4(503)$, and $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(1,\\theta,\\beta)=-503$. Deduce that $1, \\theta, \\beta$ is a $\\mathbb{Z}$-basis of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "solution": "This is easy to deduce from the formula $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(1,\\theta,\\beta)=\\frac{1}{4}d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\theta)$ as a simple computation shows.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.6 (d)", "question": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$ where $\\theta^{3}-\\theta^{2}-2\\theta-8=0$. Show that every integer $\\alpha$ of $K$ has an even discriminant.", "solution": "Write $x=A+B\\theta+C\\beta, A,B,C\\in\\mathbb{Z}$. Since $\\beta^{2}=6+2\\theta+3\\beta, \\theta^{2}=2\\beta-\\theta, \\theta\\beta=2\\beta+4,$ we find $x^{2}=(a^{2}+6C^{2}+8BC)+\\theta(2C^{2}-B^{2}+2AB)+\\beta(2B^{2}+3C^{2}+2AC+4BC)$ so that $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(1,x,x^{2})\\equiv-503(BC)^{2}(3C+B)^{2} \\pmod 2,$ which is an even number in all cases.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.6 (e)", "question": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$ where $\\theta^{3}-\\theta^{2}-2\\theta-8=0$. Deduce that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ has no integral basis of the form $\\mathbb{Z}[\\alpha]$.", "solution": "By (d), $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\alpha)$ is even and hence is not equal to -503, which proves that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ has no integral basis of the form $\\mathbb{Z}[\\alpha]$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.7", "question": "Let $m=p^{a}$ with $p$ prime and $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m}).$ Show that $(1-\\zeta_{m})^{\\varphi(m)}=p\\mathcal{O}_{K}$", "solution": "First note that $\\frac{x^{m}-1}{x^{m/p}-1}=\\prod_{1\\le b<m, (b,m)=1}(x-\\zeta_{m}^{b})$ so that taking the limit as $x$ goes to 1 of both sides gives\n$$p=\\prod_{1\\le b<m, (b,m)=1}(1-\\zeta_{m}^{b}) =(1-\\zeta_{m})^{\\varphi(m)}\\prod_{(b,m)=1, b\\ne 1}\\frac{1-\\zeta_{m}^{b}}{1-\\zeta_{m}}.$$\nThis latter quantity is a unit since $\\frac{1-\\zeta_{m}}{1-\\zeta_{m}^{b}}=\\frac{1-\\zeta_{m}^{ab}}{1-\\zeta_{m}^{b}}=1+\\zeta_{m}^{b}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\zeta_{m}^{b(a-1)}$ for any $a$ satisfying $ab\\equiv1 \\pmod m$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.8", "question": "Let $m=p^{a}$ with $p$ prime, and $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m})$. Show that $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\zeta_{m})=\\frac{(-1)^{\\varphi(m)/2}m^{\\varphi(m)}}{p^{m/p}}$", "solution": "We need to compute the Vandermonde determinant given by $(-1)^{\\varphi(m)/2} \\prod_{1\\le a,b<m, (a,m)=1, (b,m)=1, a\\ne b}(\\zeta_{m}^{a}-\\zeta_{m}^{b}).$ Let $\\theta=\\prod_{1\\le b<m, (b,m)=1, b\\ne 1}(\\zeta_{m}-\\zeta_{m}^{b}).$ Clearly $\\theta=\\phi_{m}^{\\prime}(\\zeta_{m})$ and $N_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\theta)$ is the discriminant we seek. Since $\\phi_{m}(x)=\\frac{x^{m}-1}{x^{m/p}-1},$ we find $\\phi_{m}^{\\prime}(\\zeta_{m})=\\frac{m\\zeta_{m}^{m-1}}{\\zeta_{m}^{m/p}-1}$ and the norm of this element is $\\frac{m^{m}}{N_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\zeta_{m}^{m/p}-1)}.$ Because $\\eta=\\zeta_{m}^{m/p}$ is a primitive $p$th root of unity, $N_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\zeta_{m}^{m/p}-1)=N_{\\mathbb{Q}(\\eta)/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\eta-1)^{m/p}$. In Exercise 4.3.7, we saw that $N_{\\mathbb{Q}(\\eta)/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\eta-1)=p$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.9", "question": "Let $m=p^{a}$, with $p$ prime. Show that $\\{1,\\zeta_{m},...,\\zeta_{m}^{\\varphi(m)-1}\\}$ is an integral basis for the ring of integers of $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m})$.", "solution": "Clearly $\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{m}]\\subseteq\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. We want to prove the reverse inclusion. Let $\\lambda=1-\\zeta_{m}$. Since $\\lambda^{j}=(1-\\zeta_{m})^{j}\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{m}]$ and $\\zeta_{m}^{j}=(1-\\lambda)^{j}\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{m}]$, we see that $\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{m}]=\\mathbb{Z}[\\lambda]$. Thus, it suffices to show $\\mathbb{Z}[\\lambda]\\supseteq\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Let $\\alpha\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ and write $\\alpha=\\sum_{j=0}^{\\varphi(m)-1}a_{j}\\lambda^{j}=\\sum_{j=0}^{\\varphi(m)-1}b_{j}\\zeta_{m}^{j},$ $a_{j},b_{j}\\in\\mathbb{Q}$. It suffices to show $a_{j}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ for $j=0,1,...,\\varphi(m)-1$. Let $\\sigma_{c}(\\zeta_{m})=\\zeta_{m}^{c}.$ Then $\\sigma_{c}(\\alpha)=\\sum_{j=0}^{\\varphi(m)-1}b_{j}\\sigma_{c}(\\zeta_{m})^{j}=\\sum_{j=0}^{\\varphi(m)-1}b_{j}\\zeta_{m}^{cj}$ for each $(c,m)=1$. We solve for $b_{j}$ using Cramer's rule. Moreover, by the previous question, we see that $b_{j}=\\frac{c_{j}}{p^{d_{j}}}$ where $c_{j}\\in\\mathbb{Z}.$ Thus, $a_{j}$ has at most a power of $p$ in its denominator. Let $n$ be the least nonnegative integer such that $p^{n}a_{j}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ for $j=0,1,...,\\varphi(m)-1$. Suppose $n>0$. Let $k$ be the smallest nonnegative integer such that $p$ does not divide $p^{n}a_{k}$. Then $a_{r}\\lambda^{r}\\in p\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\lambda^{\\varphi(m)}\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ (by the penultimate question) for $r=0,1,...,k-1$. Since $\\alpha$ is an integer, $p^{n}\\alpha\\in p\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\lambda^{\\varphi(m)}\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ so that $\\sum_{j=k}^{\\varphi(m)-1}p^{n}a_{j}\\lambda^{j-k}\\in\\lambda\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ so that $p^{n}a_{k}\\in\\lambda\\mathcal{O}_{K}\\cap\\mathbb{Z}=p\\mathbb{Z}$ a contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.10", "question": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m})$ where $m=p^{a}.$ Show that $d_{K}=\\frac{(-1)^{\\varphi(m)/2}m^{\\varphi(m)}}{p^{m/p}}.$", "solution": "This is immediate from the previous two questions.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.11", "question": "Show that $\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{n}+\\zeta_{n}^{-1}]$ is the ring of integers of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{n}+\\zeta_{n}^{-1})$, where $\\zeta_{n}$ denotes a primitive $n$th root of unity, and $n=p^{\\alpha}$.", "solution": "Suppose $\\alpha=a_{0}+a_{1}(\\zeta_{n}+\\zeta_{n}^{-1})+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{N}(\\zeta_{n}+\\zeta_{n}^{-1})^{N}$ is an algebraic integer with $N\\le\\frac{1}{2}\\phi(n)-1$ and the $a_{i}\\in\\mathbb{Q}$. By subtracting those terms with $a_{i}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$, we may suppose $a_{N}\\notin\\mathbb{Z}.$ Multiplying by $\\zeta_{n}^{N}$ and expanding the result as a polynomial in $\\zeta_{n}$ we find that $\\zeta_{n}^{N}\\alpha=a_{N}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{N}\\zeta_{n}^{2N}$ is an algebraic integer in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{n})$. Therefore, it lies in $\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{n}]$. Since $2N\\le\\phi(n)-2\\le\\phi(n)-1,$ we conclude $a_{N}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ contrary to our assumption above. (This is also true for arbitrary $n$ by applying Exercise 4.5.25.)", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.12", "question": "Let $K$ and $L$ be algebraic number fields of degree $m$ and $n$, respectively, over $\\mathbb{Q}$. Let $d=gcd(d_{K},d_{L})$. Show that if $[KL:\\mathbb{Q}]=mn$, then $\\mathcal{O}_{KL}\\subseteq 1/d \\mathcal{O}_{K}\\mathcal{O}_{L}$.", "solution": "Let $\\{\\alpha_{1},...,\\alpha_{m}\\}$ be a $\\mathbb{Z}$-basis for $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ and let $\\{\\beta_{1},...,\\beta_{n}\\}$ be a $\\mathbb{Z}$-basis for $\\mathcal{O}_{L}$. Then $\\alpha_{i}\\beta_{j}$, $1\\le i\\le m,$ $1\\le j\\le n$, is a $\\mathbb{Q}$-basis for $KL$ over $\\mathbb{Q}$ since $[KL:\\mathbb{Q}]=mn$. Any $\\omega\\in\\mathcal{O}_{KL}$ can therefore be written as $\\omega=\\sum_{i,j}\\frac{m_{ij}}{r}\\alpha_{i}\\beta_{j},$ where $r, m_{ij}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ and $gcd(r,gcd(m_{ij}))=1$. It suffices to show that $r|d_{K}$ and by symmetry $r|d_{L}$ so that $r|d.$ Since $[KL:\\mathbb{Q}]=mn$, every embedding $\\sigma$ of $K$ into $\\mathbb{C}$ can be extended to $KL$ acting trivially on $L$. Hence $\\sigma(\\omega)=\\sum_{i,j}\\frac{m_{ij}}{r}\\sigma(\\alpha_{i})\\beta_{j}.$ Set $x_{i}=\\sum_{j}m_{ij}\\beta_{j}/r$. We then obtain $m$ equations $\\sum_{i=1}^{m}\\sigma(\\alpha_{i})x_{i}=\\sigma(\\omega),$ one for each $\\sigma:K\\hookrightarrow\\mathbb{C}$. We solve for $x_{i}$ by Cramer's rule: $x_{i}=\\gamma_{i}/\\delta$ where $\\delta=det(\\sigma(\\alpha_{i}))$. Since $\\delta^{2}=d_{K}$ we find $\\delta\\gamma_{i}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}\\frac{\\delta^{2}m_{ij}}{r}\\beta_{j}\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ since $\\delta$ and each of $\\gamma_{i}$ are algebraic integers. Hence $d_{K}m_{ij}/r$ are all integers. It follows that $r$ divides all $d_{K}m_{ij}$. Since $gcd(r,gcd(m_{ij}))=1$, we deduce $r|d_{K}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.13", "question": "Let $K$ and $L$ be algebraic number fields of degree $m$ and $n$, respectively, with $gcd(d_{K},d_{L})=1$. If $\\{\\alpha_{1},...,\\alpha_{m}\\}$ is an integral basis of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ and $\\{\\beta_{1},...,\\beta_{n}\\}$ is an integral basis of $\\mathcal{O}_{L}$, show that $\\mathcal{O}_{KL}$ has an integral basis $\\{\\alpha_{i}\\beta_{j}\\}$ given that $[KL:\\mathbb{Q}]=mn.$", "solution": "This is immediate from the previous question.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.14", "question": "Find an integral basis for $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{2},\\sqrt{-3})$.", "solution": "If $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{2})$, $L=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-3})$ then $d_{K}=8$, $d_{L}=-3$ which are coprime. By the previous question, a $\\mathbb{Z}$-basis for the ring of integers of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{2},\\sqrt{-3})$ is given by $\\{1,\\sqrt{2},\\frac{1+\\sqrt{-3}}{2},\\sqrt{2}(\\frac{1+\\sqrt{-3}}{2})\\}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.15", "question": "Let $p$ and $q$ be distinct primes $\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$. Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{p}), L=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{q})$. Find a $\\mathbb{Z}$-basis for $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{p},\\sqrt{q})$.", "solution": "We have $d_{K}=p,$ $d_{L}=q$ which are coprime. Now invoke the penultimate question to deduce that $\\{1,\\frac{1+\\sqrt{p}}{2},\\frac{1+\\sqrt{q}}{2},(\\frac{1+\\sqrt{p}}{2})(\\frac{1+\\sqrt{q}}{2})\\}$ is a $\\mathbb{Z}$-basis for the ring of integers of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{p},\\sqrt{q})$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.16", "question": "Let $K$ be an algebraic number field of degree $n$ over $\\mathbb{Q}$. Let $a_{1},...,a_{n}\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ be linearly independent over $\\mathbb{Q}$. Set $\\Delta=d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(a_{1},...,a_{n})$. Show that if $\\alpha\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, then $\\Delta\\alpha\\in\\mathbb{Z}[a_{1},...,a_{n}]$.", "solution": "Write $\\alpha=c_{1}a_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+c_{n}a_{n}$ for some rational numbers $c_{i}.$ By taking conjugates, we get a system of $n$ equations and we can solve for $c_{i}$ using Cramer's rule. Thus $c_{j}=A_{j}D/\\Delta$ where $D^{2}=\\Delta$ and it is easy to see that $A_{j}D$ is an algebraic integer. Therefore $\\Delta c_{j}$ is an algebraic integer lying in $\\mathbb{Q}$ so $\\Delta c_{j}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ as required.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.17", "question": "Suppose $K$ is an algebraic number field of degree $n$ over $\\mathbb{Q}$. Let $a_{1},...,a_{n}\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ be linearly independent over $\\mathbb{Q}$ and set $\\Delta=d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(a_{1},...,a_{n})$. For each $i$, choose the least natural number $d_{ii}$ so that for some $d_{ij}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$, the number $w_{i}=\\Delta^{-1}\\sum_{j=1}^{i}d_{ij}a_{j}\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}.$ Show that $w_{1},...,w_{n}$ is an integral basis of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "solution": "First observe that there are integers $c_{ij}$ so that $\\Delta^{-1}\\sum_{j=1}^{i}c_{ij}a_{j}\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ (e.g., $c_{ij}=\\Delta)$. Clearly $w_{1},...,w_{n}$ are linearly independent over $\\mathbb{Q}$ because $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(w_{1},...,w_{n})=\\Delta^{-n}(d_{11}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot d_{nn})^{2}d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(a_{1},...,a_{n})$ by Exercise 4.2.7, and the right-hand side is nonzero. Observe now that if $\\alpha\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ can be written as $\\alpha=\\Delta^{-1}(c_{1}a_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+c_{j}a_{j})$ for some $j$, then $d_{jj}|c_{j}$. Indeed, write $c_{j}=sd_{jj}+r,0\\le r<d_{jj}$, so that $\\alpha-sw_{j}=\\Delta^{-1}((c_{1}-d_{j1})a_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+ra_{j})\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K},$ contrary to our choice of $w_{j}$ if $r\\ne0$. We now show by induction on $j$ that every number of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ of the form $\\Delta^{-1}(x_{1}a_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+x_{j}a_{j})$ with $x_{i}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ lies in $\\mathbb{Z}[w_{1},...,w_{n}]$. For $j=1$, there is nothing to prove because then $d_{11}|x_{1}$ and we are done. Assume that we have proved it for $j<k$. Then suppose $y=\\Delta^{-1}(x_{1}a_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+x_{k}a_{k})\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ with $x_{i}\\in\\mathbb{Z}.$ Then $d_{kk}|x_{k}$ so that for some integer $t$, $y-tw_{k}=\\Delta^{-1}(x_{1}^{\\prime}a_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+x_{k-1}^{\\prime}a_{k-1})\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. By induction, the right-hand side lies in $\\mathbb{Z}[w_{1},...,w_{n}]$ and so does $y$. For $j=n$ this means that every number of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ of the form $\\Delta^{-1}(x_{1}a_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+x_{n}a_{n})$ with $x_{i}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ lies in $\\mathbb{Z}[w_{1},...,w_{n}]$. But by the previous exercise, every $\\alpha\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ can be so expressed.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.18", "question": "If $K$ is an algebraic number field of degree $n$ over $\\mathbb{Q}$ and $a_{1},...,a_{n}\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ are linearly independent over $\\mathbb{Q}$, then there is an integral basis $w_{1},...,w_{n}$ of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ such that $a_{j}=c_{j1}w_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+c_{jj}w_{j}, c_{ij}\\in\\mathbb{Z}, j=1,...,n.$", "solution": "We take $w_{1},...,w_{n}$ as constructed in the previous exercise. This is an integral basis. Solving for $a_{j}$ and noting that the matrix $(d_{ij})$ is lower triangular, we see that each $a_{j}$ can be written as above. Moreover, the $c_{ij}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ since $w_{1},...,w_{n}$ is an integral basis by construction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.19", "question": "$\\mathbb{Q}\\subseteq K\\subseteq L$ and $K, L$ are algebraic number fields, show that $d_{K}|d_{L}.$", "solution": "Let $[K:\\mathbb{Q}]=m$, $[L:K]=n$. Let $a_{1},...,a_{m}$ be an integral basis of $K$. Extend this to a basis of $L$ (viewed as a vector space over $\\mathbb{Q}$) so that $a_{1},...,a_{mn}$ is linearly independent over $\\mathbb{Q}$. By Exercise 3.3.7, we may suppose each $a_{i}$ is an algebraic integer. By the previous exercise, there is an integral basis $w_{1},...,w_{mn}$ of $\\mathcal{O}_{L}$ such that $a_{j}=c_{j1}w_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+c_{jj}w_{j}, c_{ij}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$. Since the matrix $(c_{ij})$ is triangular, it is easy to see that $w_{1},...,w_{m}$ lie in $K$. Because the $w_{i}$ are algebraic integers, and $a_{1},...,a_{m}$ is an integral basis of $K$, it follows that $w_{1},...,w_{m}$ is an integral basis of $K$. Now write down the definition of the discriminant of $L$. Let $\\sigma_{1},...,\\sigma_{mn}$ be the embeddings of $L$ into $\\mathbb{C}$ such that $\\sigma_{i}(w_{j})=w_{j}^{(i)}$ for $1\\le j\\le m$. We order the $\\sigma_{1},...,\\sigma_{mn}$ so that $\\sigma_{i}(x)=\\sigma_{i^{\\prime}}(x)$ for $i\\equiv i^{\\prime} \\pmod m$ and $x\\in K$. Then $d_{L}=det(\\sigma_{i}(w_{j}))^{2} = d_{K}\\cdot a,$ where $a$ is an algebraic integer. Since $d_{L}/d_{K}$ is a rational number, we deduce that $a$ is a rational integer.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.20", "question": "Suppose $K$ is a number field with $r_{1}$ real embeddings and $2r_{2}$ complex embeddings so that $r_{1}+2r_{2}=[K:\\mathbb{Q}]=n$ (say). Show that $d_{K}$ has sign $(-1)^{r_{2}}$.", "solution": "Let $\\omega_{1},...,\\omega_{n}$ be an integral basis of $K$. Then $d_{K}=det(\\sigma_{i}(\\omega_{j}))^{2}$ where $\\sigma_{1},...,\\sigma_{n}$ are the embeddings of $K$. Clearly $\\overline{det(\\sigma_{i}(\\omega_{j}))}=(-1)^{r_{2}}det(\\sigma_{i}(\\omega_{j}))$ since complex conjugation interchanges $r_{2}$ rows. If $r_{2}$ is even, then $det(\\sigma_{i}(\\omega_{j}))$ is real so that $d_{K}>0$. If $r_{2}$ is odd, $det(\\sigma_{i}(\\omega_{j}))$ is purely imaginary so that $d_{K}<0$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.21", "question": "Show that only finitely many imaginary quadratic fields $K$ are Euclidean.", "solution": "If $\\psi$ is a Euclidean algorithm for $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, then let $\\alpha_{0}\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ be such that $\\psi(\\alpha_{0})$ is the minimum nonzero value of $\\psi$. Then, every residue class mod $\\alpha_{0}$ is represented by 0 or an element $\\alpha\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ such that $\\psi(\\alpha)=0.$ Thus $\\alpha_{0}$ is a unit. In an imaginary quadratic field, there are only finitely many units. If $d_{K}\\ne-3,-4$ the units are $\\pm1$. Thus, if $d_{K}\\ne-3,-4,$ we find $N_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\alpha_{0})\\le3$, which implies that $\\alpha_{0}=\\pm1$. In particular, if $\\alpha_{1}$ is such that $\\psi(\\alpha_{1})=min~\\psi(\\alpha)$ where the minimum ranges over $\\psi(\\alpha)\\ne\\psi(\\alpha_{0})$, then $\\alpha_{1}$ is not a unit, $\\psi(\\alpha_{1})>\\psi(\\alpha_{0})$ so that not every residue class mod $\\alpha_{1}$ can be represented by a class containing an element whose $\\psi$-value is smaller than $\\psi(\\alpha_{1})$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.22", "question": "Show that $\\mathbb{Z}[(1+\\sqrt{-19})/2]$ is not Euclidean. (Recall that in Exercise 2.5.6 we showed this ring is not Euclidean for the norm map.)", "solution": "The argument of the previous exercise shows that not all residue classes mod 2 and mod 3 are represented by elements of smaller $\\psi$-value.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.23 (a)", "question": "Let $A=(a_{ij})$ be an $m\\times m$ matrix, $B=(b_{ij})$ an $n\\times n$ matrix. We define the (Kronecker) tensor product $A\\otimes B$ to be the $mn\\times mn$ matrix obtained as\n$$(\\begin{matrix}Ab_{11}&Ab_{12}&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&Ab_{1n}\\\\ Ab_{21}&Ab_{22}&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&Ab_{2n}\\\\ \\vdots&\\vdots&\\vdots\\\\ Ab_{n1}&Ab_{n2}&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&Ab_{nn}\\end{matrix}).$$\nwhere each block $Ab_{ij}$ has the form $(\\begin{matrix}a_{11}b_{ij}&a_{12}b_{ij}&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&a_{1m}b_{ij}\\\\ a_{21}b_{ij}&a_{22}b_{ij}&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&a_{2m}b_{ij}\\\\ \\vdots&&\\vdots\\\\ a_{m1}b_{ij}&a_{m2}b_{ij}&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&a_{mm}b_{ij}\\end{matrix}).$\nIf $C$ and $D$ are $m\\times m$ and $n\\times n$ matrices, respectively, show that $(A\\otimes B)(C\\otimes D)=(AC)\\otimes(BD).$", "solution": "Part (a) is a straightforward matrix multiplication computation.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.23 (b)", "question": "Prove that $det(A\\otimes B)=(det~A)^{n}(det~B)^{m}.$", "solution": "For part (b), we use linear algebra to find a matrix $U$ such that $U^{-1}BU$ is upper triangular: $U^{-1}BU=(\\begin{matrix}c_{11}&c_{12}&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&c_{1n}\\\\ 0&c_{22}&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&c_{2n}\\\\ \\vdots&\\vdots&\\vdots\\\\ 0&0&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&c_{m}\\end{matrix}).$ Then $det~B=c_{11}c_{22}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot c_{nn}$. Also, by (a), $(I\\otimes U)^{-1}(A\\otimes B)(I\\otimes U)=A\\otimes(U^{-1}BU)$ which is $(\\begin{matrix}Ae_{11}&Ae_{12}&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&Ae_{1n}\\\\ 0&Ae_{22}&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&Ae_{2n}\\\\ \\vdots&\\vdots&\\vdots\\\\ 0&0&\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot&Ae_{m}\\end{matrix}).$ Again, by linear algebra, we see that $det(A\\otimes B)=\\prod_{i=1}^{n}det(Ac_{ii}) =\\prod_{i=1}^{n}(c_{ii}^{m}det~A) =(det~B)^{m}(det~A)^{n},$ as desired.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.24", "question": "Let $K$ and $L$ be algebraic number fields of degree $m$ and $n$, respectively, with $gcd(d_{K},d_{L})=1.$ Show that $d_{KL}=d_{K}^{n}\\cdot d_{L}^{m}.$ If we set $\\delta(M)=\\frac{log|d_{M}|}{[M:\\mathbb{Q}]}$, deduce that $\\delta(KL)=\\delta(K)+\\delta(L)$ whenever $gcd(d_{K},d_{L})=1.$", "solution": "By a previous exercise, $\\mathcal{O}_{KL}$ has integral basis $\\{\\alpha_{i}\\beta_{j}\\}$ where $\\alpha_{1},...,\\alpha_{m}$ is an integral basis of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ and $\\beta_{1},...,\\beta_{n}$ is an integral basis of $\\mathcal{O}_{L}$. Let $A=(Tr_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\alpha_{i}\\alpha_{j}))$, $B=(Tr_{L/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\beta_{i}\\beta_{j}))$. Then it is easily verified that the discriminant of $KL/\\mathbb{Q}$ is $det(A\\otimes B)$. By the previous exercise, this is $d_{K}^{n}d_{L}^{m}$. The second part of the question is immediate upon taking logarithms.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.25", "question": "Let $\\zeta_{m}$ denote a primitive $m$th root of unity and let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m})$. Show that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{m}]$ and $d_{K}=\\frac{(-1)^{\\phi(m)/2}m^{\\varphi(m)}}{\\prod_{p|m}p^{\\phi(m)/(p-1)}}.$", "solution": "Factor $m=\\prod_{p^{\\alpha}||m}p^{\\alpha}.$ Since the discriminants of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{p^{\\alpha}})$ for $p^{\\alpha}||m$ are coprime, we have by the previous exercise (and Supplementary Exercise 4.5.8) $\\frac{log|d_{K}|}{\\phi(m)}=\\sum_{p^{\\alpha}||m}(\\alpha-\\frac{1}{p-1})log~p.$ The sign of the determinant is $(-1)^{r_{2}}=(-1)^{\\varphi(m)/2}$. The fact that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{m}]$ follows by an induction argument and Exercise 4.5.13.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 4.5.26", "question": "Let $K$ be an algebraic number field. Suppose that $\\theta\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ is such that $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\theta)$ is squarefree. Show that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]$.", "solution": "Let $m=[\\mathcal{O}_{K}:\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]]$. Then, by Exercise 4.2.8, $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\theta)=m^{2}d_{K}$. If $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\theta)$ is squarefree, $m=1$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.1.1}", "question": "Show that a nonzero commutative ring $R$ with identity is a field if and only if it has no nontrivial ideals.", "solution": "If $x \\in R$, $x \\neq 0$, is a nonunit, then $1 \\notin (x)$, so $(x)$ is a nontrivial ideal. Suppose that $R$ has a nontrivial ideal $\\mathfrak{a}$. Let $x \\in \\mathfrak{a}$, $x \\neq 0$. Then $(x) \\subseteq \\mathfrak{a}$. If $x$ is a unit, then $1 \\in (x) \\subseteq \\mathfrak{a}$, so $\\mathfrak{a} = R$, a contradiction. Thus, $x$ is not a unit, so $R$ is not a field.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.1.2 (a)}", "question": "Let $R$ be a commutative ring with identity. Show that $\\mathfrak{m}$ is a maximal ideal if and only if $R/\\mathfrak{m}$ is a field.", "solution": "By the correspondence between ideals of $R$ containing $\\mathfrak{m}$ and ideals of $R/\\mathfrak{m}$, $R/\\mathfrak{m}$ has a nontrivial ideal if and only if there is an ideal $\\mathfrak{a}$ of $R$ strictly between $\\mathfrak{m}$ and $R$. Thus, $\\mathfrak{m}$ is maximal $\\iff$ $R/\\mathfrak{m}$ has no nontrivial ideals $\\iff$ $R/\\mathfrak{m}$ is a field.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.1.2 (b)}", "question": "Let $R$ be a commutative ring with identity. Show that $\\mathfrak{p}$ is a prime ideal if and only if $R/\\mathfrak{p}$ is an integral domain.", "solution": "$\\mathfrak{p}$ is a prime ideal $\\iff$ $ab \\in \\mathfrak{p} \\Rightarrow a \\in \\mathfrak{p}$ or $b \\in \\mathfrak{p}$ $\\iff$ $ab + \\mathfrak{p} = 0 + \\mathfrak{p}$ in $R/\\mathfrak{p} \\Rightarrow a + \\mathfrak{p} = 0 + \\mathfrak{p}$ or $b + \\mathfrak{p} = 0 + \\mathfrak{p}$ in $R/\\mathfrak{p}$ $\\iff$ $R/\\mathfrak{p}$ has no zero-divisors $\\iff$ $R/\\mathfrak{p}$ is an integral domain.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.1.2 (c)}", "question": "Let $R$ be a commutative ring with identity. Let $\\mathfrak{a}$ and $\\mathfrak{b}$ be ideals of $R$. Show that if $\\mathfrak{p}$ is a prime ideal containing $\\mathfrak{ab}$, then $\\mathfrak{p} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{a}$ or $\\mathfrak{p} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{b}$.", "solution": "Suppose that $\\mathfrak{p} \\nsupseteq \\mathfrak{a}$. Let $a \\in \\mathfrak{a}$, $a \\notin \\mathfrak{p}$. We know that $ab \\in \\mathfrak{p}$ for all $b \\in \\mathfrak{b}$ since $\\mathfrak{ab} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{p}$. But, $a \\notin \\mathfrak{p}$. Thus, $b \\in \\mathfrak{p}$ for all $b \\in \\mathfrak{b}$, since $\\mathfrak{p}$ is prime. Thus, $\\mathfrak{b} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{p}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.1.2 (d)}", "question": "Let $R$ be a commutative ring with identity. If $\\mathfrak{p}$ is a prime ideal containing the product $\\mathfrak{a}_{1}\\mathfrak{a}_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{a}_{r}$ of $r$ ideals of $R$, show that $\\mathfrak{p} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{a}_{i}$ for some $i$.", "solution": "(By induction on $r$). The base case $r=1$ is trivial. Suppose $r>1$ and $\\mathfrak{p} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{a}_{1}\\mathfrak{a}_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{a}_{r}$. Then from part (c), $\\mathfrak{p} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{a}_{1}\\mathfrak{a}_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{a}_{r-1}$ or $\\mathfrak{p} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{a}_{r}$. If $\\mathfrak{p} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{a}_{1}\\mathfrak{a}_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{a}_{r-1}$, then the induction hypothesis implies that $\\mathfrak{p} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{a}_{i}$ for some $i \\in \\{1,...,r-1\\}$. In either case, $\\mathfrak{p} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{a}_{i}$ for some $i \\in \\{1,...,r\\}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.1.3}", "question": "Show that a finite integral domain is a field.", "solution": "Let $R$ be a finite integral domain. Let $x_{1},x_{2},...,x_{n}$ be the elements of $R$. Suppose that $x_{i}x_{j}=x_{i}x_{k}$, for some $x_{i} \\ne 0$. Then $x_{i}(x_{j}-x_{k})=0$. Since $R$ is an integral domain, $x_{j}=x_{k}$, so $j=k$. Thus, for any $x_{i} \\ne 0$, $\\{x_{i}x_{1},x_{i}x_{2},...,x_{i}x_{n}\\}=\\{x_{1},x_{2},...,x_{n}\\}$. Since $1 \\in R$, there exists $x_{j}$ such that $x_{i}x_{j}=1$. Therefore, $x_{i}$ is invertible. Thus all nonzero elements are invertible, so $R$ is a field.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.1.4}", "question": "Show that every nonzero prime ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ is maximal.", "solution": "$\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{p}$ is finite from Exercise 4.4.3 and it is an integral domain from Theorem 5.1.2 (b). Thus, Exercise 5.1.3 shows that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{p}$ is a field, which in turn implies that $\\mathfrak{p}$ is a maximal ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.1.5}", "question": "Show that every unique factorization domain is integrally closed.", "solution": "Let $R$ be a unique factorization domain, $\\alpha \\in Q(R)$. Then $\\alpha=a/b$, for some $a, b \\in R$ with $(a,b)=1$. If $\\alpha$ is integral over $R$, then we have a polynomial equation $\\alpha^{n}+c_{n-1}\\alpha^{n-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+c_{0}=0$, $c_{i} \\in R$. Thus, multiplying through by $b^{n}$ and isolating $a^{n}$, we have $a^{n}=-b(c_{n-1}a^{n-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+c_{1}ab^{n-2}+c_{0}b^{n-1})$. Thus, $b|a^{n}$. But, $(a,b)=1$. By unique factorization, $(a^{n},b)=1$. Therefore, $b$ is a unit in $R$, so $a/b \\in R$. Thus, $R$ is integrally closed.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.1.6 (1) implies (2)}", "question": "For $\\alpha \\in \\mathbb{C}$, show that if $\\alpha$ is integral over $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, then $\\mathcal{O}_{K}[\\alpha]$ is a finitely generated $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-module.", "solution": "Let $\\alpha \\in \\mathbb{C}$ be integral over $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Say $\\alpha$ satisfies a monic polynomial of degree $n$ over $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Then $\\mathcal{O}_{K}[\\alpha]=\\mathcal{O}_{K}+\\mathcal{O}_{K}\\alpha+\\mathcal{O}_{K}\\alpha^{2}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathcal{O}_{K}\\alpha^{n-1}$ and so is a finitely generated $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-module.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.1.6 (2) implies (3)}", "question": "For $\\alpha \\in \\mathbb{C}$, show that if $\\mathcal{O}_{K}[\\alpha]$ is a finitely generated $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-module, then there is a finitely generated $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-module $M \\subseteq \\mathbb{C}$ such that $\\alpha M \\subseteq M$.", "solution": "Certainly, $\\alpha \\mathcal{O}_{K}[\\alpha] \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{K}[\\alpha]$, so if $\\mathcal{O}_{K}[\\alpha]$ is a finitely generated $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-module, then the condition is satisfied with $M=\\mathcal{O}_{K}[\\alpha]$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.1.6 (3) implies (1)}", "question": "For $\\alpha \\in \\mathbb{C}$, show that if there is a finitely generated $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-module $M \\subseteq \\mathbb{C}$ such that $\\alpha M \\subseteq M$, then $\\alpha$ is integral over $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "solution": "Let $u_{1},u_{2},...,u_{n}$ generate $M$ as an $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-module. Then $\\alpha u_{i} \\in M$ for all $i=1,2,...,n$ since $\\alpha M \\subseteq M$. Let $\\alpha u_{i}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}a_{ij}u_{j}$ for $i \\in \\{1,2,...,n\\}$, $a_{ij} \\in \\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Let $A=(a_{ij})$, $B=\\alpha I_{n}-A=(b_{ij})$. Then $\\sum_{j=1}^{n}b_{ij}u_{j}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}(\\alpha\\delta_{ij}-a_{ij})u_{j} = \\alpha u_{i}-\\sum_{j=1}^{n}a_{ij}u_{j} = 0$ for all $i$. Thus, $B(u_{1},u_{2},...,u_{n})^{T}=(0,0,...,0)^{T}$. But $(0,0,...,0)^{T} \\ne (u_{1},u_{2},...,u_{n})^{T} \\in \\mathbb{C}^{n}$. Thus, $\\det(B)=0$. But, the determinant of $B$ is a monic polynomial in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}[\\alpha]$, so $\\alpha$ is integral over $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.1.7}", "question": "Prove that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ is integrally closed.", "solution": "If $\\alpha \\in K$ is integral over $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, then let $M=\\mathcal{O}_{K}u_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathcal{O}_{K}u_{n}$ with $\\alpha M \\subseteq M$. Let $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}v_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}v_{m}$ where $\\{v_{1},...,v_{m}\\}$ is a basis for $K$ over $\\mathbb{Q}$. Then $M=\\sum_{i=1}^{m}\\sum_{j=1}^{n}\\mathbb{Z}v_{i}u_{j}$ is a finitely generated $\\mathbb{Z}$-module with $\\alpha M \\subseteq M$ so $\\alpha$ is integral over $\\mathbb{Z}$. By definition, $\\alpha \\in \\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.2.1}", "question": "If $\\mathfrak{a} \\subsetneq \\mathfrak{b}$ are ideals of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, show that $N(\\mathfrak{a}) > N(\\mathfrak{b})$.", "solution": "Define a map $f:\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{a} \\longrightarrow \\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{b}$ by $f(x+\\mathfrak{a})=x+\\mathfrak{b}$. If $x+\\mathfrak{a}=y+\\mathfrak{a}$, then $x-y \\in \\mathfrak{a} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{b}$, so $x+\\mathfrak{b}=y+\\mathfrak{b}$. Thus, $f$ is well-defined. The function $f$ is not one-to-one since for any $y \\in \\mathfrak{b}\\backslash\\mathfrak{a}$, $f(y+\\mathfrak{a})=0$ but $y+\\mathfrak{a} \\ne 0$. It is onto since $x+\\mathfrak{b}=f(x+\\mathfrak{a})$. So we have a map from the finite set $\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{a}$ to the finite set $\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{b}$ which is onto but not one-to-one. Thus $|\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{a}| > |\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{b}|$ i.e., $N(\\mathfrak{a}) > N(\\mathfrak{b})$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.2.2}", "question": "Show that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ is Noetherian.", "solution": "Suppose that $\\mathfrak{a}_{1} \\subsetneq \\mathfrak{a}_{2} \\subsetneq \\mathfrak{a}_{3} \\subsetneq \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot$ is an ascending chain of ideals which does not terminate. Then $N(\\mathfrak{a}_{1}) > N(\\mathfrak{a}_{2}) > N(\\mathfrak{a}_{3}) > \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot$ but $N(\\mathfrak{a}_{i})$ is finite and positive for all $i$, so such a strictly decreasing sequence of positive integers must stop. Thus, the ascending chain of ideals must terminate.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.2.3 (1) implies (2)}", "question": "For any commutative ring $R$ with identity, show that if $R$ is Noetherian, then every nonempty set of ideals contains a maximal element.", "solution": "Suppose that $S$ is a nonempty set of ideals of $R$ that does not contain a maximal element. Let $\\mathfrak{a}_{1} \\in S$. $\\mathfrak{a}_{1}$ is not maximal in $S$, so there is an $\\mathfrak{a}_{2} \\in S$ with $\\mathfrak{a}_{1} \\subsetneq \\mathfrak{a}_{2}$. $\\mathfrak{a}_{2}$ is not a maximal element of $S$, so there exists an $\\mathfrak{a}_{3} \\in S$ with $\\mathfrak{a}_{1} \\subsetneq \\mathfrak{a}_{2} \\subsetneq \\mathfrak{a}_{3}$. Continuing in this way, we find an infinite ascending chain of ideals of $R$. This contradicts $R$ being Noetherian, so every nonempty set of ideals contains a maximal element.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.2.3 (2) implies (3)}", "question": "For any commutative ring $R$ with identity, show that if every nonempty set of ideals contains a maximal element, then every ideal of $R$ is finitely generated.", "solution": "Let $\\mathfrak{b}$ be an ideal of $R$. Let $A$ be the set of ideals contained in $\\mathfrak{b}$ which are finitely generated. $A$ is nonempty, since $(0) \\in A$. Thus, $A$ has a maximal element, say $\\mathfrak{a}=(x_{1},...,x_{n})$. If $\\mathfrak{a} \\ne \\mathfrak{b}$, then $\\exists x \\in \\mathfrak{b}\\backslash\\mathfrak{a}$. But then $\\mathfrak{a}+(x)=(x_{1},x_{2},...,x_{n},x)$ is a larger finitely generated ideal contained in $\\mathfrak{b}$, contradicting the maximality of $\\mathfrak{a}$. Thus, $\\mathfrak{b}=\\mathfrak{a}$, so $\\mathfrak{b}$ is finitely generated.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.2.3 (3) implies (1)}", "question": "For any commutative ring $R$ with identity, show that if every ideal of $R$ is finitely generated, then $R$ is Noetherian.", "solution": "Let $\\mathfrak{a}_{1} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{a}_{2} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{a}_{3} \\subseteq \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot$ be an ascending chain of ideals of $R$. Then $\\mathfrak{a}=\\bigcup_{i=1}^{\\infty}\\mathfrak{a}_{i}$ is also an ideal of $R$, and so is finitely generated, say $\\mathfrak{a}=(x_{1},...,x_{n})$. Then $x_{1} \\in \\mathfrak{a}_{i_{1}},...,x_{n} \\in \\mathfrak{a}_{i_{n}}$. Let $m=\\max(i_{1},...,i_{n})$. Then $\\mathfrak{a} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{a}_{m}$, so $\\mathfrak{a}=\\mathfrak{a}_{m}$. Thus, $\\mathfrak{a}_{m}=\\mathfrak{a}_{m+1}=\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot$, and the chain does terminate. Thus, $R$ is Noetherian.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.2.4}", "question": "Show that any principal ideal domain is a Dedekind domain.", "solution": "Let $R$ be a principal ideal domain. $R$ is Noetherian since every ideal is finitely generated. $R$ is integrally closed since any principal ideal domain is a unique factorization domain, and so is integrally closed by Exercise 5.1.5. Let $(p) \\ne 0$ be a prime ideal and $(x) \\supseteq (p)$. Then, $p \\in (x)$, so $p=xy$, for some $y \\in R$. Thus, $xy \\in (p)$, so $x \\in (p)$ or $y \\in (p)$. If $x \\in (p)$, then $(x)=(p)$, and if $y \\in (p)$, then $y=pq$ for some $q \\in R$. This would imply that $p=xy=xqp$ and so $xq=1$ since $R$ is an integral domain. Thus, $(x)=R$. Therefore, $(p)$ is maximal. Thus, $R$ is a Dedekind domain.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.2.5}", "question": "Show that $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-5}]$ is a Dedekind domain, but not a principal ideal domain.", "solution": "$\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-5}]$ is not a unique factorization domain as was seen in Chapter 2 by taking $6=2\\times3=(1+\\sqrt{-5})(1-\\sqrt{-5})$, and so cannot be a principal ideal domain. To see that it is a Dedekind domain, it is enough to show that it is the set of algebraic integers of the algebraic number field $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-5})$. However, we have already proved this, in Exercise 4.1.3. So $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-5}]$ is a Dedekind domain.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.3.1}", "question": "Show that any fractional ideal is finitely generated as an $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-module.", "solution": "Let $\\mathcal{A}$ be a fractional ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Choose $m \\in \\mathbb{Z}$ such that $m\\mathcal{A} \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Since $\\mathcal{A}$ is an $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-module, $m\\mathcal{A}$ is an $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-module contained in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ and so is an ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Since $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ is Noetherian, $m\\mathcal{A}$ is finitely generated as an ideal. If $m\\mathcal{A}$ is generated as an ideal by $\\{a_{1},...,a_{n}\\}$, then $\\mathcal{A}$ is generated by $\\{m^{-1}a_{1},...,m^{-1}a_{n}\\}$ as an $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-module. Thus, $\\mathcal{A}$ is finitely generated as an $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-module.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.3.2}", "question": "Show that the sum and product of two fractional ideals are again fractional ideals.", "solution": "Let $\\mathcal{A}$ and $\\mathcal{B}$ be fractional ideals. Since $\\mathcal{A}$ and $\\mathcal{B}$ are both $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-modules, so are their sum and product. Let $m\\mathcal{A} \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{K}$, $n\\mathcal{B} \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{K}$ with $m, n \\in \\mathbb{Z}$. Then $mn(\\mathcal{AB})=(m\\mathcal{A})(n\\mathcal{B}) \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{K}$, so $\\mathcal{AB}$ is a fractional ideal. Also, $mn(\\mathcal{A}+\\mathcal{B})=n(m\\mathcal{A})+m(n\\mathcal{B}) \\subseteq n\\mathcal{O}_{K}+m\\mathcal{O}_{K} \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{K}$, so $\\mathcal{A}+\\mathcal{B}$ is a fractional ideal.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Lemma 5.3.3}", "question": "Show that any proper ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ contains a product of nonzero prime ideals.", "solution": "Let $S$ be the set of all proper ideals of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ that do not contain a product of prime ideals. We need to show that $S$ is empty. If not, then since $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ is Noetherian, $S$ has a maximal element, say $\\mathfrak{a}$. Then, $\\mathfrak{a}$ is not prime since $\\mathfrak{a} \\in S$ so there exist $a,b \\in \\mathcal{O}_{K}$, with $ab \\in \\mathfrak{a}$, $a \\notin \\mathfrak{a}$, $b \\notin \\mathfrak{a}$. Then, $(\\mathfrak{a},a) \\supseteq \\mathfrak{a}$ and $(\\mathfrak{a},b) \\supseteq \\mathfrak{a}$. Thus, $(\\mathfrak{a},a) \\notin S$, $(\\mathfrak{a},b) \\notin S$, by the maximality of $\\mathfrak{a}$. Thus, $(\\mathfrak{a},a) \\supseteq \\mathfrak{p}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r}$ and $(\\mathfrak{a},b) \\supseteq \\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{s}^{\\prime}$, with the $\\mathfrak{p}_{i}$ and $\\mathfrak{p}_{j}^{\\prime}$ nonzero prime ideals. But $ab \\in \\mathfrak{a}$, so $(\\mathfrak{a},ab)=\\mathfrak{a}$. Thus, $\\mathfrak{a}=(\\mathfrak{a},ab) \\supseteq (\\mathfrak{a},a)(\\mathfrak{a},b) \\supseteq \\mathfrak{p}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{s}^{\\prime}$. Therefore $\\mathfrak{a}$ contains a product of prime ideals. This contradicts $\\mathfrak{a}$ being in $S$, so $S$ must actually be empty.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Lemma 5.3.4}", "question": "Let $\\mathfrak{p}$ be a prime ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Show that there exists $z \\in K$, $z \\notin \\mathcal{O}_{K}$, such that $z\\mathfrak{p} \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "solution": "Take $x \\in \\mathfrak{p}$. From Lemma 5.3.3, $(x)=x\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ contains a product of prime ideals. Let $r$ be the least integer such that $(x)$ contains a product of $r$ prime ideals, and say $(x) \\supseteq \\mathfrak{p}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r}$ with the $\\mathfrak{p}_{i}$ nonzero prime ideals. Since $\\mathfrak{p} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{p}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r}$, $\\mathfrak{p} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{p}_{i}$, for some $i$, from Theorem 5.1.2 (d). Without loss of generality, we can assume that $i=1$, so $\\mathfrak{p} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{p}_{1}$. But $\\mathfrak{p}_{1}$ is a nonzero prime ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, and so is maximal. Thus, $\\mathfrak{p}=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}$. Now, $\\mathfrak{p}_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r} \\notin (x)$, since $r$ was chosen to be minimal. Choose an element $b \\in \\mathfrak{p}_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r}$, $b \\notin x\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Then $bx^{-1}\\mathfrak{p}=bx^{-1}\\mathfrak{p}_{1} \\subseteq (\\mathfrak{p}_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r})(x^{-1}\\mathfrak{p}_{1}) = x^{-1}(\\mathfrak{p}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r}) \\subseteq x^{-1}x\\mathcal{O}_{K} = \\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Let $z=bx^{-1}$. Then $z\\mathfrak{p} \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Now, if $z$ were in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, we would have $bx^{-1} \\in \\mathcal{O}_{K}$, and so $b \\in x\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. But this is not the case, so $z \\notin \\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.3.5}", "question": "Let $\\mathfrak{p}$ be a prime ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Show that $\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}$ is a fractional ideal and $\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "solution": "It is easily seen that $\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}$ is an $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-module. Now, $\\mathfrak{p} \\cap \\mathbb{Z} \\ne (0)$, so let $n \\in \\mathfrak{p} \\cap \\mathbb{Z}$, $n \\ne 0$. Then, $n\\mathfrak{p}^{-1} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}^{-1} \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{K}$, by definition. Thus, $\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}$ is a fractional ideal. It remains to show that $\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Since $1 \\in \\mathfrak{p}^{-1}$, $\\mathfrak{p} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}^{-1} \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{K}$. $\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}$ is an ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, since it is an $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-module contained in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. But $\\mathfrak{p}$ is maximal, so either $\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, in which case we are done, or $\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}=\\mathfrak{p}$. Suppose that $\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}=\\mathfrak{p}$. Then $x\\mathfrak{p} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{p}$ $\\forall x \\in \\mathfrak{p}^{-1}$. Since $\\mathfrak{p}$ is a finitely generated $\\mathbb{Z}$-module, $x \\in \\mathcal{O}_{K}$ for all $x \\in \\mathfrak{p}^{-1}$, by Theorem 5.1.6. Thus, $\\mathfrak{p}^{-1} \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{K}$. But $1 \\in \\mathfrak{p}^{-1}$, so $\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. From Lemma 5.3.4, we know this is not true, so $\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}^{-1} \\ne \\mathfrak{p}$. Thus, $\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.3.6}", "question": "Show that any ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ can be written as a product of prime ideals uniquely.", "solution": "**Existence.** Let $S$ be the set of ideals of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ that cannot be written as a product of prime ideals. If $S$ is nonempty, then $S$ has a maximal element, say $\\mathfrak{a}$, since $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ is Noetherian. Then $\\mathfrak{a} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{p}$ for some maximal ideal $\\mathfrak{p}$. Since $\\mathfrak{a} \\in S$, $\\mathfrak{a} \\ne \\mathfrak{p}$ and therefore $\\mathfrak{a}$ is not prime. Consider $\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}\\mathfrak{a}$. $\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}\\mathfrak{a} \\subset \\mathfrak{p}^{-1}\\mathfrak{p}=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Since $\\mathfrak{a} \\subsetneq \\mathfrak{p}$, $\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}\\mathfrak{a} \\subsetneq \\mathfrak{p}^{-1}\\mathfrak{p}=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, since for any $x \\in \\mathfrak{p} \\backslash \\mathfrak{a}$, $x\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}\\mathfrak{a} = \\mathcal{O}_{K}\\mathfrak{a} = \\mathfrak{a}$, which is not true. Thus, $\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}\\mathfrak{a}$ is a proper ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, and contains $\\mathfrak{a}$ properly since $\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}$ contains $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ properly. Thus, $\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}\\mathfrak{a} \\notin S$. Thus, $\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}\\mathfrak{a}=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r}$ for some prime ideals $\\mathfrak{p}_{i}$. Then, $\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}\\mathfrak{a}=\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r}$, so $\\mathfrak{a}=\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r}$. But then $\\mathfrak{a} \\notin S$, a contradiction. Thus, $S$ is empty.\n**Uniqueness.** Suppose that $\\mathfrak{a}=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r}=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{s}^{\\prime}$ are two factorizations of $\\mathfrak{a}$. Then, $\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{p}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r}$ so $\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{p}_{i}$, for some $i$, say $\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{p}_{1}$. $\\mathfrak{p}_{1}$ is maximal, so $\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime}=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}$. Thus, multiplying both sides by $(\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime})^{-1}$ and cancelling using $(\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime})^{-1}\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime}=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, we obtain $\\mathfrak{p}_{2}^{\\prime}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{s}^{\\prime}=\\mathfrak{p}_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r}$. Thus, continuing in this way, we see that $r=s$ and the primes are unique up to reordering.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.3.7}", "question": "Show that any fractional ideal $\\mathcal{A}$ can be written uniquely in the form $\\frac{\\mathfrak{p}_{1}...\\mathfrak{p}_{r}}{\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime}...\\mathfrak{p}_{s}^{\\prime}}$ where the $\\mathfrak{p}_{i}$ and $\\mathfrak{p}_{j}^{\\prime}$ may be repeated, but no $\\mathfrak{p}_{i}=\\mathfrak{p}_{j}^{\\prime}$.", "solution": "Choose a nonzero element $c \\in \\mathbb{Z}$ such that $\\mathfrak{b}:=c\\mathcal{A} \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Let $(c)=\\mathfrak{m}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{m}_{s}$, $\\mathfrak{b}=\\mathfrak{n}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{n}_{t}$, the $\\mathfrak{m}_{i}$, $\\mathfrak{n}_{j}$ prime. Then $(c)\\mathcal{A}=\\mathfrak{b}$, so $\\mathcal{A}=\\frac{\\mathfrak{n}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{n}_{t}}{\\mathfrak{m}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{m}_{s}}$ and cancelling the primes on the numerator that equal some prime on the denominator, we have that $\\mathfrak{m}_{i} \\ne \\mathfrak{n}_{j} \\forall i,j$. Also, if $\\mathcal{A}=\\frac{\\mathfrak{a}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{a}_{v}}{\\mathfrak{b}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{b}_{w}}$ with no $\\mathfrak{a}_{i}=\\mathfrak{b}_{j}$, then $\\mathfrak{a}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{a}_{v}\\mathfrak{m}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{m}_{s}=\\mathfrak{b}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{b}_{w}\\mathfrak{n}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{n}_{t}$. By unique factorization and the fact that no $\\mathfrak{b}_{i}$ is an $\\mathfrak{a}_{j}$ and no $\\mathfrak{m}_{i}$ is an $\\mathfrak{n}_{j}$, the $\\mathfrak{b}_{i}$ must coincide up to reordering with the $\\mathfrak{m}_{j}$'s and the $\\mathfrak{a}_{i}$ with the $\\mathfrak{n}_{j}$'s, and so the factorization is unique.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.3.8}", "question": "Show that, given any fractional ideal $\\mathcal{A} \\ne 0$ in $K$, there exists a fractional ideal $\\mathcal{A}^{-1}$ such that $\\mathcal{AA}^{-1}=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "solution": "Let $\\mathcal{A}=\\frac{\\mathfrak{p}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r}}{\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{s}^{\\prime}}.$ Then $\\mathcal{A}^{-1}=\\frac{\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{s}^{\\prime}}{\\mathfrak{p}_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r}}$ is a fractional ideal with $\\mathcal{AA}^{-1}=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.3.9}", "question": "Show that if $\\mathfrak{a}$ and $\\mathfrak{b}$ are ideals of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, then $\\mathfrak{b} | \\mathfrak{a}$ (where divisibility denotes $\\mathfrak{b} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{a}$) if and only if there is an ideal $\\mathfrak{c}$ of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ with $\\mathfrak{a}=\\mathfrak{bc}$.", "solution": "If $\\mathfrak{b} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{a}$, then $\\mathfrak{c}:=\\mathfrak{ab}^{-1} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{bb}^{-1}=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Thus, $\\mathfrak{a}=\\mathfrak{bc},$ with $\\mathfrak{c}$ an ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. If $\\mathfrak{a} = \\mathfrak{bc}$ with $\\mathfrak{c} \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{K}$, then $\\mathfrak{a}=\\mathfrak{bc} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{b}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.3.10}", "question": "Let $\\mathfrak{a}=\\prod_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}}$ and $\\mathfrak{b}=\\prod_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{f_{i}}$ with $e_i, f_i \\in \\mathbb{Z}_{\\ge 0}$. Show that $\\gcd(\\mathfrak{a},\\mathfrak{b})=\\mathfrak{a}+\\mathfrak{b}=\\prod_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{\\min(e_{i},f_{i})}$.", "solution": "$\\mathfrak{a} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{a}+\\mathfrak{b}$, $\\mathfrak{b} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{a}+\\mathfrak{b}$, so $\\mathfrak{a}+\\mathfrak{b}|\\mathfrak{a}, \\mathfrak{a}+\\mathfrak{b}|\\mathfrak{b}$. If $\\mathfrak{e}|\\mathfrak{a}$ and $\\mathfrak{e}|\\mathfrak{b}$ then $\\mathfrak{a} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{e}$, $\\mathfrak{b} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{e}$, so that $\\mathfrak{a}+\\mathfrak{b} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{e}$ i.e., $\\mathfrak{e} | \\mathfrak{a}+\\mathfrak{b}$. Therefore, $\\mathfrak{a}+\\mathfrak{b}=\\gcd(\\mathfrak{a},\\mathfrak{b})$. Let $\\mathfrak{d}=\\prod_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{\\min(e_{i},f_{i})}$, and let $\\min(e_{i},f_{i})=a_{i}$. $\\mathfrak{a}=\\prod_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}} = \\prod_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}-a_{i}}\\prod_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{a_{i}} = \\prod_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}-a_{i}}\\mathfrak{d},$ $e_{i}-a_{i} \\ge 0$ $\\forall i$. Thus, $\\mathfrak{d} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{a}$ which implies that $\\mathfrak{d}|\\mathfrak{a}$. Similarly, $\\mathfrak{d} | \\mathfrak{b}$. Suppose that $\\mathfrak{e}|\\mathfrak{a}$ and $\\mathfrak{e}|\\mathfrak{b}$. Let $\\mathfrak{c}=\\prod_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{k_{i}}$ ($k_{i} \\ge 0$) be the unique factorization of $\\mathfrak{e}$ as a product of prime ideals. Suppose $k_{i} > e_{i}$ for some $i \\in \\{1,...,r\\}$. We know that $\\mathfrak{e}|\\mathfrak{a}$ and so $\\mathfrak{a} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{e}$, i.e., $\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{k_{i}} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{e_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r}^{e_{r}}$. Thus, $\\mathfrak{p}_{i} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{p}_{j}$ for some $j \\ne i$ or $k_i \\le e_i$. Since $\\mathfrak{p}_i$ are distinct, we must have $k_{i} \\le e_{i}$ for all $i$. Similarly for $\\mathfrak{b}$, so $k_{i} \\le \\min(e_{i},f_{i})$. Thus, $\\mathfrak{e}|\\mathfrak{d}$ so $\\mathfrak{d}=\\gcd(\\mathfrak{a},\\mathfrak{b})$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.3.11}", "question": "Let $\\mathfrak{a}=\\prod_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}}$ and $\\mathfrak{b}=\\prod_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{f_{i}}$ with $e_i, f_i \\in \\mathbb{Z}_{\\ge 0}$. Show that $\\text{lcm}(\\mathfrak{a},\\mathfrak{b})=\\mathfrak{a}\\cap\\mathfrak{b}=\\prod_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{\\max(e_{i},f_{i})}$.", "solution": "$\\mathfrak{a} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{a}\\cap\\mathfrak{b}$, $\\mathfrak{b} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{a}\\cap\\mathfrak{b}$ so $\\mathfrak{a}|\\mathfrak{a}\\cap\\mathfrak{b}, \\mathfrak{b}|\\mathfrak{a}\\cap\\mathfrak{b}$. Suppose that $\\mathfrak{a}|\\mathfrak{e}$ and $\\mathfrak{b}|\\mathfrak{e}$. Then $\\mathfrak{e} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{a}$ and $\\mathfrak{e} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{b}$, so $\\mathfrak{e} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{a}\\cap\\mathfrak{b}$. Thus, $\\mathfrak{a}\\cap\\mathfrak{b}=\\text{lcm}(\\mathfrak{a},\\mathfrak{b})$. Let $\\mathfrak{m}=\\prod_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{\\max(e_{i},f_{i})}$ and let $\\mathfrak{c}=\\prod_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{k_{i}}\\prod_{j=1}^{s}(\\mathfrak{p}_{j}^{\\prime})^{t_{j}}$. Suppose $k_{i} < e_{i}$ for some $i$. $\\mathfrak{e} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{a} \\implies \\prod \\mathfrak{p}^{k} \\prod (\\mathfrak{p}')^t \\subseteq \\prod \\mathfrak{p}^e \\subseteq \\mathfrak{p}_i^{e_i} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{p}_i$. Thus $\\mathfrak{p}_i$ must contain some factor on the left. Since primes are distinct, this implies $k_i \\ge e_i$. Similarly $k_i \\ge f_i$. Thus $k_i \\ge \\max(e_i, f_i)$, so $\\mathfrak{m} | \\mathfrak{e}$. Thus $\\mathfrak{m}=\\text{lcm}(\\mathfrak{a},\\mathfrak{b})$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.3.12}", "question": "Suppose $\\mathfrak{a}, \\mathfrak{b}, \\mathfrak{c}$ are ideals of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Show that if $\\mathfrak{a}\\mathfrak{b}=\\mathfrak{c}^{g}$ and $\\gcd(\\mathfrak{a},\\mathfrak{b})=1$ then $\\mathfrak{a}=\\mathfrak{d}^{g}$ and $\\mathfrak{b}=\\mathfrak{e}^{g}$ for some ideals $\\mathfrak{d}$ and $\\mathfrak{e}$ of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "solution": "We factor uniquely into prime ideals: $\\mathfrak{a}=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{e_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r}^{e_{r}}$ and $\\mathfrak{b}=(\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime})^{f_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot(\\mathfrak{p}_{t}^{\\prime})^{f_{t}}$ where $\\mathfrak{p}_{1},...,\\mathfrak{p}_{r},\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime},...,\\mathfrak{p}_{t}^{\\prime}$ are distinct prime ideals since $\\gcd(\\mathfrak{a},\\mathfrak{b})=1.$ Now let $\\mathfrak{c}=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{a_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r}^{a_{r}}(\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime})^{b_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot(\\mathfrak{p}_{t}^{\\prime})^{b_{t}}$. Since $\\mathfrak{ab} = \\mathfrak{c}^{g}$ we must have $e_{i}=a_{i}g$ ($1\\le i\\le r$) and $f_{i}=b_{i}g$ ($1\\le i\\le t$) by unique factorization. Thus $\\mathfrak{a}=\\mathfrak{d}^{g}$ and $\\mathfrak{b}=\\mathfrak{e}^{g}$ with $\\mathfrak{d}=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{a_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r}^{a_{r}}$ and $\\mathfrak{e}=(\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime})^{b_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot(\\mathfrak{p}_{t}^{\\prime})^{b_{t}}$ as desired.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.3.13 (a)}", "question": "Let $\\mathfrak{a}, \\mathfrak{b}$ be ideals so that $\\gcd(\\mathfrak{a},\\mathfrak{b})=1$, i.e., $\\mathfrak{a}+\\mathfrak{b}=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Given $a, b \\in \\mathcal{O}_{K}$, show that we can solve $x \\equiv a \\pmod{\\mathfrak{a}}$, $x \\equiv b \\pmod{\\mathfrak{b}}$.", "solution": "Since $\\mathfrak{a}+\\mathfrak{b}=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, $\\exists x_{1} \\in \\mathfrak{a},$ $x_{2} \\in \\mathfrak{b}$ with $x_{1}+x_{2}=1$. Let $x=bx_{1}+ax_{2} \\equiv ax_{2} \\pmod{\\mathfrak{a}}$. But, $x_{2}=1-x_{1} \\equiv 1 \\pmod{\\mathfrak{a}}$. Thus, we have found an $x$ such that $x \\equiv a \\pmod{\\mathfrak{a}}$. Similarly, $x \\equiv b \\pmod{\\mathfrak{b}}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.3.13 (b)}", "question": "Let $\\mathfrak{p}_{1},...,\\mathfrak{p}_{r}$ be distinct prime ideals in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Given $a_{i} \\in \\mathcal{O}_{K}$, $e_{i} \\in \\mathbb{Z}_{>0}$, show that there exists $x$ such that $x \\equiv a_{i} \\pmod{\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}}}$ for all $i \\in \\{1,...,r\\}$.", "solution": "We proceed by induction on $r$. If $r=1$, there is nothing to show. Suppose $r>1$, and that we can solve $x \\equiv a_{i} \\pmod{\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}}}$ for $i=1,...,r-1$, say $a \\equiv a_{i} \\pmod{\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}}}$ for $i=1,...,r-1$. From part (a), we can solve $x \\equiv a \\pmod{\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{e_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r-1}^{e_{r-1}}}$ and $x \\equiv a_{r} \\pmod{\\mathfrak{p}_{r}^{e_{r}}}$. Then $x-a_{i} \\in \\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{e_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{r-1}^{e_{r-1}}$ and $x \\equiv a_{r} \\pmod{\\mathfrak{p}_{r}^{e_{r}}}$. Thus, $x-a_{i} \\in \\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}} \\forall i$, i.e., $x \\equiv a_{i} \\pmod{\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}}} \\forall i$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.3.14}", "question": "Show that $\\text{ord}_{\\mathfrak{p}}(\\mathfrak{ab})=\\text{ord}_{\\mathfrak{p}}(\\mathfrak{a})+\\text{ord}_{\\mathfrak{p}}(\\mathfrak{b})$ where $\\mathfrak{p}$ is a prime ideal.", "solution": "From a previous exercise, $\\mathfrak{a}=\\mathfrak{p}^{t}\\mathfrak{a}_{1}$ and $\\mathfrak{b}=\\mathfrak{p}^{s}\\mathfrak{b}_{1}$, where $\\mathfrak{p} \\nmid \\mathfrak{a}_{1}$, and $\\mathfrak{p} \\nmid \\mathfrak{b}_{1}$. Thus, $\\mathfrak{ab}=\\mathfrak{p}^{t+s}\\mathfrak{a}_{1}\\mathfrak{b}_{1}$, so $\\mathfrak{p}^{s+t} | \\mathfrak{ab}$. If $\\mathfrak{p}^{s+t+1} | \\mathfrak{ab}$, then $\\mathfrak{ab}=\\mathfrak{p}^{s+t+1}\\mathfrak{c}$, so $\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{c}=\\mathfrak{a}_{1}\\mathfrak{b}_{1}$. Thus, $\\mathfrak{p} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{a}_{1}\\mathfrak{b}_{1}$, so $\\mathfrak{p} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{a}_{1}$ or $\\mathfrak{p} \\supseteq \\mathfrak{b}_{1}$, since $\\mathfrak{p}$ is prime. This is a contradiction, so $\\text{ord}_{\\mathfrak{p}}(\\mathfrak{ab})=t+s=\\text{ord}_{\\mathfrak{p}}(\\mathfrak{a})+\\text{ord}_{\\mathfrak{p}}(\\mathfrak{b})$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.3.15}", "question": "Show that, for $\\alpha \\ne 0$ in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, $N((\\alpha))=|N_{K}(\\alpha)|$.", "solution": "Let $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{n}$. There exist $\\alpha_{i}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}p_{ij}\\omega_{j}$, with $p_{ii}>0$, $p_{ij} \\in \\mathbb{Z}$ such that $(\\alpha)=\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha_{n}$ and $N((\\alpha))=p_{11}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{nn},$ from Theorem 4.2.2. We also know that $(\\alpha)=\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha\\omega_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}\\alpha\\omega_{n}$. Now, $N_{K}(\\alpha)=\\det(c_{ij})$ where $\\alpha\\omega_{i}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}c_{ij}\\omega_{j}$. And, if $C=(c_{ij})$, $R=(r_{ij})$, $P=(p_{ij})$, then $(\\alpha\\omega_{1},...,\\alpha\\omega_{n})^{T}=C(\\omega_{1},...,\\omega_{n})^{T} = R(\\alpha_{1},...,\\alpha_{n})^{T} = RP(\\omega_{1},...,\\omega_{n})^{T}$ where $\\alpha\\omega_{i}=\\sum_{j=i}^{n}r_{ji}\\alpha_{j}$, $r_{ji} \\in \\mathbb{Z}$. Therefore, by definition, $N_{K}(\\alpha)=\\det(RP)=\\det(R)\\det(P)$. $R$ and $R^{-1}$ have integer entries, since $\\{\\alpha\\omega_{i}\\}$ and $\\{\\alpha_{i}\\}$ are both $\\mathbb{Z}$-bases for $(\\alpha)$. Thus, $\\det(R)=\\pm 1$. So, $\\det(C)=\\pm \\det(P)$, $\\det(P) \\ge 0$. Thus, $|\\det(C)|=\\det(P)$. Thus, $|N_{K}(\\alpha)|=|\\det(C)|=\\det(P)=N((\\alpha))$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.3.16 (a)}", "question": "If $\\mathfrak{a}=\\prod_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}}$ show that $N(\\mathfrak{a})=\\prod_{i=1}^{r}N(\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}}).$", "solution": "Consider the map $\\phi:\\mathcal{O}_{K}\\longrightarrow\\bigoplus_{i=1}^{r}(\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}})$ defined by $x \\longrightarrow (x_{1},...,x_{r})$ where $x_{i} \\equiv x \\pmod{\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}}}$. The function is surjective by the Chinese Remainder Theorem, and is a homomorphism since each of the $r$ components is a homomorphism. Next, we show by induction that $\\bigcap_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}}=\\prod_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}}$. The base case $r=1$ is trivial. Suppose $r>1$, and that the result is true for numbers smaller than $r$. $\\bigcap_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}} = \\text{lcm}(\\bigcap_{i=1}^{r-1}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}},\\mathfrak{p}_{r}^{e_{r}}) = \\text{lcm}(\\prod_{i=1}^{r-1}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}},\\mathfrak{p}_{r}^{e_{r}}) = \\prod_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}}.$ Thus, $\\ker(\\phi)=\\bigcap_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}}=\\prod_{i=1}^{r}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}}$, which implies that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{a} \\simeq \\oplus(\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}}).$ Hence, $N(\\mathfrak{a})=\\prod_{i=1}^{r}N(\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}})$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.3.16 (b)}", "question": "Show that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{p} \\simeq \\mathfrak{p}^{e-1}/\\mathfrak{p}^{e}$ and $N(\\mathfrak{p}^{e})=(N(\\mathfrak{p}))^{e}$ for any integer $e \\ge 0$.", "solution": "Since $\\mathfrak{p}^{e} \\subsetneq \\mathfrak{p}^{e-1}$, we can find an element $\\alpha \\in \\mathfrak{p}^{e-1}/\\mathfrak{p}^{e},$ so that $\\text{ord}_{\\mathfrak{p}}(\\alpha)=e-1$. Then $\\mathfrak{p}^{e} \\subseteq (\\alpha)+\\mathfrak{p}^{e} \\subseteq \\mathfrak{p}^{e-1}$. So $\\mathfrak{p}^{e-1}|(\\alpha)+\\mathfrak{p}^{e}$. But $(\\alpha)+\\mathfrak{p}^{e} \\ne \\mathfrak{p}^{e}$ so $\\mathfrak{p}^{e-1}=(\\alpha)+\\mathfrak{p}^{e},$ by unique factorization. Define the map $\\phi:\\mathcal{O}_{K}\\longrightarrow\\mathfrak{p}^{e-1}/\\mathfrak{p}^{e}$ by $\\phi(\\gamma)=\\gamma\\alpha+\\mathfrak{p}^{e}$. This is clearly a homomorphism and is surjective since $\\mathfrak{p}^{e-1}=(\\alpha)+\\mathfrak{p}^{e}$. Now, $\\gamma \\in \\ker(\\phi) \\iff \\gamma\\alpha \\in \\mathfrak{p}^{e} \\iff \\text{ord}_{\\mathfrak{p}}(\\gamma\\alpha) \\ge e \\iff \\text{ord}_{\\mathfrak{p}}(\\gamma)+\\text{ord}_{\\mathfrak{p}}(\\alpha) \\ge e \\iff \\text{ord}_{\\mathfrak{p}}(\\gamma)+e-1 \\ge e \\iff \\text{ord}_{\\mathfrak{p}}(\\gamma) \\ge 1 \\iff \\gamma \\in \\mathfrak{p}$. Thus, $\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{p} \\simeq \\mathfrak{p}^{e-1}/\\mathfrak{p}^{e}$. Also, $(\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{p}^{e})/(\\mathfrak{p}^{e-1}/\\mathfrak{p}^{e}) \\simeq \\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{p}^{e-1}$ since the map from $\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{p}^{e}$ to $\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{p}^{e-1}$ taking $x+\\mathfrak{p}^{e}$ to $x+\\mathfrak{p}^{e-1}$ is a surjective homomorphism with kernel $\\mathfrak{p}^{e-1}/\\mathfrak{p}^{e}$. Thus, $N(\\mathfrak{p}^{e})=|\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{p}^{e}|=|\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{p}^{e-1}| |\\mathfrak{p}^{e-1}/\\mathfrak{p}^{e}| = N(\\mathfrak{p}^{e-1})N(\\mathfrak{p}) = N(\\mathfrak{p})^{e-1}N(\\mathfrak{p}) = N(\\mathfrak{p})^{e}$ by the induction hypothesis.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.3.17}", "question": "If we write $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ as its prime factorization, $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{e_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{g}^{e_{g}}$, show that $N(\\mathfrak{p}_{i})$ is a power of $p$ and that if $N(\\mathfrak{p}_{i})=p^{f_{i}}$ then $\\sum_{i=1}^{g}e_{i}f_{i}=n$.", "solution": "Since $\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}}+\\mathfrak{p}_{j}^{e_{j}}=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ for $i \\ne j$, $\\mathcal{O}_{K}/p\\mathcal{O}_{K} \\simeq \\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{e_{1}} \\oplus \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot \\oplus \\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{p}_{g}^{e_{g}}$, by the Chinese Remainder Theorem. Therefore $p^{n}=N(\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{e_{1}})\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot N(\\mathfrak{p}_{g}^{e_{g}}) = N(\\mathfrak{p}_{1})^{e_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot N(\\mathfrak{p}_{g})^{e_{g}}$. Thus, $N(\\mathfrak{p}_{i})=p^{f_{i}}$ for some positive integer $f_{i},$ and $n=e_{1}f_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+e_{g}f_{g}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.4.1}", "question": "Let $\\mathcal{D}^{-1}=\\{x \\in K : \\text{Tr}(x\\mathcal{O}_{K}) \\subseteq \\mathbb{Z}\\}$. Show that $\\mathcal{D}^{-1}$ is a fractional ideal of $K$ and find an integral basis.", "solution": "$\\mathcal{D}^{-1}$ is an $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-module since if $x \\in \\mathcal{O}_{K}$ and $y \\in \\mathcal{D}^{-1}$, then $xy \\in \\mathcal{D}^{-1}$ because $\\text{Tr}(xy\\mathcal{O}_{K}) \\subseteq \\text{Tr}(y\\mathcal{O}_{K}) \\subseteq \\mathbb{Z}$. Thus, $\\mathcal{O}_{K}\\mathcal{D}^{-1} \\subseteq \\mathcal{D}^{-1}$. Now, let $\\{\\omega_{1},...,\\omega_{n}\\}$ be an integral basis of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. There is a dual basis $\\{\\omega_{1}^{*},...,\\omega_{n}^{*}\\}$ such that $\\text{Tr}(\\omega_{i}\\omega_{j}^{*})=\\delta_{ij}$, $1 \\le i, j \\le n$. Now $\\text{Tr}(\\omega_{i}^{*}\\omega_{j}) \\in \\mathbb{Z}$ for all $\\omega_{j}$, $\\omega_{i}^{*}$, so $\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{1}^{*}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{n}^{*} \\subseteq \\mathcal{D}^{-1}$. We claim that $\\mathcal{D}^{-1}=\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{1}^{*}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{n}^{*}$. Let $x \\in \\mathcal{D}^{-1}$. Then $x=\\sum_{i=1}^{n}a_{i}\\omega_{i}^{*},$ $a_{i} \\in \\mathbb{Q}$, $\\text{Tr}(x\\omega_{j})=\\text{Tr}(\\sum_{i=1}^{r}a_{i}\\omega_{i}^{*}\\omega_{j})=a_{j} \\in \\mathbb{Z}$ since $\\{\\omega_{1}^{*},...,\\omega_{n}^{*}\\}$ is a $\\mathbb{Q}$-basis for $K$. Therefore $x \\in \\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{1}^{*}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{n}^{*}$. Therefore $\\mathcal{D}^{-1}=\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{1}^{*}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}\\omega_{n}^{*}$. Since for each $\\omega_{i}^{*}$ there is an $a_{i} \\in \\mathbb{Z}$ such that $a_{i}\\omega_{i}^{*} \\in \\mathcal{O}_{K}$, if we let $m=\\prod_{i=1}^{n}a_{i},$ then $m\\mathcal{D}^{-1} \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Thus, $\\mathcal{D}^{-1}$ is a fractional ideal.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.4.2}", "question": "Let $\\mathcal{D}$ be the fractional ideal inverse of $\\mathcal{D}^{-1}$. We call $\\mathcal{D}$ the different of $K$. Show that $\\mathcal{D}$ is an ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "solution": "$\\mathcal{D}$ is certainly a fractional ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ and $\\mathcal{D}\\mathcal{D}^{-1}=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. But, from Lemma 4.1.1, $1 \\in \\mathcal{D}^{-1}$. Thus, $\\mathcal{D} \\subseteq \\mathcal{D}\\mathcal{D}^{-1}=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Thus, $\\mathcal{D}$ is an ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.4.3}", "question": "Let $\\mathcal{D}$ be the different of an algebraic number field $K$. Show that $N(\\mathcal{D})=|d_{K}|$.", "solution": "For some $m>0$, $m\\mathcal{D}^{-1}$ is an ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Now, $m\\mathcal{D}^{-1}=\\mathbb{Z}m\\omega_{1}^{*}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}m\\omega_{n}^{*}$. Let $m\\omega_{i}^{*}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}a_{ij}\\omega_{j},$ so $\\omega_{i}^{*}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}\\frac{a_{ij}}{m}\\omega_{j}$ and $\\omega_{i}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}b_{ij}\\omega_{j}^{*}$. Thus, $(b_{ij})$ is the matrix inverse of $(a_{ij}/m)$. But $\\text{Tr}(\\omega_{i}\\omega_{j})=\\text{Tr}(\\sum_{k=1}^{n}b_{ik}\\omega_{k}^{*}\\omega_{j}) = \\sum_{k=1}^{n}b_{ik}\\text{Tr}(\\omega_{k}^{*}\\omega_{j}) = b_{ij}$. Thus, $\\det(b_{ij})=d_{K}$. However, by Exercise 4.2.8, since $m\\mathcal{D}^{-1}$ is an ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ with integral basis $m\\omega_{1}^{*},...,m\\omega_{n}^{*}$ we know that $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(m\\omega_{1}^{*},...,m\\omega_{n}^{*})=N(m\\mathcal{D}^{-1})^{2}d_{K}$ and from Exercise 4.2.7 we have $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(m\\omega_{1}^{*},...,m\\omega_{n}^{*})=(\\det(a_{ij}))^{2}d_{K}$ which shows that $|\\det(a_{ij})|=N(m\\mathcal{D}^{-1})=m^{n}N(\\mathcal{D}^{-1})$, and thus $|\\det(\\frac{a_{ij}}{m})|=N(\\mathcal{D}^{-1})=N(\\mathcal{D})^{-1}$. Hence, $|d_{K}|=|\\det(b_{ij})|=|\\det(a_{ij}/m)|^{-1}=N(\\mathcal{D})$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.4.4}", "question": "Let $p \\in \\mathbb{Z}$ be prime, $\\mathfrak{p} \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{K}$ a prime ideal and $\\mathcal{D}$ the different of $K$. Show that if $\\mathfrak{p}^{e}|(p)$, then $\\mathfrak{p}^{e-1}|\\mathcal{D}$.", "solution": "We may assume that $e$ is the highest power of $\\mathfrak{p}$ dividing $(p)$. So let $(p)=\\mathfrak{p}^{e}\\mathfrak{a}$, $\\gcd(\\mathfrak{a},\\mathfrak{p})=1$. Let $x \\in \\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{a}$. Then $x=\\sum_{i=1}^{n}p_{i}a_{i}$ $p_{i} \\in \\mathfrak{p},$ $a_{i} \\in \\mathfrak{a}.$ Hence, $x^{p} \\equiv \\sum_{i=1}^{n}p_{i}^{p}a_{i}^{p} \\pmod p,$ and $x^{p^{m}} \\equiv \\sum_{i=1}^{n}p_{i}^{p^{m}}a_{i}^{p^{m}} \\pmod p.$ For sufficiently large $m$, $p_{i}^{p^{m}} \\in \\mathfrak{p}^{e}$, so $x^{p^{m}} \\in \\mathfrak{p}^{e}$ and thus, $x^{p^{m}} \\in \\mathfrak{p}^{e}\\mathfrak{a}=(p)$. Therefore, $\\text{Tr}(x^{p^{m}}) \\in p\\mathbb{Z},$ which implies that $(\\text{Tr}(x))^{p^{m}} \\in p\\mathbb{Z} \\Rightarrow \\text{Tr}(x) \\in p\\mathbb{Z} \\Rightarrow \\text{Tr}(p^{-1}\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{a}) \\subseteq \\mathbb{Z} \\Rightarrow p^{-1}\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{a} \\subseteq \\mathcal{D}^{-1} \\Rightarrow \\mathcal{D}p^{-1}\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{a} \\subseteq \\mathcal{D}\\mathcal{D}^{-1}=\\mathcal{O}_{K} \\Rightarrow \\mathcal{D} \\subseteq p\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}\\mathfrak{a}^{-1}=\\mathfrak{p}^{e}\\mathfrak{a}\\mathfrak{p}^{-1}\\mathfrak{a}^{-1}=\\mathfrak{p}^{e-1} \\Rightarrow \\mathfrak{p}^{e-1}|\\mathcal{D}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.4.5}", "question": "Show that if $p$ is ramified, $p|d_{K}$.", "solution": "Since $p$ is ramified, $e_{\\mathfrak{p}}>1$ for some prime ideal $\\mathfrak{p}$ containing $p$. Thus, $\\mathfrak{p}|\\mathcal{D}$ from the previous theorem, say $\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{a}=\\mathcal{D}.$ From the multiplicativity of the norm function, we have $N(\\mathfrak{p})N(\\mathfrak{a})=N(\\mathcal{D})$, so $N(\\mathfrak{p})|N(\\mathcal{D}).$ Thus, $p^{f_{\\mathfrak{p}}}|d_{K}$, and so $p|d_{K}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 5.5.1}", "question": "Suppose that there is a $\\theta \\in K$ such that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]$. Let $f(x)$ be the minimal polynomial of $\\theta$ over $\\mathbb{Z}[x]$. Let $p$ be a rational prime, and suppose $f(x) \\equiv f_{1}(x)^{e_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot f_{g}(x)^{e_{g}} \\pmod p$, where each $f_{i}(x)$ is irreducible in $\\mathbb{F}_{p}[x]$. Show that $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{e_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{g}^{e_{g}}$ where $\\mathfrak{p}_{i}=(p,f_{i}(\\theta))$ are prime ideals, with $N(\\mathfrak{p}_{i})=p^{\\deg f_{i}}$.", "solution": "We first note that $(p,f_{1}(\\theta))^{e_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot(p,f_{g}(\\theta))^{e_{g}} \\subseteq p\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Thus it suffices to show that $(p,f_{i}(\\theta))$ is a prime ideal of norm $p^{d_{i}}$ where $d_{i}$ is the degree of $f_{i}$. Now, since $f_{i}(x)$ is irreducible over $\\mathbb{F}_{p}$, then $\\mathbb{F}_{p}[x]/(f_{i}(x))$ is a field. Also, $\\mathbb{Z}[x]/(p) \\simeq \\mathbb{F}_{p}[x] \\Rightarrow \\mathbb{Z}[x]/(p, f_{i}(x)) \\simeq \\mathbb{F}_{p}[x]/(f_{i}(x)),$ and so $\\mathbb{Z}[x]/(p,f_{i}(x))$ is a field. Consider the map $\\varphi:\\mathbb{Z}[x]\\rightarrow\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]/(p,f_{i}(\\theta))$. Clearly $(p,f_{i}(x)) \\subseteq \\ker(\\varphi)=\\{n(x):n(\\theta) \\in (p,f_{i}(\\theta))\\}$. If $n(x) \\in \\ker(\\varphi)$, we can divide by $f_{i}(x)$ to get $n(x)=q(x)f_{i}(x)+r_{i}(x)$, $\\deg(r_{i})<\\deg(f_{i})$. We assume that $r_{i}$ is nonzero, for otherwise the result is trivial. Since $n(\\theta) \\in (p,f_{i}(\\theta))$, then $r_{i}(\\theta) \\in (p,f_{i}(\\theta))$ so $r_{i}(\\theta)=pa(\\theta)+f_{i}(\\theta)b(\\theta)$. Here we have used the fact that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]$. Now define the polynomial $h(x)=r_{i}(x)-pa(x)-f_{i}(x)b(x)$. Since $h(\\theta)=0$ and $f$ is the minimal polynomial of $\\theta$, then $h(x)=g(x)f(x)$ for some polynomial $g(x) \\in \\mathbb{Z}[x]$. We conclude that $r_{i}(x)=p\\tilde{a}(x)+f_{i}(x)\\tilde{b}(x)$ for some $\\tilde{a}(x),\\tilde{b}(x) \\in \\mathbb{Z}[x]$. Therefore $r_{i}(x) \\in (p,f_{i}(x))$. Thus, $\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]/(p,f_{i}(\\theta)) \\simeq \\mathbb{Z}[x]/(p,f_{i}(x)) \\simeq \\mathbb{F}_{p}[x]/(f_{i}(x))$ and is therefore a field. Hence, $(p,f_{i}(\\theta))$ is a maximal ideal and is therefore prime. Now, let $e_{i}^{\\prime}$ be the ramification index of $\\mathfrak{p}_{i}$, so that $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{e_{1}^{\\prime}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{g}^{e_{g}^{\\prime}}$ and let $d_{i}=[\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{p}_{i}:\\mathbb{Z}/p].$ Clearly $d_{i}$ is the degree of the polynomial $f_{i}(x).$ Since $f(\\theta)=0$ and since $f(x)-f_{1}(x)^{e_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot f_{g}(x)^{e_{g}} \\in p\\mathbb{Z}[x]$, it follows that $f_{1}(\\theta)^{e_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot f_{g}(\\theta)^{e_{g}} \\in p\\mathcal{O}_{K}=p\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]$. Also, $\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{e_{i}} \\subset p\\mathcal{O}_{K}+(f_{i}(\\theta)^{e_{i}})$ and so $\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{e_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{g}^{e_{g}} \\subseteq p\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{e_{1}^{\\prime}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{g}^{e_{g}^{\\prime}}$. Therefore, $e_{i} \\ge e_{i}^{\\prime}$ for all $i$. But $\\sum e_{i}d_{i}=\\deg f=[K:\\mathbb{Q}]=\\sum e_{i}^{\\prime}d_{i}$. Thus, $e_{i}=e_{i}^{\\prime}$ for all $i$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.5.2}", "question": "If in the previous theorem (Theorem 5.5.1) we do not assume that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]$ but instead that $p \\nmid [\\mathcal{O}_{K}:\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]]$, show that the same result holds.", "solution": "Let $m$ be the index of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]$ in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Then for $\\alpha \\in \\mathcal{O}_{K}$, $m\\alpha \\in \\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]$. In other words, given any $\\alpha$, we may write $m\\alpha=b_{0}+b_{1}\\theta+b_{2}\\theta^{2}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+b_{n-1}\\theta^{n-1}$. Consider this expression mod $p$. Since $m$ is coprime to $p$ there is an $m^{\\prime}$ such that $m^{\\prime}m \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$. Then $\\alpha \\equiv b_{0}m^{\\prime}+b_{1}m^{\\prime}\\theta+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+b_{n-1}m^{\\prime}\\theta^{n-1} \\pmod p.$ Thus, $\\mathcal{O}_{K} \\equiv \\mathbb{Z}[\\theta] \\pmod p$. In the proof of the previous exercise, we only used the fact that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]$ at one point. This was when we wrote that $r_{i}(\\theta)=pa(\\theta)+f_{i}(\\theta)b(\\theta)$. We now note that we simply need that $r_{i}(\\theta) \\equiv pa(\\theta)+f_{i}(\\theta)b(\\theta) \\pmod p$. The proof will follow through in the same way, and we deduce that $(p,f_{i}(\\theta))$ is a prime ideal of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]$. However, since $\\mathcal{O}_{K}/(p) \\simeq \\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]/(p)$, then $\\mathcal{O}_{K}/(p,f_{i}(\\theta)) \\simeq \\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]/(p,f_{i}(\\theta)).$ The rest of the proof will be identical to what was written above.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.5.3}", "question": "Suppose that $f(x)$ in the previous exercise (Theorem 5.5.1/Exercise 5.5.2) is Eisensteinian with respect to the prime $p$. Show that $p$ ramifies totally in $K$. That is, $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}=(\\mathfrak{p})^{n}$ where $n=[K:\\mathbb{Q}]$.", "solution": "By Example 4.3.1, we know that $p \\nmid [\\mathcal{O}_{K}:\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]]$. Moreover, $f(x) \\equiv x^{n} \\pmod p$. The result is now immediate from Exercise 5.5.2.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.5.4}", "question": "Show that $(p)=(1-\\zeta_{p})^{p-1}$ when $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{p})$.", "solution": "The minimal polynomial of $\\zeta_{p}$ is $\\Phi_{p}(x)$, the $p$th cyclotomic polynomial. Recall that $f(x)=\\Phi_{p}(x+1)$ is $p$-Eisensteinian, and that $\\zeta_{p}-1$ is a root. Since $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{p})=\\mathbb{Q}(1-\\zeta_{p}),$ and $\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{p}]=\\mathbb{Z}[1-\\zeta_{p}]$, the previous exercise tells us that $(p)=(1-\\zeta_{p})^{p-1}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.1}", "question": "Show that if a ring $R$ is a Dedekind domain and a unique factorization domain, then it is a principal ideal domain.", "solution": "Consider an arbitrary prime ideal $I$ of $R$. Since $R$ is a Dedekind domain, $I$ is finitely generated and we can write $I=(a_{1},...,a_{n})$ for some set of generators $a_{1},...,a_{n}$. In a unique factorization domain, every pair of elements has a gcd, and so $d=\\gcd(a_{1},...,a_{n})$ exists. Then $(d)=(a_{1},...,a_{n})=I$, thus proving that $R$ is a principal ideal domain.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.2}", "question": "Using Theorem 5.5.1, find a prime ideal factorization of $5\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ and $7\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ in $\\mathbb{Z}[(1+\\sqrt{-3})/2]$.", "solution": "We now consider $f(x)$ (mod 7). We have $x^{2}-x+1 \\equiv x^{2}+6x+1 \\equiv (x+2)(x+4) \\pmod 7$ so 7 splits and its factorization is $(7)=(7,\\frac{5+\\sqrt{-3}}{2})(7,\\frac{9+\\sqrt{-3}}{2})$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.3}", "question": "Find a prime ideal factorization of (2), (5), (11) in $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$.", "solution": "The minimal polynomial of $i$ is $x^{2}+1$. We consider it first mod 2. $x^{2}+1 \\equiv (x+1)^{2} \\pmod 2$, so $(2)=(2,i+1)^{2}=(i+1)^{2}$ since $2i=(i+1)^{2}$. $x^{2}+1 \\equiv x^{2}-4 \\equiv (x+2)(x-2) \\pmod 5$, so $(5)=(5,i+2)(5,i-2)=(i+2)(i-2)$ since $(2+i)(2-i)=5$. Finally, we consider $f(x) \\pmod{11}$. Since if the polynomial reduces it must have an integral root, we check all the possibilities mod 11 and deduce that it is in fact irreducible. Thus, 11 stays prime in $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.4}", "question": "Compute the different $\\mathcal{D}$ of $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-2})$.", "solution": "By Theorem 5.4.3, we know that $N(\\mathcal{D})=|d_{K}|=8$. Also, we showed in Chapter 2 that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-2}]$ is Euclidean and thus a principal ideal domain. Then $\\mathcal{D}=(a+b\\sqrt{-2})$ for some $a,b \\in \\mathbb{Z}$ and $N(\\mathcal{D})=a^{2}+2b^{2}=8$. The only solution in integers is $a=0$, $b=\\pm 2,$ so $\\mathcal{D}=(2\\sqrt{-2})=(-2\\sqrt{-2})$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.5}", "question": "Compute the different $\\mathcal{D}$ of $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-3})$.", "solution": "As in the previous exercise, we first observe that $N(\\mathcal{D})=|d_{K}|=3$ and since the integers of this ring are the Eisenstein integers, which form a Euclidean ring, $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$ is a principal ideal domain and $\\mathcal{D}=(a+b\\rho)$ for some $a,b \\in \\mathbb{Z}.$ We must find all solutions to the equation $N(\\mathcal{D})=3=a^{2}-ab+b^{2}.$ Since this is equivalent to $(2a-b)^{2}+3b^{2}=12$, we note that $|b|$ cannot be greater than 2. Checking all possibilities, we find all the elements of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$ of norm 3: $2+\\rho$, $-1+\\rho$, $-2-\\rho,$ $1-\\rho$, $1+2\\rho$ and $-1-2\\rho$. Some further checking reveals that these six elements are all associates, and so they each generate the same principal ideal. Thus, $\\mathcal{D}=(2+\\rho)$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.6}", "question": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\alpha)$ be an algebraic number field of degree $n$ over $\\mathbb{Q}$. Suppose $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\alpha]$ and that $f(x)$ is the minimal polynomial of $\\alpha$. Write $f(x)=(x-\\alpha)(b_{0}+b_{1}x+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+b_{n-1}x^{n-1})$, $b_{i} \\in \\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Prove that the dual basis to $1,\\alpha,...,\\alpha^{n-1}$ is $\\frac{b_{0}}{f^{\\prime}(\\alpha)},...,\\frac{b_{n-1}}{f^{\\prime}(\\alpha)}$ and deduce that $\\mathcal{D}^{-1}=\\frac{1}{f^{\\prime}(\\alpha)}(\\mathbb{Z}b_{0}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}b_{n-1}).$", "solution": "Let $\\alpha_{1}=\\alpha,\\alpha_{2},...,\\alpha_{n}$ be the $n$ distinct roots of $f(x)$. We would like to show that $\\sum_{i=1}^{n}\\frac{f(x)}{x-\\alpha_{i}}\\cdot\\frac{\\alpha_{i}^{r}}{f^{\\prime}(\\alpha_{i})}=x^{r}$ for $0 \\le r \\le n-1$. Define the polynomial $g_{r}(x)=\\sum_{i=1}^{n}\\frac{f(x)}{x-\\alpha_{i}}\\cdot\\frac{\\alpha_{i}^{r}}{f^{\\prime}(\\alpha_{i})}-x^{r}.$ Consider $g_{r}(\\alpha_{1})$. Note that $f(\\alpha_{1})/(\\alpha_{1}-\\alpha_{i})=0$ for all $i$ except $i=1.$ Also, $(\\frac{f(x)}{x-\\alpha_{1}})_{x=\\alpha_{1}}=f^{\\prime}(\\alpha_{1}).$ Thus, $g_{r}(\\alpha_{1})=0$, and similarly, $g_{r}(\\alpha_{i})=0$ for $1 \\le i \\le n$. Since $\\deg(g_{r}(x)) \\le n-1$, it can have at most $n-1$ roots. As we found $n$ distinct roots, $g_{r}(x)$ must be identically zero. For a polynomial $h(x)=c_{0}+c_{1}x+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+c_{m}x^{m} \\in K[x]$ we define the trace of $h(x)$ to be $\\text{Tr}(h(x))=\\sum_{i=0}^{m}\\text{Tr}(c_{i})x^{i} \\in \\mathbb{Q}[x].$ Since $\\alpha_{1},...,\\alpha_{n}$ are all the conjugates of $\\alpha$, it is clear that $\\text{Tr}(\\frac{f(x)\\alpha^{r}}{(x-\\alpha)f^{\\prime}(\\alpha)})=\\sum_{i=1}^{n}\\frac{f(x)\\alpha_{i}^{r}}{(x-\\alpha_{i})f^{\\prime}(\\alpha_{i})}=x^{r}.$ But, $\\text{Tr}(\\frac{f(x)\\alpha^{r}}{(x-\\alpha)f^{\\prime}(\\alpha)})=\\sum_{i=0}^{n-1}\\text{Tr}(\\frac{b_{i}\\alpha^{r}}{f^{\\prime}(\\alpha)})x^{i}=x^{r}.$ Thus, $\\text{Tr}(\\frac{b_{i}\\alpha^{r}}{f^{\\prime}(\\alpha)})=0$ unless $i=r$ in which case the trace is 1. Recall that if $\\omega_{1},...,\\omega_{n}$ is a basis, its dual basis $\\omega_{1}^{*},...,\\omega_{n}^{*}$ is characterized by $\\text{Tr}(\\omega_{i}\\omega_{j}^{*})=\\delta_{ij},$ the Kronecker delta function. Thus, we have found a dual basis to $1,\\alpha,...,\\alpha^{n-1}$ and it is $\\frac{b_{0}}{f^{\\prime}(\\alpha)},...,\\frac{b_{n-1}}{f^{\\prime}(\\alpha)}.$ By Exercise 5.4.1, $\\mathcal{D}^{-1}=\\frac{1}{f^{\\prime}(\\alpha)}(\\mathbb{Z}b_{0}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}b_{n-1}).$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.7}", "question": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\alpha)$ be of degree $n$ over $\\mathbb{Q}$. Suppose that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\alpha].$ Prove that $\\mathcal{D}=(f^{\\prime}(\\alpha))$.", "solution": "Let $f(x)$ be the minimal polynomial of $\\alpha$, and let $f(x)=(x-\\alpha)(b_{0}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+b_{n-1}x^{n-1})$. Since $f(x)$ is monic, $b_{n-1}=1.$ Also, $a_{n-1}=b_{n-2}-\\alpha b_{n-1}$ which means that $b_{n-2}=a_{n-1}+\\alpha$, where $a_{n-1}$ is an integer. We know from the previous exercise that $\\mathcal{D}^{-1}=\\frac{1}{f^{\\prime}(\\alpha)}(\\mathbb{Z}b_{0}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}b_{n-1}).$ Since $b_{n-1}=1,\\mathbb{Z} \\subseteq \\mathbb{Z}b_{0}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}b_{n-1}$. Since $b_{n-2}=a_{n-1}+\\alpha,$ we can deduce that $\\alpha \\in \\mathbb{Z}b_{0}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}b_{n-1}$ and by considering the expressions for $a_{i}$, $0 \\le i \\le n$, we see that in fact $\\alpha^{i} \\in \\mathbb{Z}b_{0}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}b_{n-1}$ for $1 \\le i \\le n-1.$ Thus, $\\mathbb{Z}[\\alpha] \\subseteq \\mathbb{Z}b_{0}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}b_{n-1} \\subseteq \\mathbb{Z}[\\alpha]$ and so we have equality. Thus, $\\mathcal{D}^{-1}=\\frac{1}{f^{\\prime}(\\alpha)}\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ and so $\\mathcal{D}=(f^{\\prime}(\\alpha))$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.8}", "question": "Compute the different $\\mathcal{D}$ of $\\mathbb{Q}[\\zeta_{p}]$ where $\\zeta_{p}$ is a primitive $p$th root of unity.", "solution": "We can apply the results of the previous exercise to get $\\mathcal{D}=(f^{\\prime}(\\zeta_{p}))$. $f(x)=\\frac{x^{p}-1}{x-1}=x^{p-1}+x^{p-2}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+x+1,$ $f^{\\prime}(x)=\\frac{px^{p-1}(x-1)-(x^{p}-1)}{(x-1)^{2}},$ $f^{\\prime}(\\zeta_{p})=\\frac{p\\zeta_{p}^{-1}}{\\zeta_{p}-1}$. Since $\\zeta_{p}^{-1}$ is a unit, we find $\\mathcal{D}=(\\frac{p}{\\zeta_{p}-1})$. From Exercise 5.5.4 we know that $(p)=(1-\\zeta_{p})^{p-1}$, and so $\\mathcal{D}=(1-\\zeta_{p})^{p-2}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.9}", "question": "Let $p$ be a prime, $p \\nmid m$, and $a \\in \\mathbb{Z}$. Show that $p|\\phi_{m}(a)$ if and only if the order of $a \\pmod p$ is $m$. (Here $\\phi_{m}(x)$ is the $m$th cyclotomic polynomial.)", "solution": "Since $x^{m}-1=\\prod_{d|m}\\phi_{d}(x)$, we have $a^{m} \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$. Let $k$ be the order of $a \\pmod p$. Then $k|m$. If $k<m$, then $a^{k}-1=\\prod_{d|k}\\phi_{d}(a) \\equiv 0 \\pmod p$ so that $\\phi_{d}(a) \\equiv 0 \\pmod p$ for some $d|k$. Then $a^{m}-1=\\phi_{m}(a)\\phi_{d}(a)(\\text{other factors}) \\equiv 0 \\pmod{p^{2}}$. Since $\\phi_{m}(a+p) \\equiv \\phi_{m}(a) \\pmod p$ and similarly for $\\phi_{d}(a)$, we also have $(a+p)^{m} \\equiv 1 \\pmod{p^{2}}$. But then $(a+p)^{m}=a^{m}+ma^{m-1}p \\pmod{p^{2}}$ so that $ma^{m-1} \\equiv 0 \\pmod p$, a contradiction. Conversely, suppose that $a$ has order $m$ so that $a^{m} \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$. Then $\\phi_{d}(a) \\equiv 0 \\pmod p$ for some $d|m$. If $d<m,$ then the order of $a \\pmod p$ would be less than $m$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.10}", "question": "Suppose $p \\nmid m$ is prime. Show that $p|\\phi_{m}(a)$ for some $a \\in \\mathbb{Z}$ if and only if $p \\equiv 1 \\pmod m$. Deduce from Exercise 1.2.5 that there are infinitely many primes congruent to 1 (mod m).", "solution": "If $p|\\phi_{m}(a)$, by the previous exercise the order of $a \\pmod p$ is $m$ so that $m|p-1$. Conversely, if $p \\equiv 1 \\pmod m$, there is an element $a$ of order $m \\pmod p$ because $(\\mathbb{Z}/p\\mathbb{Z})^{*}$ is cyclic. Again by the previous exercise $p|\\phi_{m}(a)$. If there are only finitely many primes $p_{1},...,p_{r}$ (say) that are congruent to 1 (mod m), then setting $a=(p_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{r})m$ we examine the prime divisors of $\\phi_{m}(a)$. Observe that the identity $x^{m}-1=\\prod_{d|m}\\phi_{d}(x)$ implies that $\\phi_{m}(0)=\\pm 1$. Thus, the constant term of $\\phi_{m}(x)$ is $\\pm 1$ so that $\\phi_{m}(a)$ is coprime to $a$ and hence coprime to $m$. (If $\\phi_{m}(a)=\\pm 1$ one can replace $a$ by any suitable power of $a$, so that $|\\phi_{m}(a)|>1.$) By what we have proved, any prime divisor $p$ of $\\phi_{m}(a)$ coprime to $m$ must be congruent to 1 (mod m). The prime $p$ is distinct from $p_{1},...,p_{r}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.11}", "question": "Show that $p \\nmid m$ splits completely in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m})$ if and only if $p \\equiv 1 \\pmod m$.", "solution": "Observe that $\\phi_{m}(x)$ has a root mod $p$ if and only if $p \\equiv 1 \\pmod m$ by the previous exercise. But then if it has one root $a$ it has $\\varphi(m)$ roots because $m|(p-1)$ and so $(\\mathbb{Z}/p\\mathbb{Z})^{*}$ has a cyclic subgroup of order $m$. Thus, $\\phi_{m}(x)$ splits completely if and only if $p \\equiv 1 \\pmod m$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.12}", "question": "Let $p$ be prime and let $a$ be squarefree and coprime to $p$. Set $\\theta=a^{1/p}$ and consider $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$. Show that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]$ if and only if $a^{p-1} \\not\\equiv 1 \\pmod{p^{2}}$.", "solution": "Assume that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]$. We will show that $a^{p-1} \\not\\equiv 1 \\pmod{p^{2}}.$ By Theorem 5.5.1, $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathfrak{p}^{p}$ since $\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$ has degree $p$ over $\\mathbb{Q}$. Moreover, $\\mathfrak{p}=(p,\\theta-a)$. Also, $(\\theta-a) \\in \\mathfrak{p}$ and $(\\theta-a) \\notin \\mathfrak{p}^{2}$ so that $(\\theta-a)=\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{a}$ for some ideal $\\mathfrak{a}$. Taking norms, we find $|N(\\theta-a)|=pN\\mathfrak{a}$ and $(N\\mathfrak{a},p)=1$. $(\\theta-a)$ is a root of $(x+a)^{p}-a$ and this polynomial is irreducible since $\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta-a)=\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$ has degree $p$ over $\\mathbb{Q}$. Hence $N(\\theta-a)=a^{p}-a=pN\\mathfrak{a}$ so that $a^{p} \\not\\equiv a \\pmod{p^{2}}$. Conversely, suppose that $a^{p} \\not\\equiv a \\pmod{p^{2}}$. Then the polynomial $(x+a)^{p}-a$ is Eisenstein with respect to the prime $p$. Therefore $p \\nmid [\\mathcal{O}_{K}:\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta-a]]$ by Example 4.3.1. But $\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta-a]=\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]$ so we deduce that $p \\nmid [\\mathcal{O}_{K}:\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]]$. In addition, $x^{p}-a$ is Eisenstein with respect to every prime divisor of $a$. Again, by Example 4.3.1, we deduce that $[\\mathcal{O}_{K}:\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]]$ is coprime to $a$. By Exercises 4.3.3 and 4.2.8, $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\theta)=(-1)^{\\binom{p}{2}}p^{p}a^{p-1}=[\\mathcal{O}_{K}:\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]]^{2}\\cdot d_{K}$. Since the index of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]$ in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ is coprime to both $p$ and $a$, it must equal 1. Thus $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.13}", "question": "Suppose that $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$ and $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]$. Show that if $p|d_{K}$, $p$ ramifies.", "solution": "We will use the result of Theorem 5.5.1. Let $f(x)$ be the minimal polynomial of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]$. Suppose that $p|d_{K}$ and $f(x) \\equiv f_{1}(x)^{e_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot f_{g}(x)^{e_{g}} \\pmod p$. Since $p|d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\theta)=\\prod(\\theta_{i}-\\theta_{j})^{2}$, then $\\theta_{i} \\equiv \\theta_{j}$ in $\\overline{\\mathbb{F}}_{p}$ for some $i \\ne j$. Thus, $f$ has multiple roots in $\\overline{\\mathbb{F}}_{p}$. Hence, one of the $e_{i}$ is greater than 1.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.14}", "question": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$ and suppose that $p|d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\theta)$, $p^{2} \\nmid d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\theta).$ Show that $p|d_{K}$ and $p$ ramifies in $K$.", "solution": "Recall that $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\theta)=m^{2}d_{K}$ where $m=[\\mathcal{O}_{K}:\\mathbb{Z}[\\theta]]$. Clearly, since $p|d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\theta)$ but $p^{2} \\nmid d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\theta), p|d_{K}$, and $p \\nmid m$. We can now apply the result of Exercise 5.5.2. Using the same argument as in 5.6.13, we deduce that $f(x)$ has a multiple root mod $p$ and so $p$ ramifies in $K$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.15}", "question": "Let $K$ be an algebraic number field of discriminant $d_{K}.$ Show that the normal closure of $K$ contains a quadratic field of the form $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d_{K}})$.", "solution": "Let $\\tilde{K}$ be the normal closure of $K$, $\\omega_{1},...,\\omega_{n}$ an integral basis of $K, \\sigma_{1},...,\\sigma_{n}$ the distinct embeddings of $K$ into $\\mathbb{C}$. Then $d_{K}=\\det(\\sigma_{i}(\\omega_{j}))^{2} \\in \\mathbb{Z}.$ Thus $\\sqrt{d_{K}}=\\det(\\sigma_{i}(\\omega_{j})) \\in \\tilde{K}.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.16}", "question": "Show that if $p$ ramifies in $K$, then it ramifies in each of the conjugate fields of $K$. Deduce that if $p$ ramifies in the normal closure of $K$, then it ramifies in $K$.", "solution": "Since each embedding $\\sigma_{i}:K\\rightarrow K^{(i)}$ is an isomorphism of fields, any factorization of $(p)=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{e_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{g}^{e_{g}}$ takes each prime ideal $\\mathfrak{p}_{j}$ into a conjugate prime ideal $\\mathfrak{p}_{j}^{(i)}.$ If some $e_{j}>1$ then in each conjugate field, $p$ ramifies. The second part is straightforward upon intersecting with $K$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.17}", "question": "Deduce the following special case of Dedekind's theorem: if $p^{2m+1}||d_{K}$ show that $p$ ramifies in $K$.", "solution": "By the penultimate exercise, $p$ ramifies in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d_{K}})$ and hence in the normal closure. By the previous exercise, $p$ ramifies in $K$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.18}", "question": "Determine the prime ideal factorization of (7), (29), and (31) in $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt[3]{2})$.", "solution": "By Example 4.3.6, $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[2^{1/3}]$. We may apply Theorem 5.5.1. Since $x^{3}-2$ is irreducible mod 7, $7\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ is prime in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Since $x^{3}-2 \\equiv (x+3)(x^{2}-3x+9) \\pmod{29}$ and the quadratic factor is irreducible, we get $29\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}\\mathfrak{p}_{2}$ where $\\deg \\mathfrak{p}_{1}=1$, $\\deg \\mathfrak{p}_{2}=2$ and $\\mathfrak{p}_{1}$, $\\mathfrak{p}_{2}$ are prime ideals. Finally, $x^{3}-2 \\equiv (x-4)(x-7)(x+11) \\pmod{31}$ so that $31\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ splits completely in $K$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.19}", "question": "If $L/K$ is a finite extension of algebraic number field, we can view $L$ as a finite dimensional vector space over $K$. If $\\alpha \\in L$, the map $v \\mapsto \\alpha v$ is a linear mapping and one can define, as before, the relative norm $N_{L/K}(\\alpha)$ and relative trace $\\text{Tr}_{L/K}(\\alpha)$ as the determinant and trace, respectively, of this linear map. If $\\alpha \\in \\mathcal{O}_{L}$ show that $\\text{Tr}_{L/K}(\\alpha)$ and $N_{L/K}(\\alpha)$ lie in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$.", "solution": "By taking a basis $\\omega_{1},...,\\omega_{n}$ of $L$ over $K$ and repeating the argument of Lemma 4.1.1, the result follows immediately.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.20}", "question": "If $K \\subseteq L \\subseteq M$ are finite extensions of algebraic number fields, show that $N_{M/K}(\\alpha)=N_{L/K}(N_{M/L}(\\alpha))$ and $\\text{Tr}_{M/K}(\\alpha)=\\text{Tr}_{L/K}(\\text{Tr}_{M/L}(\\alpha))$ for any $\\alpha \\in M.$", "solution": "Fix an algebraic closure $\\overline{M}$ of $M$. Let $\\sigma_{1},...,\\sigma_{m}$ be the distinct embeddings of $L$ into $\\overline{M}$ which are equal to the identity on $K$. By field theory, we can extend these to embeddings of $M$ into $\\overline{M}.$ Of these, let $\\eta_{1},...,\\eta_{n}$ be the ones trivial on $L$. If $\\sigma$ is an arbitrary embedding of $M$ into $\\overline{M}$ which is trivial on $K$, then as $\\sigma$ is also an embedding of $L$ into $\\overline{M},$ it must be $\\sigma_{j}$ for some $j$. Thus, $\\sigma_{j}^{-1}\\sigma$ fixes $L$ and so must be an $\\eta_{i}$ for some $i$. Thus, every embedding of $M$ is of the form $\\sigma_{j}\\circ\\eta_{i}$ so that $N_{M/K}(\\alpha)=\\prod_{i,j}\\sigma_{j}(\\eta_{i}(\\alpha))=\\prod_{j}\\sigma_{j}(N_{M/L}(\\alpha))=N_{L/K}(N_{M/L}(\\alpha))$, as desired.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.21}", "question": "Let $L/K$ be a finite extension of algebraic number fields. Show that the map $\\text{Tr}_{L/K}:L\\times L\\rightarrow K$ is non-degenerate.", "solution": "This follows from an argument analogous to the proof of Lemma 4.1.4.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.22}", "question": "Let $L/K$ be a finite extension of algebraic number fields. Let $\\mathfrak{a}$ be a finitely generated $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-module contained in $L$. The set $\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}^{-1}(\\mathfrak{a})=\\{x \\in L:\\text{Tr}_{L/K}(x\\mathfrak{a}) \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{K}\\}$ is called codifferent of $\\mathfrak{a}$ over $K$. If $\\mathfrak{a} \\ne 0$ show that $\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}^{-1}(\\mathfrak{a})$ is a finitely generated $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-module. Thus, it is a fractional ideal of $L$.", "solution": "The fact that $\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}^{-1}(\\mathfrak{a})$ is an $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-module is clear. To see that it is finitely generated, we take an $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$-basis of $\\mathfrak{a}$ and repeat the argument in Exercise 5.4.1 to deduce the result.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.23}", "question": "If in the previous exercise $\\mathfrak{a}$ is an ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{L}$, show that the fractional ideal inverse, denoted $\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}(\\mathfrak{a})$ of $\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}^{-1}(\\mathfrak{a})$ is an integral ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{L}$. (We call $\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}(\\mathfrak{a})$ the different of $\\mathfrak{a}$ over $K$. In the case $\\mathfrak{a}$ is $\\mathcal{O}_{L}$, we call it the relative different of $L/K$ and denote it by $\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}$.)", "solution": "We have $\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}(\\mathfrak{a})\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}^{-1}(\\mathfrak{a})=\\mathcal{O}_{L}$ and $1 \\in \\mathcal{D}_{L/K}^{-1}(\\mathfrak{a})$ so that $\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}(\\mathfrak{a}) \\subseteq \\mathcal{D}_{L/K}(\\mathfrak{a})\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}^{-1}(\\mathfrak{a}) \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{L}$ so that $\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}(\\mathfrak{a})$ is an integral ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{L}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.24}", "question": "Let $K \\subseteq L \\subseteq M$ be algebraic number fields of finite degree over the rationals. Show that $\\mathcal{D}_{M/K}=\\mathcal{D}_{M/L}(\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}\\mathcal{O}_{M}).$", "solution": "We have $x \\in \\mathcal{D}_{M/L}^{-1}$ if and only if $\\text{Tr}_{M/L}(x\\mathcal{O}_{M}) \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{L}$ which is equivalent to $\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}^{-1}\\text{Tr}_{M/L}(x\\mathcal{O}_{M}) \\subseteq \\mathcal{D}_{L/K}^{-1}\\mathcal{O}_{L}$ iff $\\text{Tr}_{L/K}(\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}^{-1}\\text{Tr}_{M/L}(x\\mathcal{O}_{M})) \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{K}$ which by transitivity of the trace is equivalent to $\\text{Tr}_{M/K}(x\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}^{-1}) \\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{K}$. That is, we must have $x\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}^{-1} \\subseteq \\mathcal{D}_{M/K}^{-1}$ which is true if and only if $x \\in \\mathcal{D}_{L/K}\\mathcal{D}_{M/K}^{-1}$ which means $\\mathcal{D}_{M/L}^{-1}=\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}\\mathcal{D}_{M/K}^{-1}$ which gives the required result.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.25}", "question": "Let $L/K$ be a finite extension of algebraic number fields. We define the relative discriminant of $L/K$, denoted $d_{L/K}$, as $N_{L/K}(\\mathcal{D}_{L/K})$. This is an integral ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. If $K \\subseteq L \\subseteq M$ are as in Exercise 5.6.24, show that $d_{M/K}=d_{L/K}^{[M:L]}N_{L/K}(d_{M/L})$.", "solution": "By the transitivity of the norm map and by Exercise 5.6.24, we have $N_{M/K}(\\mathcal{D}_{M/K})=N_{M/K}(\\mathcal{D}_{M/L}\\mathcal{D}_{L/K})=N_{L/K}(N_{M/L}(\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}\\mathcal{D}_{M/L}))=N_{L/K}(\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}^{[M:L]}N_{M/L}(\\mathcal{D}_{M/L}))$ which gives the result.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.26}", "question": "Let $L/K$ be a finite extension of algebraic number fields. Suppose that $\\mathcal{O}_{L}=\\mathcal{O}_{K}[\\alpha]$ for some $\\alpha \\in L.$ If $f(x)$ is the minimal polynomial of $\\alpha$ over $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, show that $\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}=(f^{\\prime}(\\alpha)).$", "solution": "This result is identical to Exercises 5.6.6 and 5.6.7.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.27}", "question": "Let $K_{1}$, $K_{2}$ be algebraic number fields of finite degree over $K$. If $L/K$ is the compositum of $K_{1}/K$ and $K_{2}/K,$ show that the set of prime ideals dividing $d_{L/K}$ and $d_{K_{1}/K}d_{K_{2}/K}$ are the same.", "solution": "By Exercise 5.6.25, we see that every prime ideal dividing $d_{K_{1}/K}d_{K_{2}/K}$ also divides $d_{L/K}$. Suppose now that $\\mathfrak{p}$ is a prime ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ which divides $d_{L/K}$ but not $d_{K_{1}/K}$. We have to show that $\\mathfrak{p}$ divides $d_{K_{2}/K}$. By the definition of the relative discriminant, there is a prime ideal of $\\mathcal{O}_{L}$ lying above $\\mathfrak{p}$ which divides the different $\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}$. This ideal cannot divide $\\mathcal{D}_{K_{1}/K}\\mathcal{O}_{L}$ for this would imply that $\\mathfrak{p}$ divides $d_{K_{1}/K}$, contrary to assumption. Since $\\mathcal{D}_{L/K}=\\mathcal{D}_{L/K_{1}}\\mathcal{D}_{K_{1}/K}$ we deduce that divides $\\mathcal{D}_{L/K_{1}}$. Now let $\\alpha \\in \\mathcal{O}_{K_{2}}$ so that $\\alpha$ generates $K_{2}$ over $K$. Let $f(x)$ be its minimal polynomial over $K_{1}$ and $g(x)$ its minimal polynomial over $K$. (We have assumed that we have fixed a common algebraic closure which contains $K_{1}$ and $K_{2}$) Then $L=K_{1}(\\alpha)$ and $g(x)=f(x)h(x)$ for some polynomial $h$ over $K_{1}$. Hence, $g^{\\prime}(x)=f^{\\prime}(x)h(x)+f(x)h^{\\prime}(x)$ which implies $g^{\\prime}(\\alpha)=f^{\\prime}(\\alpha)h(\\alpha)$. Thus, $g^{\\prime}(\\alpha)$ is in the ideal generated by $f^{\\prime}(\\alpha)$. By the remark in the solution of Exercise 5.6.26, we deduce that $f^{\\prime}(\\alpha) \\in \\mathcal{D}_{L/K} \\subseteq \\mathcal{P}$. Therefore, $g^{\\prime}(\\alpha) \\in \\mathcal{P}$. The same remark enables us to deduce that $g^{\\prime}(\\alpha) \\in \\mathcal{D}_{K_{2}/K}$ implying that $\\mathfrak{p}$ divides $d_{K_{2}/K}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 5.6.28}", "question": "Let $L/K$ be a finite extension of algebraic number fields. If $\\tilde{L}$ denotes the normal closure, show that a prime $\\mathfrak{p}$ of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ is unramified in $L$ if and only if it is unramified in $\\tilde{L}$.", "solution": "If we apply the preceding exercise to the compositum of the conjugate fields of $L$, the result is immediate.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Lemma 6.1.1}", "question": "Let $K$ be an algebraic number field. Show that there is a constant $H_{K}$ such that given $\\alpha\\in K$, there exists $\\beta\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, and a non-zero integer $t$, with $|t|\\le H_{K}$, such that $|N(t\\alpha-\\beta)|<1$.", "solution": "Let $\\{\\omega_{1},\\omega_{2},...,\\omega_{n}\\}$ be an integral basis of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Given any $\\alpha\\in K$, there exists $m\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ such that $m\\alpha\\in\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$, so $\\alpha$ can be written as $\\alpha=\\sum_{i=1}^{n}c_{i}\\omega_{i},$ with $c_{i}\\in\\mathbb{Q}$ for all $i=1,2,...,n.$ Let $L$ be a natural number. Partition the interval $[0, 1]$ into $L$ parts, each of length $1/L$. This induces a subdivision of $[0, 1]^n$ into $L^{n}$ subcubes. Consider the map $\\varphi:\\alpha\\mathbb{Z}\\longrightarrow[0,1]^{n}$ defined by $t\\alpha \\mapsto (\\{tc_{1}\\},\\{tc_{2}\\},...,\\{tc_{n}\\})$ where $t\\in\\mathbb{Z}$, and $\\{a\\}$ denotes the fractional part of $a\\in\\mathbb{R}$. Let $t$ run from $0$ to $L^{n}$ (the number of subcubes in $[0,1]^n$). The number of choices for $t$ is then $L^{n}+1$ which is one more than the number of subcubes. There must be two distinct values of $t$, say $t_{1}$ and $t_{2}$, so that $t_{1}\\alpha$ and $t_{2}\\alpha$ get mapped to the same subcube of $[0, 1]^n$. Let $\\beta=\\sum_{i=1}^{n}([t_{1}c_{i}]-[t_{2}c_{i}])\\omega_{i},$ where $[a]$ denotes the integer part of $a\\in\\mathbb{R}$. Then, $(t_{1}-t_{2})\\alpha-\\beta=\\sum_{i=1}^{n}(\\{t_{1}c_{i}\\}-\\{t_{2}c_{i}\\})\\omega_{i}.$ Let $t=t_{1}-t_{2}$, then $|N(t\\alpha-\\beta)|=|N(\\sum_{i=1}^{n}(\\{t_{1}c_{i}\\}-\\{t_{2}c_{i}\\})\\omega_{i})|$. Since $|(\\{t_{1}c_{i}\\}-\\{t_{2}c_{i}\\})|\\le1/L$ we then have $|N(t\\alpha-\\beta)|\\le\\frac{1}{L^{n}}\\prod_{j=1}^{n}(\\sum_{i=1}^{n}|\\omega_{i}^{(j)}|)$ where $\\omega_{i}^{(j)}$ is the $i$th conjugate of $\\omega_{i}$. If we take $L^{n}>\\prod_{j=1}^{n}(\\sum_{i=1}^{n}|\\omega_{i}^{(j)}|)=H_{K}$ (say), then $|N(t\\alpha-\\beta)|<1$. Furthermore, since $0\\le t_{1}, t_{2}\\le L^{n}$, we have $|t|\\le L^{n}$. Thus, if we choose $L=H_{K}^{1/n}$ we are done.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.1.2}", "question": "Show that given $\\alpha,\\beta\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K},$ there exist $t\\in\\mathbb{Z},|t|\\le H_{K}$ and $w\\in\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$ so that $|N(\\alpha t-\\beta w)|<|N(\\beta)|$.", "solution": "If we apply Lemma 6.1.1 with $\\alpha$ replaced by $\\alpha/\\beta$, we conclude that there exist $t\\in\\mathbb{Z}$, $|t|\\le H_{K}$, and $w\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ such that $|N(t\\alpha/\\beta-w)|<1$. This implies $|N(t\\alpha-w\\beta)|<|N(\\beta)|$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.2.1}", "question": "Two fractional ideals $\\mathcal{A}$ and $\\mathcal{B}$ in $K$ are said to be equivalent if there exist $\\alpha,\\beta\\in\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$ such that $(\\alpha)\\mathcal{A}=(\\beta)\\mathcal{B}$. In this case, we write $\\mathcal{A}\\sim\\mathcal{B}$. Show that the relation $\\sim$ defined above is an equivalence relation.", "solution": "It is trivial that $\\mathcal{A}\\sim\\mathcal{A}$ and if $\\mathcal{A}\\sim\\mathcal{B}$ then $\\mathcal{B}\\sim\\mathcal{A}$ for any ideals $\\mathcal{A}$ and $\\mathcal{B}$. Suppose now that $\\mathcal{A}\\sim\\mathcal{B}$, and $\\mathcal{B}\\sim\\mathcal{C}$. That is, there exist $\\alpha,\\beta,\\gamma,\\theta\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ such that $(\\alpha)\\mathcal{A}=(\\beta)\\mathcal{B}$ and $(\\gamma)\\mathcal{B}=(\\theta)\\mathcal{C}$. It is now easily seen that $(\\alpha\\gamma)\\mathcal{A}=(\\beta\\theta)\\mathcal{C}$. Thus, $\\mathcal{A}\\sim\\mathcal{B}$ and $\\mathcal{B}\\sim\\mathcal{C}$ imply $\\mathcal{A}\\sim\\mathcal{C}$. Hence, $\\sim$ is an equivalence relation.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 6.2.2}", "question": "Show that there exists a constant $C_{K}$ such that every ideal $\\mathfrak{a}\\subseteq\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$ is equivalent to an ideal $\\mathfrak{b}\\subseteq\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$ with $N(\\mathfrak{b})\\le C_{K}$.", "solution": "Suppose $\\mathfrak{a}$ is an ideal of $\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$. Let $\\beta\\in\\mathfrak{a}$ be a non-zero element such that $|N(\\beta)|$ is minimal. For each $\\alpha\\in\\mathfrak{a}$, by Exercise 6.1.2, we can find $t\\in\\mathbb{Z},$ $|t|\\le H_{K}$ and $w\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ such that $|N(t\\alpha-w\\beta)|<|N(\\beta)|$. Moreover, since $\\alpha, \\beta\\in\\mathfrak{a}$, so $\\alpha-w\\beta\\in\\mathfrak{a};$ and therefore, by the minimality of $|N(\\beta)|$, we must have $t\\alpha=w\\beta$. Thus, we have shown that for any $\\alpha\\in\\mathfrak{a}$ there exist $t\\in\\mathbb{Z}$, $|t|\\le H_{K}$, and $w\\in\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$ such that $t\\alpha=w\\beta$. Let $M=\\prod_{|t|\\le H_{K}}t;$ and we have $M\\mathfrak{a}\\subseteq(\\beta)$. This means that $(\\beta)$ divides $(M)\\mathfrak{a}$, and so $(M)\\mathfrak{a}=(\\beta)\\mathfrak{b}$, for some ideal $\\mathfrak{b}\\subseteq\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$. Observe that $\\beta\\in\\mathfrak{a}$, so $M\\beta\\in(\\beta)\\mathfrak{b}$, and hence $(M)\\subseteq\\mathfrak{b}$. This implies that $|N(\\mathfrak{b})|\\le N((M))=C_{K}$. Hence, $\\mathfrak{a}\\sim\\mathfrak{b}$, and $C_{K}=N((M))$ satisfies the requirements.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.2.3}", "question": "Show that each equivalence class of ideals has an integral ideal representative.", "solution": "Suppose $\\mathcal{A}$ is a fractional ideal in $K$. Let $\\mathcal{A}=\\mathfrak{b}/\\mathfrak{c}$ with $\\mathfrak{b}, \\mathfrak{c}\\subseteq \\mathcal{O}_{K}$. We know from Exercise 4.4.1 that $\\mathfrak{c}\\cap\\mathbb{Z}\\ne\\{0\\}$, so there exists $0\\ne t\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ such that $t\\in\\mathfrak{c}$. Thus, $\\mathfrak{c}\\supseteq(t)=t\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, and so $\\mathfrak{c}$ divides $(t)$. This implies that there exists an integral ideal $\\mathfrak{e}\\subseteq\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ such that $\\mathfrak{ce}=(t)$. We now have $(t)\\mathcal{A}=(t)\\frac{\\mathfrak{b}}{\\mathfrak{c}}=\\frac{\\mathfrak{ce}\\mathfrak{b}}{\\mathfrak{c}}=\\mathfrak{e}\\mathfrak{b}\\subseteq\\mathcal{O}_{K}.$ Thus, $\\mathcal{A}\\sim\\mathfrak{be}\\subseteq\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ and the result is proved.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.2.4}", "question": "Prove that for any integer $x>0$, the number of integral ideals $\\mathfrak{a}\\subseteq\\mathbb{O}_{K}$ for which $N(\\mathfrak{a})\\le x$ is finite.", "solution": "Since the norm is multiplicative and takes values $> 1$ on prime ideals, and since integral ideals have unique factorization, it is sufficient to prove that there are only a finite number of prime ideals with $N(\\mathfrak{p})\\le x.$ Now, any prime contains exactly one prime $p\\in\\mathbb{Z}$, as shown in Exercise 4.4.4. Thus, $\\mathfrak{p}$ occurs in the factorization of $(p)\\subseteq\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$ into prime ideals. Since $N(\\mathfrak{p})\\ge2$, we have $N(\\mathfrak{p})=p^{t}$ for some $t\\ge1$. This implies there are at most $n$ possibilities for such $\\mathfrak{p}$, since the factorization $(p)=\\prod_{i=1}^{s}\\mathfrak{p}_{i}^{a_{i}}$ implies that $p^{n}=N((p))=\\prod_{i=1}^{s}N(\\mathfrak{p}_{i})^{a_{i}}$ leading to $s\\le n$. Moreover, $p\\le N(\\mathfrak{p})\\le x$. This proves the exercise.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 6.2.5}", "question": "Show that the number of equivalence classes of ideals is finite.", "solution": "By Exercise 6.2.3, each equivalence class of ideals can be represented by an integral ideal. This integral ideal, by Theorem 6.2.2, is equivalent to another integral ideal with norm less than or equal to a given constant $C_{K}$. Apply Exercise 6.2.4, and we are done.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.2.6}", "question": "Let $\\mathcal{H}$ be the set of all the equivalence classes of ideals of $K$. Given $\\mathcal{C}_{1}$ and $\\mathcal{C}_{2}$ in $\\mathcal{H}$, we define the product of $\\mathcal{C}_{1}$ and $\\mathcal{C}_{2}$ to be the equivalence class of $\\mathcal{AB}$, where $\\mathcal{A}$ and $\\mathcal{B}$ are two representatives of $\\mathcal{C}_{1}$ and $\\mathcal{C}_{2}$, respectively. Show that the product defined above is well defined, and that $\\mathcal{H}$ together with this product form a group, of which the equivalence class containing the principal ideals is the identity element.", "solution": "To show that the product defined above is well-defined we only need to show that if $\\mathcal{A}_{1}\\sim\\mathcal{B}_{1}$ and $\\mathcal{A}_{2}\\sim\\mathcal{B}_{2}$, then $\\mathcal{A}_{1}\\mathcal{A}_{2}\\sim\\mathcal{B}_{1}\\mathcal{B}_{2}$. Indeed, by definition, there exist $\\alpha_{1},\\alpha_{2},\\beta_{1},\\beta_{2}\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ such that $(\\alpha_{1})\\mathcal{A}_{1}=(\\beta_{1})\\mathcal{B}_{1}$ and $(\\alpha_{2})\\mathcal{A}_{2}=(\\beta_{2})\\mathcal{B}_{2}$. Therefore $(\\alpha_{1}\\alpha_{2})\\mathcal{A}_{1}\\mathcal{A}_{2}=(\\beta_{1}\\beta_{2})\\mathcal{B}_{1}\\mathcal{B}_{2}$. Thus, $\\mathcal{A}_{1}\\mathcal{A}_{2}\\sim\\mathcal{B}_{1}\\mathcal{B}_{2}$. Now, it is easy to check that $\\mathcal{H}$ with the product defined above is closed, associative, commutative, and has the class of principal ideals as the identity element. Thus, to finish the exercise, we need to show that each element of $\\mathcal{H}$ does have an inverse. Suppose $\\mathcal{C}$ is an arbitrary element of $\\mathcal{H}$. Let $\\mathfrak{a}\\subseteq\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$ be a representative of $\\mathcal{C}$ (we showed in Exercise 6.2.3 that every equivalence class of ideals contains an integral representative). If we proceed as we did when deriving equation (6.1) [in Exercise 6.2.3], we conclude that there exists an integral ideal $\\mathfrak{b}$ such that $\\mathfrak{ab}$ is principal. It then follows immediately that the class containing $\\mathfrak{b}$ is the inverse of $\\mathcal{C}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.2.7}", "question": "Show that the constant $C_{K}$ in Theorem 6.2.2 could be taken to be the greatest integer less than or equal to $H_{K}$, the Hurwitz constant.", "solution": "As in Lemma 6.1.1, let $\\{\\omega_{1},\\omega_{2},...,\\omega_{n}\\}$ be an integral basis of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Let $\\mathcal{C}$ be a given class of ideals. We denote by $\\mathcal{C}^{-1}$ the inverse class of $\\mathcal{C}$ in $\\mathcal{H}$. Let $\\mathfrak{a}$ be an integral representative of $\\mathcal{C}^{-1}$. Consider the following set $S=\\{s\\in\\mathbb{O}_{K}|s=\\sum_{i=1}^{n}m_{i}\\omega_{i},m_{i}\\in\\mathbb{Z},0\\le m_{i}<(N(\\mathfrak{a}))^{1/n}+1\\}.$ Then $|S|\\ge N(\\mathfrak{a})+1$. Since $N(\\mathfrak{a})=[\\mathfrak{O}_{K}:\\mathfrak{a}],$ we can find distinct $a, b\\in S$ such that $a\\equiv b$ (mod $\\mathfrak{a}$). Thus, $(a-b)\\subseteq\\mathfrak{a}$. This implies that there exists an integral ideal $\\mathfrak{b}$ such that $(a-b)=\\mathfrak{ab}$. It is easy to observe that $\\mathfrak{b}\\in\\mathcal{C}$. We may write $a-b=\\sum_{i=1}^{n}p_{i}\\omega_{i}$. Since $a, b\\in S,$ $|p_{i}|\\le(N(\\mathfrak{a}))^{1/n}+1,$ and so we have $|N(a-b)|=|\\prod_{j=1}^{n}(\\sum_{i=1}^{n}p_{i}\\omega_{i}^{(j)})| \\le\\prod_{j=1}^{n}(\\sum_{i=1}^{n}|p_{i}||\\omega_{i}^{(j)}|) \\le[(N(\\mathfrak{a}))^{1/n}+1]^{n}\\prod_{j=1}^{n}(\\sum_{i=1}^{n}|\\omega_{i}^{(j)}|) \\le[(N(\\mathfrak{a}))^{1/n}+1]^{n}H_{K}$. We also know that since $(a-b)=\\mathfrak{ab}, |N(a-b)|=N(\\mathfrak{a})N(\\mathfrak{b})$. Thus, $N(\\mathfrak{b})\\le[1+(N(\\mathfrak{a}))^{-1/n}]^{n}H_{K}$. However, observe that we can always replace $\\mathfrak{a}$ by the ideal $c\\mathfrak{a}$, in the same equivalence class, for any $c\\in\\mathfrak{O}_{K}\\backslash\\{0\\},$ and with $|N(c)|$ arbitrarily large; we can therefore make $[1+(N(\\mathfrak{a}))^{-1/n}]^n$ arbitrarily close to 1. Thus, every equivalence class $\\mathcal{C}$ has an integral representative $\\mathfrak{b}$ with $N(\\mathfrak{b})\\le H_{K}$. This implies that every ideal is equivalent to another integral ideal with norm less than or equal to $H_{K}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Example 6.2.8}", "question": "Show that the class number of $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-5})$ is 2.", "solution": "We proved in Exercise 4.1.3 that the integers in $K$ are $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-5}]$ so that $\\omega_{1}^{(1)}=1$, $\\omega_{2}^{(1)}=\\sqrt{-5}$, $\\omega_{1}^{(2)}=1$, $\\omega_{2}^{(2)}=-\\sqrt{-5}$, and the Hurwitz constant is $(1+\\sqrt{5})^{2}=10.45...$. Thus, $C_{K}=10.$ This implies that every equivalence class of ideals $\\mathcal{C}\\in\\mathcal{H}$ has an integral representative $\\mathfrak{a}$ such that $N(\\mathfrak{a})\\le10$. $\\mathfrak{a}$ has a factorization into a product of primes, say, $\\mathfrak{a}=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}\\mathfrak{p}_{2}...\\mathfrak{p}_{m}$. Consider $\\mathfrak{p}_{1}$. There exists, by Exercise 4.4.4, a unique prime number $p\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ such that $p\\in\\mathfrak{p}_{1}$. This implies that $\\mathfrak{p}_{1}$ is in the factorization of $(p)$ into product of primes in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Thus, $N(\\mathfrak{p}_{1})$ is a power of $p$. Since $N(\\mathfrak{a})=\\prod_{i=1}^{m}N(\\mathfrak{p}_{i})$, and $N(\\mathfrak{a})\\le10$, we deduce that $N(\\mathfrak{p}_{i})\\le10$ for all $i$. And so, in particular, $N(\\mathfrak{p}_{1})\\le10$. Therefore, $p\\le10$. Thus, $p$ could be 2, 3, 5, or 7. For $p=2,3,5$, and 7, $(p)$ factors in $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-5}]$ as follows: $(2)=(2,1+\\sqrt{-5})(2,1-\\sqrt{-5})$, $(3)=(3,1+\\sqrt{-5})(3,1-\\sqrt{-5})$, $(7)=(7,3+\\sqrt{-5})(7,3-\\sqrt{-5})$, $(5)=(\\sqrt{-5})^{2}$. Thus, $\\mathfrak{p}_{1}$ can only be $(2,1+\\sqrt{-5})$, $(2,1-\\sqrt{-5})$, $(3,1+\\sqrt{-5})$, $(3, 1-\\sqrt{-5})$, $(7,3+\\sqrt{-5})$, $(7,3-\\sqrt{-5})$, or $(\\sqrt{-5})$. The same conclusion holds for any $\\mathfrak{p}_{i}$ for $i=2,...,m$. Moreover, it can be seen that $(\\sqrt{-5})$ is principal, and all the others are not principal (by taking the norms), but are pairwise equivalent by the following relations: $(2,1+\\sqrt{-5})=(2,1-\\sqrt{-5})$, $(3,1+\\sqrt{-5})(1-\\sqrt{-5})=(3)(2,1-\\sqrt{-5})$, $(3,1-\\sqrt{-5})(1+\\sqrt{-5})=(3)(2,1+\\sqrt{-5})$, $(7,3+\\sqrt{-5})(3-\\sqrt{-5})=(7)(2,1-\\sqrt{-5})$, $(7,3-\\sqrt{-5})(3+\\sqrt{-5})=(7)(2,1+\\sqrt{-5})$. Therefore, $\\mathfrak{a}$ is equivalent to either the class of principal ideals or the class of those primes listed above. Hence, the class number of $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-5})$ is 2.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Example 6.3.1}", "question": "Show that the equation $x^{2}+5=y^{3}$ has no integral solution.", "solution": "Observe that if $y$ is even, then $x$ is odd, and $x^{2}+5\\equiv0$ (mod 4), and hence $x^{2}\\equiv3$ (mod 4), which is a contradiction. Therefore, $y$ is odd. Also, if a prime $p|(x,y)$, then $p|5$, so $p=5;$ and hence, by dividing both sides of the equation by 5, we end up with $1\\equiv0$ (mod 5), which is absurd. Thus, $x$ and $y$ are coprime. Suppose now that $(x, y)$ is an integral solution to the given equation. We consider the factorization $(x+\\sqrt{-5})(x-\\sqrt{-5})=y^{3}$ in the ring of integers $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-5}]$. Suppose a prime $\\mathfrak{p}$ divides the gcd of $(x+\\sqrt{-5})$ and $(x-\\sqrt{-5})$ (which implies $\\mathfrak{p}$ divides $(y)$). Then $\\mathfrak{p}$ divides $(2x)$. Also, since $y$ is odd, $\\mathfrak{p}$ does not divide $(2)$. Thus, $\\mathfrak{p}$ divides $(x)$. This is a contradiction to the fact that $x$ and $y$ are coprime. Hence, $(x+\\sqrt{-5})$ and $(x-\\sqrt{-5})$ are coprime ideals. This and the equation ensure (by Exercise 5.3.12) that $(x+\\sqrt{-5})=\\mathfrak{a}^{3}$ and $(x-\\sqrt{-5})=\\mathfrak{b}^{3}$, for some ideals $\\mathfrak{a}$ and $\\mathfrak{b}$. Since the class number of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-5})$ was found in Example 6.2.8 to be 2, $\\mathfrak{c}^{2}$ is principal for any ideal $\\mathfrak{c}$. Thus, since $\\mathfrak{a}^{3}$ and $\\mathfrak{b}^{3}$ are principal, we deduce that $\\mathfrak{a}$ and $\\mathfrak{b}$ are also principal. Moreover, since the units of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-5})$ are 1 and -1, which are both cubes, we conclude that $x+\\sqrt{-5}=(a+b\\sqrt{-5})^{3}$ for some integers $a$ and $b$. This implies that $1=b(3a^{2}-5b^{2})$. It is easy to see that $b|1$ so $b=\\pm1$. Therefore, $3a^{2}-5=\\pm1$. Both cases lead to contradiction with the fact that $a\\in\\mathbb{Z}$. Hence, the given equation does not have an integral solution.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.3.2}", "question": "Let $k>0$ be a squarefree positive integer. Suppose that $k\\equiv1,2$ (mod 4), and $k$ does not have the form $k=3a^{2}\\pm1$ for an integer $a$. Consider the equation $x^{2}+k=y^{3}$. Show that if 3 does not divide the class number of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-k})$ then this equation has no integral solution.", "solution": "Similar to what was done in Example 6.3.1, $y$ must be odd (consider congruences modulo 4). Also, if a prime $p|(x,y)$, then $p|k$; and hence, since $k$ is squarefree (so, in particular, $k$ is not divisible by $p^{2}$), by dividing both sides of the equation by $p$, we end up having a contradiction modulo $p$. Thus, $x$ and $y$ are coprime. Suppose now that $(x,y)$ is an integral solution. As given, $k\\equiv1,2$ (mod 4), so $-k\\equiv3,2$ (mod 4). Thus, the integers in $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-k})$ are $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-k}]$. We consider the factorization $(x+\\sqrt{-k})(x-\\sqrt{-k})=y^{3}$ in the ring of integers $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-k}]$. As in Example 6.3.1, suppose a prime $\\mathfrak{p}$ divides the gcd of the ideals $(x+\\sqrt{-k})$ and $(x-\\sqrt{-k})$ (which implies $\\mathfrak{p}$ divides $(y)$). Then $\\mathfrak{p}$ divides $(2x)$. Since $y$ is odd, $\\mathfrak{p}$ does not divide $(2)$. Thus, $\\mathfrak{p}$ divides $(x)$. This contradicts the fact that $x$ and $y$ are coprime. Hence, $(x+\\sqrt{-k})$ and $(x-\\sqrt{-k})$ are coprime. The equation now implies that $(x+\\sqrt{-k})=\\mathfrak{a}^{3}$ and $(x-\\sqrt{-k})=\\mathfrak{b}^{3}$ for some ideals $\\mathfrak{a}$ and $\\mathfrak{b}$. Let $h(K)$ be the class number of the field $K$, then $\\mathfrak{c}^{h(K)}$ is principal for any ideal $\\mathfrak{c}$. As given, $3 \\nmid h(K)$, so $(3,h(K))=1$. Thus, since $\\mathfrak{a}^{3}$ and $\\mathfrak{b}^{3}$ are principal, $\\mathfrak{a}$ and $\\mathfrak{b}$ are also principal. We must have $(x+\\sqrt{-k})=\\epsilon(a+b\\sqrt{-k})^{3}$ for some integers $a, b$, and a unit $\\epsilon\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-k}]$. Let $\\epsilon=x_{1}+x_{2}\\sqrt{-k}$. Then, since $\\alpha\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-k}]$ is a unit if and only if $N(\\alpha)=\\pm1$, we have $x_{1}^{2}+kx_{2}^{2}=\\pm1$. As given $k>0$ and $k$ is square-free, so $k>1$. Thus, $x_{2}=0$ and $x_{1}=\\pm1$. Hence, $\\epsilon=\\pm1$, and in the equation it could be absorbed into the cube. We have $(x+\\sqrt{-k})=(a+b\\sqrt{-k})^{3}$. This implies $1=b(3a^{2}-kb^{2})$. It is clear that $b|1$, so $b=\\pm1$. Both cases lead to either $k=3a^{2}+1$ or $k=3a^{2}-1$, which violates the hypothesis. Hence, we conclude that equation does not have an integral solution.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.4.1}", "question": "Fix a positive integer $g>1$. Suppose that $n$ is odd, greater than 1, and $n^{g}-1=d$ is squarefree. Show that the ideal class group of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-d})$ has an element of order $g$.", "solution": "Since $d$ is even and squarefree, $d\\equiv2$ (mod 4). The ring of integers of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-d})$ is $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-d}].$ We have the ideal factorization: $(n)^{g}=(n^{g})=(1+d)=(1+\\sqrt{-d})(1-\\sqrt{-d})$. The ideals $(1+\\sqrt{-d})$ and $(1-\\sqrt{-d})$ are coprime since $n$ is odd. Thus by Theorem 5.3.13, each of the ideals $(1+\\sqrt{-d})$, $(1-\\sqrt{-d})$ must be $g$th powers. Thus $\\mathfrak{a}^{g}=(1+\\sqrt{-d})$, $(\\mathfrak{a}^{\\prime})^{g}=(1-\\sqrt{-d})$, with $\\mathfrak{a}\\mathfrak{a}^{\\prime}=(n)$. Hence $\\mathfrak{a}$ has order dividing $g$ in the class group. Suppose $\\mathfrak{a}^{m}=(u+v\\sqrt{-d})$ for some $u, v\\in\\mathbb{Z}.$ Note that $v$ cannot be zero for otherwise $\\mathfrak{a}^{m}=(u)$ implies that $(\\mathfrak{a}^{\\prime})^{m}=(u)$ so that $(u)=\\gcd(\\mathfrak{a}^{m},(\\mathfrak{a}^{\\prime})^{m})$, contrary to $\\gcd(\\mathfrak{a},\\mathfrak{a}^{\\prime})=1$. Therefore $v\\ne0$. Now take norms of the equation $\\mathfrak{a}^{m}=(u+v\\sqrt{-d})$ to obtain $n^{m}=u^{2}+v^{2}d\\ge d=n^{g}-1$. If $m\\le g-1$, we get $n^{g-1}\\ge n^{g}-1$ which implies that $1\\ge n^{g-1}(n-1)\\ge2,$ a contradiction. Therefore $\\mathfrak{a}^{g}=(1+\\sqrt{-d})$ and $\\mathfrak{a}^{m}$ is not principal for any $m<g$. Thus there is an element of order $g$ in the ideal class group of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-d})$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.4.2}", "question": "Let $g$ be odd and greater than 1. If $d=3^{g}-x^{2}$ is squarefree with $x$ odd and satisfying $x^{2}<3^{g}/2$, show that $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-d})$ has an element of order $g$ in the class group.", "solution": "Observe that $d\\equiv2$ (mod 4) so the ring of integers of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-d})$ is $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-d}]$. The factorization $3^{g}=(x+\\sqrt{-d})(x-\\sqrt{-d})$ shows that 3 splits in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-d})$, as the ideals $(x+\\sqrt{-d})$ and $(x-\\sqrt{-d})$ are coprime. Thus $(3)=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime}$. We must have $(x+\\sqrt{-d})=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{g}$. Therefore, the order of $\\mathfrak{p}_{1}$ in the ideal class group is a divisor of $g$. If $\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{m}=(u+v\\sqrt{-d})$ then $3^{m}=u^{2}+v^{2}d$. If $v\\ne0$, we deduce $3^{m}\\ge d>3^{g}/2$ which is a contradiction if $m\\le g-1$. Either $\\mathfrak{p}_{1}$ has order $g$ or $v=0.$ In the latter case, we get $u^{2}=3^{m}$, a contradiction since $m$ is odd.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.4.3}", "question": "Let $g$ be odd. Let $N$ be the number of squarefree integers of the form $3^{g}-x^{2}$, $x$ odd, $0<x^{2}<3^{g}/2$. For $g$ sufficiently large, show that $N\\gg3^{g/2}$. Deduce that there are infinitely many imaginary quadratic fields whose class number is divisible by $g$.", "solution": "The number of integers under consideration is $\\frac{1}{2\\sqrt{2}}3^{g/2}+O(1).$ From these, we will remove any number divisible by the square of a prime. Since $g$ is odd, $x^{2}\\equiv3^{g}$ (mod 4) implies that $x^{2}\\equiv-1$ (mod 4) has a solution. This is a contradiction. Therefore $4 \\nmid 3^{g}-x^{2}$. If $3|x$, then $3|3^{g}-x^{2}$ so we remove such numbers. Their count is $\\frac{1}{6\\sqrt{2}}3^{g/2}+O(1).$ If $p$ is odd and greater than 3, the number of $3^{g}-x^{2}$ divisible by $p^{2}$ is at most $\\frac{3^{g/2}}{p^{2}\\sqrt{2}}+O(1).$ Thus, $N\\ge\\frac{3^{g/2}}{\\sqrt{2}}\\{\\frac{1}{2}-\\frac{1}{6}-\\sum_{5\\le p\\le 3^{g/2}}\\frac{1}{p^{2}}+O(\\frac{3^{g/2}}{g})\\}$ by using Exercise 1.1.26. Now $\\sum_{p\\ge5}\\frac{1}{p^{2}}\\le\\sum_{n=5}^{\\infty}\\frac{1}{n(n-1)}=(\\frac{1}{4}-\\frac{1}{5})+(\\frac{1}{5}-\\frac{1}{6})+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot =\\frac{1}{4}$. Since $\\frac{1}{2}-\\frac{1}{4}-\frac{1}{6}=\\frac{1}{12}$ we see $N\\gg3^{g/2}$. By the previous exercise, each of these values gives rise to a distinct quadratic field whose class group has exponent divisible by $g$. By applying this result for powers of $g$ we deduce that there are infinitely many imaginary quadratic fields of class number divisible by $g$. (This argument is due to Ankeny and Chowla.)", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.1}", "question": "Show that the class number of $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-19})$ is 1.", "solution": "We know that $1, (1+\\sqrt{-19})/2$ forms an integral basis. We then write $\\omega_{1}^{(1)}=1, \\omega_{2}^{(1)}=\\frac{1+\\sqrt{-19}}{2}, \\omega_{1}^{(2)}=1, \\omega_{2}^{(2)}=\\frac{1-\\sqrt{-19}}{2},$ and use this to find the Hurwitz constant $H_{K}=\\prod_{j=1}^{2}(\\sum_{i=1}^{2}|\\omega_{i}^{(j)}|) = (1+|\\frac{1+\\sqrt{-19}}{2}|)(1+|\\frac{1-\\sqrt{-19}}{2}|) = 13.53...$. Just as in Example 6.2.8, we examine all the primes $p\\le13$ to determine the prime ideals with $N(\\mathfrak{p})\\le13$. The primes in question are 2, 3, 5, 7, 11, and 13. They factor in $\\mathbb{Z}[(1+\\sqrt{-19})/2]$ as follows: 2, 3, and 13 stay prime, and $5=(\\frac{1+\\sqrt{-19}}{2})(\\frac{1-\\sqrt{-19}}{2})$, $7=(\\frac{3+\\sqrt{-19}}{2})(\\frac{3-\\sqrt{-19}}{2})$, $11=(\\frac{5+\\sqrt{-19}}{2})(\\frac{5-\\sqrt{-19}}{2})$. These are all principal ideals and thus are all equivalent. This shows that the class number of $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-19})$ is 1.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.2}", "question": "(Siegel) Let $C$ be a symmetric, bounded domain in $\\mathbb{R}^{n}$. (That is, $C$ is bounded and if $x\\in C$ so is $-x$.) If $\\text{vol}(C)>1$, then there are two distinct points $P,Q\\in C$ such that $P-Q$ is a lattice point.", "solution": "Let $\\varphi(x)=1$ or 0 according as $x\\in C$ or not. Then set $\\psi(x)=\\sum_{\\gamma\\in\\mathbb{Z}^{n}}\\varphi(x+\\gamma).$ Clearly, $\\psi(x)$ is bounded and integrable. Thus $\\int_{\\mathbb{R}^{n}/\\mathbb{Z}^{n}}\\psi(x)dx=\\int_{\\mathbb{R}^{n}/\\mathbb{Z}^{n}}\\sum_{\\gamma\\in\\mathbb{Z}^{n}}\\varphi(x+\\gamma)dx =\\sum_{\\gamma\\in\\mathbb{Z}^{n}}\\int_{\\mathbb{R}^{n}/\\mathbb{Z}^{n}}\\varphi(x+\\gamma)dx =\\sum_{\\gamma\\in\\mathbb{Z}^{n}}\\int_{\\gamma+\\mathbb{R}^{n}/\\mathbb{Z}^{n}}\\varphi(x)dx =\\int_{\\mathbb{R}^{n}}\\varphi(x)dx =\\text{vol}(C)>1$. Since $\\psi(x)$ takes only integer values, we must have $\\psi(x)\\ge2$ for some $x$. Therefore, there are two distinct points $P+\\gamma,$ $P+\\gamma^{\\prime}$ in $C$ so their difference is a lattice point.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.3}", "question": "If $C$ is any convex, bounded, symmetric domain of volume $>2^{n}$, show that $C$ contains a non-zero lattice point. ($C$ is said to be convex if $x, y\\in C$ implies $\\lambda x+(1-\\lambda)y\\in C$ for $0\\le\\lambda\\le1.$)", "solution": "By the previous question, the bounded symmetric domain $\\frac{1}{2}C$ contains two distinct points $\\frac{1}{2}P$ and $\\frac{1}{2}Q$ such that $\\frac{1}{2}P-\\frac{1}{2}Q$ is a lattice point, because $\\text{vol}(\\frac{1}{2}C)=\\frac{\\text{vol}(C)}{2^{n}}>1.$ Since $C$ is convex, $0\\ne\\gamma=\\frac{1}{2}P-\\frac{1}{2}Q\\in C$ as $P,Q\\in C.$ This is a nonzero lattice point in $C$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.4}", "question": "Show in the previous question if the volume $\\ge2^{n}$, the result is still valid, if $C$ is closed.", "solution": "We can enlarge our domain by $\\epsilon$ to create $C_{\\epsilon}$ of volume $>2^{n}.$ For each $\\epsilon$, $C_{\\epsilon}$ contains a lattice point. Since $\\lim_{\\epsilon\\rightarrow0}C_{\\epsilon}=C,$ $C$ also contains a lattice point (perhaps on the boundary).", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.5}", "question": "Show that there exist bounded, symmetric convex domains with volume $<2^{n}$ that do not contain a lattice point.", "solution": "Consider $-1<x_{i}<1$, $1\\le i\\le n$. This hypercube has volume $2^{n}$ and the only lattice point it contains is 0.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.6}", "question": "(Minkowski) For $x=(x_{1},...,x_{n})$, let $L_{i}(x)=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}a_{ij}x_{j}, 1\\le i\\le n$ be $n$ linear forms with real coefficients. Let $C$ be the domain defined by $|L_{i}(x)|\\le\\lambda_{i}, 1\\le i\\le n$. Show that if $\\lambda_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\lambda_{n}\\ge|\\det A|$ where $A=(a_{ij})$, then $C$ contains a nonzero lattice point.", "solution": "Clearly $C$ is convex, bounded, and symmetric. We want to compute the volume of $C/2$. We make a linear change of variables: $y=Ax$. Then $dy_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot dy_{n}=(\\det A)dx_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot dx_{n}$, so we get $\\text{vol}(C/2)=\\frac{\\lambda_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\lambda_{n}}{|\\det A|}\\ge1$ from which the result follows because $C$ is closed.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.7}", "question": "Suppose that among the $n$ linear forms $L_{i}(x)$ defined in Exercise 6.5.6, $1\\le i\\le r_{1}$ are real (i.e., $a_{ij}\\in\\mathbb{R})$, and $2r_{2}$ are not real (i.e., some $a_{ij}$ may be nonreal). Further assume that $L_{r_{1}+r_{2}+j}=\\overline{L_{r_{1}+j}}$ for $1\\le j\\le r_{2}$. That is, $L_{r_{1}+r_{2}+j}(x)=\\sum_{k=1}^{n}\\overline{a}_{r_{1}+j,k}x_{k}$ for $1\\le j\\le r_{2}$. Now let $C$ be the convex, bounded symmetric domain defined by $|L_{i}(x)|\\le\\lambda_{i}$ ($1\\le i\\le n$), with $\\lambda_{r_{1}+j}=\\lambda_{r_{1}+r_{2}+j}$ ($1\\le j\\le r_{2}$). Show that if $\\lambda_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\lambda_{n}\\ge|\\det A|,$ then $C$ contains a nonzero lattice point.", "solution": "We replace the nonreal linear forms by real ones and apply the previous result. Set $L_{r_{1}+j}^{\\prime}=\\frac{L_{r_{1}+j}+L_{r_{1}+r_{2}+j}}{2}$ and $L_{r_{1}+j}^{\\prime\\prime}=\\frac{L_{r_{1}+j}-L_{r_{1}+r_{2}+j}}{2}.$ Then $L_{r_{1}+j}^{\\prime},L_{r_{1}+j}^{\\prime\\prime}$ are linear forms. Clearly, if $|L_{r_{1}+j}^{\\prime}|\\le\\frac{\\lambda_{r_{1}+j}}{\\sqrt{2}}$ and $|L_{r_{1}+j}^{\\prime\\prime}|\\le\\frac{\\lambda_{r_{1}+j}}{\\sqrt{2}}$ then $|L_{r_{1}+j}|\\le\\lambda_{r_{1}+j}$, so we replace $|L_{r_{1}+j}|\\le\\lambda_{r_{1}+j}$, $|L_{r_{1}+r_{2}+j}|\\le\\lambda_{r_{1}+j}$ with $L_{r_{1}+j}^{\\prime}$ and $L_{r_{1}+j}^{\\prime\\prime}$ satisfying the inequalities above. We deduce by the results established in the previous questions, that this domain contains a nonzero lattice point provided $\\frac{\\lambda_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\lambda_{n}2^{-r_{2}}}{|\\det A^{\\prime}|}>1,$ where $A^{\\prime}$ is the appropriately modified matrix. A simple linear algebra computation shows $\\det A^{\\prime}=2^{-r_{2}}\\det A$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.8}", "question": "Using the previous result, deduce that if $K$ is an algebraic number field with discriminant $d_{K}$, then every ideal class contains an ideal $\\mathfrak{b}$ satisfying $N\\mathfrak{b}\\le\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}$.", "solution": "Let $\\mathfrak{a}$ be any integral ideal and $\\alpha_{1},...,\\alpha_{n}$ an integral basis of $\\mathfrak{a}$. Consider the linear forms $L_{i}(x)=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}\\alpha_{j}^{(i)}x_{j}$ and the bounded symmetric convex domain defined by $|L_{i}(x)|\\le|\\Delta|^{1/n}$, where $|\\Delta|=|\\det(\\alpha_{j}^{(i)})|$. By the previous question, the system has a non-trivial integral solution, $(x_{1},...,x_{n})$. Let $\\omega=x_{1}\\alpha_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+x_{n}\\alpha_{n}\\in\\mathfrak{a}$. Then $(\\omega)\\subseteq\\mathfrak{a}$ so that for some ideal $\\mathfrak{b}$, $\\mathfrak{ab}=(\\omega)$. But $|N(\\omega)|=|N\\mathfrak{a}||N\\mathfrak{b}|\\le|\\Delta|$ by construction. Also, $|\\Delta|^{2}=(N\\mathfrak{a})^{2}|d_{K}|$ by Exercise 4.4.5. Hence, $|N\\mathfrak{b}|\\le\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}$. Given any ideal $\\mathfrak{a}$ we have found an ideal $\\mathfrak{b}$ in the inverse class whose norm is less than or equal to $\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.9}", "question": "Let $X_{t}$ consist of points $(x_{1},...,x_{r},y_{1},z_{1},...,y_{s},z_{s})$ in $\\mathbb{R}^{r+2s}$ where the coordinates satisfy $|x_{1}|+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+|x_{r}|+2\\sqrt{y_{1}^{2}+z_{1}^{2}}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+2\\sqrt{y_{s}^{2}+z_{s}^{2}}<t.$ Show that $X_{t}$ is a bounded, convex, symmetric domain.", "solution": "The fact that $X_{t}$ is bounded and symmetric is clear. To see convexity, let $P=(a_{1},...,a_{r},b_{1},c_{1},...,b_{s},c_{s})$ and $Q=(d_{1},...,d_{r},e_{1},f_{1},...,e_{s},f_{s})$ be points of $X_{t}$. We must show that $\\lambda P+\\mu Q\\in X_{t}$ whenever $\\lambda, \\mu\\ge0$ and $\\lambda+\\mu=1$. Clearly $|\\lambda a_{i}+\\mu d_{i}|\\le\\lambda|a_{i}|+\\mu|d_{i}|$. Also $\\sqrt{(\\lambda b_{i}+\\mu e_{i})^{2}+(\\lambda c_{i}+\\mu f_{i})^{2}}\\le\\lambda\\sqrt{b_{i}^{2}+c_{i}^{2}}+\\mu\\sqrt{e_{i}^{2}+f_{i}^{2}},$ as is easily verified. From these inequalities, it follows that $\\lambda P+\\mu Q\\in X_{t}$ so that $X_{t}$ is convex.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.10}", "question": "In the previous question, show that the volume of $X_{t}$ is $\\frac{2^{r-s}\\pi^{s}t^{n}}{n!}$ where $n=r+2s$.", "solution": "We begin by making a change of variables to polar coordinates: $2y_{j}=\\rho_{j}\\cos\\theta_{j}$, $2z_{j}=\\rho_{j}\\sin\\theta_{j}$, $4 dy_j dz_j = \\rho_j d\\rho_j d\\theta_j$ so that integrating over $x_{i}\\ge0$ for $1\\le i\\le r$ gives $\\text{vol}(X_{t})=2^{r}\\cdot2^{-2s}\\int\\rho_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\rho_{s}dx_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot dx_{r}d\\rho_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot d\\rho_{s}d\\theta_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot d\\theta_{s} =2^{r}2^{-2s}(2\\pi)^{s}\\int_{Y_{t}}\\rho_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\rho_{s}dx_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot dx_{r}d\\rho_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot d\\rho_{s}$ where $Y_{t}=\\{(x_{1},...,x_{r},\\rho_{1},...,\\rho_{s}):x_{i},\\rho_{j}\\ge0,x_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+x_{r}+\\rho_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\rho_{s}\\le t\\}.$ Let $f_{r,s}(t)$ denote the value of the above integral. By changing variables, it is clear that $f_{r,s}(1)=\\int_{0}^{1}f_{r-1,s}(1-x_{1})dx_{1} =f_{r-1,s}(1)\\int_{0}^{1}x_{1}^{r-1+2s}dx_{1} =\\frac{1}{r+2s}f_{r-1,s}(1)$. Proceeding inductively, we get $f_{r,s}(1)=\\frac{(2s)!}{(r+2s)!}f_{0,s}(1).$ Now we evaluate $f_{0,s}(1)$ by integrating with respect to $\\rho_{s}$ first: $f_{0,s}(1)=\\int_{0}^{1}\\rho_{s}f_{0,s-1}(1-\\rho_{s})d\\rho_{s} =f_{0,s-1}(1)\\int_{0}^{1}\\rho_{s}(1-\\rho_{s})^{2s-2}d\\rho_{s} =\\frac{f_{0,s-1}(1)}{2s(2s-1)}.$ Again, proceeding inductively, we find $f_{0,s}(1)=1/(2s)!$ so that $f_{r,s}(1)=\\frac{1}{(r+2s)!}=\\frac{1}{n!}.$ This completes the proof.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.11}", "question": "Let $C$ be a bounded, symmetric, convex domain in $\\mathbb{R}^{n}$. Let $a_{1},...,a_{n}$ be linearly independent vectors in $\\mathbb{R}^{n}$. Let $A$ be the $n\\times n$ matrix whose rows are the $a_{i}$. If $\\text{vol}(C)>2^{n}|\\det A|$ show that there exist rational integers $x_{1},...,x_{n}$ (not all zero) such that $x_{1}a_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+x_{n}a_{n}\\in C$.", "solution": "Consider the set $D$ of all $(x_{1},...,x_{n})\\in\\mathbb{R}^{n}$ such that $x_{1}a_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+x_{n}a_{n}\\in C$. It is easily seen that $D$ is bounded, symmetric, and convex because $C$ is. Moreover, $D=A^{-1}C$ so that by linear algebra, $\\text{vol}(D)=\\text{vol}(C)(|\\det A|)^{-1}$. Thus, if $\\text{vol}(D)>2^{n}$, then $D$ contains a lattice point $(x_{1},...,x_{n})\\ne0$ such that $x_{1}a_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+x_{n}a_{n}\\in C$. But $\\text{vol}(D)>2^{n}$ is equivalent to $\\text{vol}(C)>2^{n}|\\det A|$ as desired.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.12}", "question": "(Minkowski's Bound) Let $K$ be an algebraic number field of degree $n$ over $\\mathbb{Q}$. Show that each ideal class contains an ideal $\\mathfrak{a}$ satisfying $N\\mathfrak{a}\\le\\frac{n!}{n^{n}}(\\frac{4}{\\pi})^{r_{2}}|d_{K}|^{1/2},$ where $r_{2}$ is the number of pairs of complex embeddings of $K$, and $d_{K}$ is the discriminant.", "solution": "Given any ideal $\\mathfrak{b}$, let $\\omega_{1},...,\\omega_{n}$ be a basis of $\\mathfrak{b}$. Let $a_{i}=(\\sigma_{1}(\\omega_{i}),...,\\sigma_{r_{1}}(\\omega_{i}),\\text{Re}(\\sigma_{r_{1}+1}(\\omega_{i})), \\text{Im}(\\sigma_{r_{1}+1}(\\omega_{i})),...,\\text{Re}(\\sigma_{r_{1}+r_{2}}(\\omega_{i})),\\text{Im}(\\sigma_{r_{1}+r_{2}}(\\omega_{i})))\\in\\mathbb{R}^{n}$. Then the $a_{i}$ are linearly independent vectors in $\\mathbb{R}^{n}$. Consider the bounded symmetric convex domain $X_{t}$ defined in Exercise 6.5.9 above (with $r=r_{1}, s=r_{2}$). By Exercise 6.5.10 above, the volume of $X_{t}$ is $\\frac{2^{r_{1}-r_{2}}\\pi^{r_{2}}t^{n}}{n!}$. If $t$ is chosen so that this volume is greater than $2^{n}|\\det A|$, then $X_{t}$ contains a lattice point $(x_{1},...,x_{n})$ so that $0\\ne x_{1}a_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+x_{n}a_{n}\\in X_{t}.$ Let us set $\\alpha=x_{1}\\omega_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+x_{n}\\omega_{n}\\in\\mathfrak{b}.$ By the arithmetic mean geometric mean inequality, we find $|N(\\alpha)|^{1/n}<\\frac{t}{n}$ so that $|N(\\alpha)|<(\\frac{t}{n})^{n}$. Moreover, $\\det A=2^{-r_{2}}|N(\\mathfrak{b})||d_{K}|^{1/2}$ and $\\frac{t^{n}}{n!}=\\frac{2^{n}|\\det A|}{2^{r_{1}-r_{2}}\\pi^{r_{2}}}=(\\frac{4}{\\pi})^{r_{2}}|N\\mathfrak{b}||d_{K}|^{1/2}.$ Thus, there is an $\\alpha\\in\\mathfrak{b}$, $\\alpha\\ne0$ such that $|N(\\alpha)|\\le\\frac{n!}{n^{n}}(\\frac{4}{\\pi})^{r_{2}}|N\\mathfrak{b}||d_{K}|^{1/2}.$ Write $(\\alpha)=\\mathfrak{ab}$ for some ideal $\\mathfrak{a}$. Then $N\\mathfrak{a}\\le\\frac{n!}{n^{n}}(\\frac{4}{\\pi})^{r_{2}}|d_{K}|^{1/2},$ as desired.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.13}", "question": "Show that if $K\\ne\\mathbb{Q}$, then $|d_{K}|>1$. Thus, by Dedekind's theorem, in any nontrivial extension of $K$, some prime ramifies.", "solution": "Since $N\\mathfrak{a}\\ge1$, we have by the Minkowski bound, $1\\le\\frac{n!}{n^{n}}(\\frac{4}{\\pi})^{r_{2}}|d_{K}|^{1/2}$ so that $|d_{K}|^{1/2}\\ge\\frac{n^{n}}{n!}(\\frac{\\pi}{4})^{r_{2}}\\ge\\frac{n^{n}}{n!}(\\frac{\\pi}{4})^{n/2}=c_{n},$ say. Then $\\frac{c_{n+1}}{c_{n}}=(\\frac{\\pi}{4})^{1/2}(1+\\frac{1}{n})^{n}$ which is greater than 1 for every positive $n$. Hence $c_{n+1}>c_{n}$. We have $c_{2}>1$ so that $|d_{K}|>1$, if $n\\ge2$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.14}", "question": "If $K$ and $L$ are algebraic number fields such that $d_{K}$ and $d_{L}$ are coprime, show that $K\\cap L=\\mathbb{Q}$. Deduce that $[KL:\\mathbb{Q}]=[K:\\mathbb{Q}][L:\\mathbb{Q}]$.", "solution": "If $M=K\\cap L$ then by a result of Chapter 4, $d_{M}|d_{K}$ and $d_{M}|d_{L}$. Since $d_{K}$ and $d_{L}$ are coprime, $d_{M}=1$. But then, by the previous exercise, $M=\\mathbb{Q}$. We have $[KL:\\mathbb{Q}]=[KL:K][K:\\mathbb{Q}]$. Let $L=\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$ and $g$ its minimal polynomial over $\\mathbb{Q}$. If $[KL:K]<[L:\\mathbb{Q}]$, then the minimal polynomial $h$ of $\\theta$ over $K$ divides $g$ and has degree smaller than that of $g$. Thus the coefficients of $h$ generate a proper extension $T$ (say) of $\\mathbb{Q}$ which is necessarily contained in $K$. Hence, $d_{T}|d_{K}$. If we let $\\tilde{L}$ be the normal closure of $L$ over $\\mathbb{Q}$, then $h\\in\\tilde{L}[x]$. We now need to use the fact that primes which ramify in $L$ are the same as the ones that ramify in $\\tilde{L}$ (see Exercise 5.6.28). Since $T$ is contained in $\\tilde{L}$, we see that $d_{T}|d_{\\tilde{L}}$ and by the quoted fact, we deduce that $d_{L}$ and $d_{K}$ have a common prime factor if $d_{T}>1$, which is contrary to hypothesis. Thus, $d_{T}=1$ and by Exercise 6.5.13 we deduce $T=\\mathbb{Q}$, a contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.15}", "question": "Use Minkowski's bound to show that $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{5})$ has class number 1.", "solution": "The discriminant of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{5})$ is 5 and the Minkowski bound is $\\frac{2!}{2^{2}}\\sqrt{5}=\\frac{\\sqrt{5}}{2}=1.11....$ The only ideal of norm less than $\\sqrt{5}/2$ is the trivial ideal which is principal.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.16}", "question": "Using Minkowski's bound, show that $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-5})$ has class number 2.", "solution": "The discriminant of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-5})$ is 20 and the Minkowski bound is $\\frac{2}{\\pi}\\sqrt{20}=\\frac{4}{\\pi}(2.236...)=2.84...$ We need to look at ideals of norm 2. There is only one ideal of norm 2 and by Exercise 5.2.5 we know that $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-5}]$ is not a principal ideal domain. Hence the class number must be 2.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.17}", "question": "Compute the class numbers of the fields $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{2})$, $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{3})$, and $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{13})$.", "solution": "The discriminants of these fields are 8, 12, and 13 respectively. The Minkowski bound is $\\frac{1}{2}\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}<\\frac{1}{2}\\sqrt{13}=1.802....$ The only ideal of norm less than 1.8 is the trivial ideal, which is principal, so the class number is 1. (Recall that in Exercises 2.4.5 and 2.5.4 we showed that the ring of integers of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{2})$ and $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{3})$ are Euclidean and hence PIDs. So that the class number is 1 for each of these was already known to us from Chapter 2.)", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.18}", "question": "Compute the class number of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{17}).$", "solution": "The discriminant of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{17})$ is 17 and the Minkowski bound is $\\frac{1}{2}\\sqrt{17}=2.06...$ We need to consider ideals of norm 2. Since $-2=\\frac{9-17}{4}=\\frac{3-\\sqrt{17}}{2}\\cdot\\frac{3+\\sqrt{17}}{2},$ 2 splits and the principal ideals $((3+\\sqrt{17})/2)$ and $((3-\\sqrt{17})/2)$ are the only ones of norm 2. Therefore, the class number is 1.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.19}", "question": "Compute the class number of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{6})$.", "solution": "The discriminant is 24 and the Minkowski bound is $\\frac{1}{2}\\sqrt{24}=\\sqrt{6}=2.44...,$ 2 ramifies in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{6})$. Moreover, $-2=(2-\\sqrt{6})(2+\\sqrt{6})$ so that the ideal $(2-\\sqrt{6})$ is the only one of norm 2 since $(2+\\sqrt{6})/(2-\\sqrt{6})$ is a unit. Thus, the class number is 1.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.20}", "question": "Show that the fields $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-1})$, $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-2})$, $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-3})$, and $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-7})$ each have class number 1.", "solution": "The Minkowski bound for an imaginary quadratic field $K$ is $\\frac{2}{\\pi}\\sqrt{|d_{K}|}$. The given fields have discriminants equal to -4, -8, -3, -7, respectively. Since $\\frac{2}{\\pi}\\sqrt{8}=\\frac{4\\sqrt{2}}{\\pi}=1.80...$ we deduce that every ideal is principal.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.21}", "question": "Let $K$ be an algebraic number field of degree $n$ over $\\mathbb{Q}$. Prove that $|d_{K}|\\ge(\\frac{\\pi}{4})^{n}(\\frac{n^{n}}{n!})^{2}$.", "solution": "This follows directly from Minkowski's bound.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.22}", "question": "Show that $|d_{K}|\\rightarrow\\infty$ as $n\\rightarrow\\infty$ in the preceding question.", "solution": "From integral calculus, $\\log n!=n\\log n-n+O(\\log n)$, so that $\\log|d_{K}|\\ge(2+\\log\\frac{\\pi}{4})n+O(\\log n).$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.23}", "question": "(Hermite) Show that there are only finitely many algebraic number fields with a given discriminant.", "solution": "We give a brief hint of the proof. From the preceding question, the degree $n$ of $K$ is bounded. By Minkowski's theorem, we can find an element $\\alpha\\ne0$ in $\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$ so that $|\\alpha^{(1)}|\\le\\sqrt{|d_{K}|},$ $|\\alpha^{(i)}|<1$, $i=2,...,r.$ We must show $\\alpha$ generates $K$, but this is not difficult. With these inequalities, the coefficients of the minimal polynomial of $\\alpha$ are bounded. Since the coefficients are integers, there are only finitely many such polynomials.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.24}", "question": "Let $p$ be a prime $\\equiv11$ (mod 12). If $p>3^{n}$, show that the ideal class group of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-p})$ has an element of order greater than $n$.", "solution": "Since $-p\\equiv1$ (mod 3), $x^{2}\\equiv-p$ (mod 3) has a solution and so 3 splits in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-3})$. [Note: The context implies $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-p})$.] Write $(3)=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime}$. We claim the order of $\\mathfrak{p}_{1}$ in the ideal class group is at least $n$. If not, $\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{m}$ is principal and equals $(u+v\\sqrt{-p})$ (say) for some $m<n$. Taking norms, we see $3^{m}=u^{2}+pv^{2}$ has a solution. If $v\\ne0$, this is a contradiction since $p>3^{n}$. If $v=0$, we get $m$ is even, so that $\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{m}=(u)=(3^{m/2})=\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{m/2}(\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{\\prime})^{m/2}$, contradicting unique factorization.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.25}", "question": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\alpha)$ where $\\alpha$ is a root of the polynomial $f(x)=x^{5}-x+1$. Prove that $\\mathbb{Q}(\\alpha)$ has class number 1.", "solution": "Since $f(x)$ is a polynomial of the type described in Exercise 4.5.4, we deduce immediately that $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\alpha)=5^{5}-4^{4}=2869=19\\cdot151$. Since $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(\\alpha)$ is squarefree, Exercise 4.5.26 tells us that $\\mathfrak{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\alpha]$ and $d_{K}=2869$. A quick look at the graph of $f(x)=x^{5}-x+1$ shows that $r_{1}=1$ and $r_{2}=2$. Using Minkowski's bound, we find that every ideal class must contain an ideal $\\mathfrak{a}$ of norm strictly less than 4. Therefore we must look at the numbers 2 and 3 to see how they factor in this ring. Let $\\mathfrak{p}$ be an ideal such that $N\\mathfrak{p}=2$ or 3. Then $\\mathfrak{p}$ is prime, because $\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathfrak{p}$ is a field. Recall that to find $\\mathfrak{p}$ we consider $f(x)$ mod $p$. If $f(x)\\equiv f_{1}^{e_{1}}(x)\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot f_{g}^{e_{g}}(x) \\pmod p$, then $p\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$ factors as $\\mathfrak{p}_{1}^{e_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{g}^{e_{g}}$ with $N\\mathfrak{p}_{i}=p^{f_{i}}$ where $f_{i}$ is the degree of $f_{i}(x)$. First, suppose we have an ideal with $N\\mathfrak{p}=2$. Then $\\mathfrak{p}$ must appear in the prime factorization of $2\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ and so in the factorization of $f(x)$ (mod 2), there is a linear factor. However, it is easy to see that $x^{5}-x+1$ has no linear factor mod 2, and so there are no ideals of norm 2. By a similar argument, we see that $x^{5}-x+1$ must have a linear factor mod 3, if there exists an ideal with norm 3. Again, it is clear that $x^{5}-x+1$ can have no linear factor, and we conclude that there are no ideals of norm 3 in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Thus, the only ideal of norm less than 4 is the trivial ideal, and we conclude that $\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$ has class number 1.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.26}", "question": "Determine the class number of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{14})$.", "solution": "The Minkowski bound in this case is $\\frac{2!}{2^{2}}\\sqrt{14\\cdot4}=\\sqrt{14}=3.74...$ Then we must check ideals of norm less than or equal to 3. Therefore we must look at $2\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ and $3\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ to see how they factor in this ring. Since 3 is inert, there are no ideals of norm 3. However, 2 ramifies as $(2)=(4+\\sqrt{14})(4-\\sqrt{14})=\\mathfrak{p}^{2}$, where $\\mathfrak{p}=(4+\\sqrt{14})$. This is a principal ideal, and we conclude that all ideals of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{14})$ are principal and so the class number is 1.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 6.5.27}", "question": "If $K$ is an algebraic number field of finite degree over $\\mathbb{Q}$ with $d_{K}$ squarefree, show that $K$ has no non-trivial subfields.", "solution": "By Exercise 6.5.13 and 5.6.25, any proper subfield would introduce a power into the discriminant of $K$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.1.1}", "question": "Let $p$ be a prime and $a \\ne 0$. Show that $x^{2} \\equiv a \\pmod p$ has a solution if and only if $a^{(p-1)/2} \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$.", "solution": "Suppose that $x^{2} \\equiv a \\pmod p$ has a solution. Let $x_{0}$ be this solution, i.e., $x_{0}^{2} \\equiv a \\pmod p$. But then, $a^{(p-1)/2} \\equiv (x_{0}^{2})^{(p-1)/2} \\equiv x_{0}^{p-1} \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$. The last congruence follows from Fermat's Little Theorem.\n\nWe begin by noting that $a \\not\\equiv 0 \\pmod p$. So $a \\pmod p$ can be viewed as an element of $(\\mathbb{Z}/p\\mathbb{Z})^{\\times}$, the units of $(\\mathbb{Z}/p\\mathbb{Z})$. Since $(\\mathbb{Z}/p\\mathbb{Z})^{\\times}$ is a cyclic group, there exists some generator $g$ such that $\\langle g\\rangle=(\\mathbb{Z}/p\\mathbb{Z})^{\\times}$. So, $a=g^{k}$, where $1 \\le k \\le p-1$. From our hypothesis, $a^{(p-1)/2} \\equiv g^{k(p-1)/2} \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$. Because the order of $g$ is $p-1$, $p-1|k(p-1)/2.$ But this implies that $2|k$. So $k=2k^{\\prime}$. So, we can write $a \\pmod p$ as $a \\equiv g^{k} \\equiv g^{2k^{\\prime}} \\equiv (g^{k^{\\prime}})^{2} \\pmod p$. Hence $a$ is a square mod $p$, completing the proof.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.1.2}", "question": "Using Wilson's theorem and the congruence $k(p-k) \\equiv -k^{2} \\pmod p$, compute $(-1/p)$ for all primes $p$.", "solution": "The case when $p=2$ is trivial since every odd number is congruent to 1 (mod 2). Then we will assume that $p$ is an odd prime. To begin, we recall Wilson's theorem (proved in Exercise 1.4.10) which states that for any prime $p$, we have $(p-1)! \\equiv -1 \\pmod p$. We note that $(p-1)!$ can be expressed as $(p-1)! = 1 \\cdot 2 \\cdot 3 \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot \\frac{p-1}{2} \\cdot (p-\\frac{p-1}{2}) \\cdot (p-(\\frac{p-1}{2}-1)) \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot (p-1).$ Thus, when we mod out by $p$ on both sides, we get $-1 \\equiv 1 \\cdot 2 \\cdot 3 \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot \\frac{p-1}{2} \\cdot (-\\frac{p-1}{2}) \\cdot (-(\\frac{p-1}{2}-1)) \\cdot\\cdot\\cdot (-1) \\equiv (-1)^{(p-1)/2} [(\\frac{p-1}{2})!]^{2} \\pmod p$.\n\nIf $p \\equiv 1 \\pmod 4$, then it follows that $(p-1)/2=2a$ for some integer $a$. Hence, from the above identity, $(-1)^{(p-1)/2}[(\\frac{p-1}{2})!]^{2} \\equiv [(\\frac{p-1}{2})!]^{2} \\equiv -1 \\pmod p$. So, $-1$ is a quadratic residue mod $p$ if $p \\equiv 1 \\pmod 4$.\n\nIf $p \\equiv 3 \\pmod 4$, we find that $(p-1)/2$ is odd. If $x^{2} \\equiv -1 \\pmod p$, then by Exercise 7.1.1, $(-1)^{(p-1)/2} \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$. But since $p \\equiv 3 \\pmod 4$, we know that $(-1)^{(p-1)/2} \\equiv -1 \\pmod p$. So, there can be no solutions to $x^{2} \\equiv -1 \\pmod p$ if $p \\equiv 3 \\pmod 4$.\n\nThus $(\\frac{-1}{p}) = \\begin{cases} 1 & \\text{if } p \\equiv 1 \\pmod 4, \\\\ -1 & \\text{if } p \\equiv 3 \\pmod 4. \\end{cases}$ Finally, we observe that we can encode this information more compactly as $(\\frac{-1}{p}) = (-1)^{(p-1)/2}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.1.3}", "question": "Show that $a^{(p-1)/2} \\equiv (\\frac{a}{p}) \\pmod p$.", "solution": "If $p|a$, then the conclusion is trivial. So, suppose $p$ does not divide $a$. By Fermat's Little Theorem, $a^{p-1} \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$. We can factor this statement as $a^{p-1}-1 \\equiv (a^{(p-1)/2}-1)(a^{(p-1)/2}+1) \\equiv 0 \\pmod p$. Thus, $a^{(p-1)/2} \\equiv \\pm 1 \\pmod p$. We will consider each case separately.\n\nIf $a^{(p-1)/2} \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$, then by Exercise 7.1.1, there exists a solution to the equation $x^{2} \\equiv a \\pmod p$. But this implies $(a/p)=1$.\n\nIf $a^{(p-1)/2} \\equiv -1 \\pmod p$, then Exercise 7.1.1 tells us there is no solution to the equation $x^{2} \\equiv a \\pmod p$. So, $(a/p)=-1$. We conclude that $a^{(p-1)/2} \\equiv (\\frac{a}{p}) \\pmod p$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.1.4}", "question": "Show that $(\\frac{ab}{p}) = (\\frac{a}{p})(\\frac{b}{p})$.", "solution": "We will use Exercise 7.1.3 to prove this result. Thus, $(\\frac{ab}{p}) \\equiv (ab)^{(p-1)/2} \\pmod p$. Similarly, $(\\frac{a}{p}) \\equiv a^{(p-1)/2} \\pmod p$ and $(\\frac{b}{p}) \\equiv b^{(p-1)/2} \\pmod p$. But then $(\\frac{ab}{p}) \\equiv (ab)^{(p-1)/2} = a^{(p-1)/2}b^{(p-1)/2} \\equiv (\\frac{a}{p})(\\frac{b}{p}) \\pmod p$. Thus $(\\frac{ab}{p}) \\equiv (\\frac{a}{p})(\\frac{b}{p}) \\pmod p$. But because the Legendre symbol only takes on the values $\\pm 1$, we can rewrite this statement as $(\\frac{ab}{p}) = (\\frac{a}{p})(\\frac{b}{p})$ which is what we wished to show.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.1.5}", "question": "If $a \\equiv b \\pmod p$, show that $(\\frac{a}{p}) = (\\frac{b}{p})$.", "solution": "This is clear from the definition of the Legendre symbol. If $a$ is a quadratic residue mod $p$ then so is $b$. The same is true if $a$ is a quadratic nonresidue.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 7.1.6}", "question": "For all odd primes $p$, show that $(\\frac{2}{p}) = \\begin{cases} 1 & \\text{if } p \\equiv \\pm 1 \\pmod 8, \\\\ -1 & \\text{if } p \\equiv 3, 5 \\pmod 8. \\end{cases}$", "solution": "To exhibit this result, we will work in the field $\\mathbb{Q}(i)$, where $i=\\sqrt{-1}.$ Notice that the ring of integers of this field is $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$. We wish to find when there exist solutions to $x^{2} \\equiv 2 \\pmod p$. We will make use of Exercise 7.1.1 which tells us there exists a solution if and only if $2^{(p-1)/2} \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$.\n\nWorking in $\\mathbb{Z}[i]$, we observe that $(1+i)^{2} = 1+2i+i^{2} = 2i$. Also, for $p$ prime, $(1+i)^{p} = 1+\\binom{p}{1}i+\\binom{p}{2}i^{2}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+i^{p}.$ Considering the above equation mod $p\\mathbb{Z}[i]$ we get $(1+i)^{p} \\equiv 1+i^{p} \\pmod{p\\mathbb{Z}[i]}$. But we also observe that $(1+i)^{p} = (1+i)(1+i)^{p-1} = (1+i)((1+i)^{2})^{(p-1)/2} = (1+i)(2i)^{(p-1)/2} = i^{(p-1)/2}(1+i)2^{(p-1)/2}.$ So, $i^{(p-1)/2}(1+i)2^{(p-1)/2} \\equiv 1+i^{p} \\pmod{p\\mathbb{Z}[i]}$.\n\nWe now consider the various possibilities for $p \\pmod 8$.\n\nIf $p \\equiv 1 \\pmod 8$, then $i^{p}=i.$ As well, $i^{(p-1)/2}=1$. So, the equation becomes $(1+i) \\equiv (1+i)2^{(p-1)/2} \\pmod{p\\mathbb{Z}[i]}$, which implies $1 \\equiv 2^{(p-1)/2} \\pmod{p\\mathbb{Z}[i]}$. So, $1 \\equiv 2^{(p-1)/2} \\pmod p$, and thus $(2/p)=1$ by Exercise 7.1.1.\n\nIf $p \\equiv -1 \\pmod 8$, then $i^{p}=-i$. As well, $i^{(p-1)/2}=-i$. So, the equation becomes $(1-i) \\equiv -i(1+i)2^{(p-1)/2} \\pmod{p\\mathbb{Z}[i]}$, which implies $1 \\equiv 2^{(p-1)/2} \\pmod{p\\mathbb{Z}[i]}$. Again, we have $1 \\equiv 2^{(p-1)/2} \\pmod p$, and thus $(2/p)=1$.\n\nIf $p \\equiv 3 \\pmod 8$, then $i^{p}=-i$. Also, $i^{(p-1)/2}=i$. So, the equation becomes $(1-i) \\equiv i(1+i)2^{(p-1)/2} \\pmod{p\\mathbb{Z}[i]}$. So $-i(1+i) \\equiv i(1+i)2^{(p-1)/2} \\pmod{p\\mathbb{Z}[i]}$, which simplifies to $-1 \\equiv 2^{(p-1)/2} \\pmod{p\\mathbb{Z}[i]}$. Since $1 \\not\\equiv 2^{(p-1)/2} \\pmod p$, $(2/p)=-1$.\n\nFinally, if $p \\equiv 5 \\pmod 8$, then $i^{p}=i$. As well, $i^{(p-1)/2}=-1$. From this, it follows that $(1+i) \\equiv -1(1+i)2^{(p-1)/2} \\pmod{p\\mathbb{Z}[i]}$, so $-1 \\equiv 2^{(p-1)/2} \\pmod{p\\mathbb{Z}[i]}$. Hence, $(2/p)=-1$ thus completing the proof.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.1.7}", "question": "Show that the number of quadratic residues mod $p$ is equal to the number of quadratic nonresidues mod $p$.", "solution": "The equation $a^{(p-1)/2} \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$ will have $(p-1)/2$ solutions. This can be deduced from the fact that $(\\mathbb{Z}/p\\mathbb{Z})^{\\times}$ is a cyclic group with some generator $g$, where $g$ is a $(p-1)$-st root of unity. So, for any even power of $g$, i.e., $g^{2k}$, we will have $(g^{2k})^{(p-1)/2} \\equiv (g^{p-1})^{k} \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$. For any odd power, $(g^{2k+1})^{(p-1)/2} \\equiv (g^{(p-1)/2}) \\not\\equiv 1 \\pmod p$. The last congruence holds since $g$ is a $(p-1)$-st root of unity. Thus, half of the elements of $(\\mathbb{Z}/p\\mathbb{Z})^{\\times}$ will correspond to some even power of $g$, and hence, $a^{(p-1)/2} \\equiv 1 \\pmod p$. But this in turn implies that there are $(p-1)/2$ elements such that $(a/p)=1$. Since there are $(p-1)$ residues mod $p$, there are $(p-1)-(p-1)/2=(p-1)/2$ residues that are not squares. But now we have that the number of quadratic residues mod $p$ and the number of quadratic nonresidues mod $p$ are equal.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.1.8}", "question": "Show that $\\sum_{a=1}^{p-1}(\\frac{a}{p})=0$ for any fixed prime $p$.", "solution": "From Exercise 7.1.7, the number of residues equals the number of nonresidues. So, there are $(p-1)/2$ residues, and $(p-1)/2$ nonresidues. Thus $\\sum_{a=1}^{p-1}(\\frac{a}{p})=\\frac{p-1}{2}(1)+\\frac{p-1}{2}(-1)=0.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 7.2.1}", "question": "For $S=\\sum_{a \\pmod p}(\\frac{a}{p})\\zeta_{p}^{a}$, show that $S^{2}=(\\frac{-1}{p})p.$", "solution": "From the definition of a Gauss sum, we have $S^{2}=(\\sum_{a \\pmod p}(\\frac{a}{p})\\zeta_{p}^{a})(\\sum_{b \\pmod p}(\\frac{b}{p})\\zeta_{p}^{b})$. By applying Exercise 7.1.4, we can simplify the above to get $S^{2}=\\sum_{a,b}(\\frac{ab}{p})\\zeta_{p}^{a+b}.$ We now make a substitution by letting $b=ca$, where $(c,p)=1$. Thus, $S^{2}=\\sum_{(a,p)=1}\\sum_{(c,p)=1}(\\frac{a^{2}c}{p})\\zeta_{p}^{a(1+c)}.$ Again, using Exercise 7.1.4, we get $S^{2}=\\sum_{(a,p)=1}\\sum_{(c,p)=1}(\\frac{c}{p})\\zeta_{p}^{a(1+c)} =\\sum_{(c,p)=1}(\\frac{c}{p})(\\sum_{(a,p)=1}\\zeta_{p}^{a(1+c)})$.\n\nObserve that $(1+c,p)=1$ or $(1+c,p)=p.$ Since $(c,p)=1$, the second case will only happen if $c=p-1$. But then, if $(1+c,p)=1$, we will have $\\sum_{(a,p)=1}\\zeta_{p}^{a(1+c)}=\\zeta_{p}^{(1+c)}+\\zeta_{p}^{2(1+c)}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\zeta_{p}^{(p-1)(1+c)}=-1.$ But $(1+c,p)=p$ implies that $\\sum_{(a,p)=1}\\zeta_{p}^{a(1+c)}=1+1^{2}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+1^{p-1}=p-1$.\n\nThus $S^{2}=\\sum_{(c,p)=1}(\\frac{c}{p})(\\sum_{(a,p)=1}\\zeta_{p}^{a(1+c)}) =\\sum_{1\\le c\\le p-2}(\\frac{c}{p})(-1)+(\\frac{p-1}{p})(p-1) =(-1)\\sum_{1\\le c\\le p-2}(\\frac{c}{p})+(\\frac{-1}{p})(p-1).$ But $\\sum_{1\\le c\\le p-2}(\\frac{c}{p})=\\sum_{1\\le c\\le p-1}(\\frac{c}{p})-(\\frac{-1}{p})$. From Exercise 7.1.8, we know that the first term on the right-hand side must be equal to 0. So, $S^{2}=(-1)[-(\\frac{-1}{p})]+(\\frac{-1}{p})(p-1) =(\\frac{-1}{p})+(\\frac{-1}{p})(p-1) =(\\frac{-1}{p})p.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.2.2}", "question": "Show that $S^q \\equiv (\\frac{q}{p})S \\pmod q$, where $q$ and $p$ are odd primes.", "solution": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{q})$, where $\\zeta_{q}$ is a primitive $q$th root of unity. Let $R=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ be its ring of integers. So $S^{q}=[\\sum_{a \\pmod p}(\\frac{a}{p})\\zeta_{p}^{a}]^{q} \\equiv\\sum_{a \\pmod p}(\\frac{a}{p})^{q}\\zeta_{p}^{aq} \\pmod{qR}.$ This follows from the fact that $(x_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+x_{n})^{q}\\equiv x_{1}^{q}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+x_{n}^{q} \\pmod q$. Also, because $q$ is an odd prime, and because $(a/p)$ only takes on the values $\\pm1$, we have $(a/p)^{q}=(a/p)$. Hence $S^{q}\\equiv\\sum_{a \\pmod p}(\\frac{a}{p})\\zeta_{p}^{aq} \\pmod{qR}.$ However, $(\\frac{a}{p})=(\\frac{a}{p})(\\frac{q^{2}}{p})=(\\frac{aq^{2}}{p})$. So, it follows that $S^{q}\\equiv\\sum_{a \\pmod p}(\\frac{aq^{2}}{p})\\zeta_{p}^{aq} \\pmod{qR} \\equiv(\\frac{q}{p})\\sum_{a \\pmod p}(\\frac{aq}{p})\\zeta_{p}^{aq} \\pmod{qR}.$ But as $a$ runs through all the residue classes mod $p$, so will $aq$. Thus, $S^{q}\\equiv(\\frac{q}{p})S \\pmod{qR}.$ From this, it follows that $S^q \\equiv (\\frac{q}{p})S \\pmod q$, completing the proof.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 7.3.1}", "question": "(Law of Quadratic Reciprocity) Let $p$ and $q$ be odd primes. Show that $(\\frac{p}{q})=(\\frac{q}{p})(-1)^{\\frac{p-1}{2}\\cdot\\frac{q-1}{2}}.$", "solution": "From Exercise 7.2.2, we have $S^q \\equiv (\\frac{q}{p})S \\pmod q$. Thus, cancelling out an $S$ from both sides will give us $S^{q-1}\\equiv(\\frac{q}{p}) \\pmod q$. Since $q$ is odd, $q-1$ must be divisible by 2. So $S^{q-1}=(S^{2})^{(q-1)/2}=[p(\\frac{-1}{p})]^{(q-1)/2}$. The last equality follows from Theorem 7.2.1. Thus, $(\\frac{q}{p})\\equiv[p(\\frac{-1}{p})]^{(q-1)/2} \\pmod q.$ From Exercise 7.1.2, $(-1/p)=(-1)^{(p-1)/2}$. We substitute this into the above equation to get $(\\frac{q}{p})\\equiv p^{\\frac{q-1}{2}}(-1)^{\\frac{p-1}{2}\\cdot\\frac{q-1}{2}} \\pmod q.$ Exercise 7.1.3 tells us that $p^{(q-1)/2}\\equiv(p/q) \\pmod q$. So, $(\\frac{q}{p})\\equiv(\\frac{p}{q})(-1)^{\\frac{p-1}{2}\\cdot\\frac{q-1}{2}} \\pmod q$. But both sides only take on the value $\\pm1$, and since $q\\ge3$ the congruence can be replaced by an equals sign. This gives us $(\\frac{p}{q})=(\\frac{q}{p})(-1)^{\\frac{p-1}{2}\\cdot\\frac{q-1}{2}}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.3.2 (a)}", "question": "Let $q$ be an odd prime. Prove that if $q\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$, then $q$ is a quadratic residue mod $p$ if and only if $p\\equiv r \\pmod q$, where $r$ is a quadratic residue mod $q$.", "solution": "We begin by rewriting the result of Theorem 7.3.1 in the following equivalent form: $(\\frac{p}{q})(\\frac{q}{p})=(-1)^{\\frac{p-1}{2}\\cdot\\frac{q-1}{2}}.$ Since $q\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$, $(q-1)/2$ is even, so we will have $(\\frac{p}{q})(\\frac{q}{p})=1.$ From this it follows that either $(p/q)=1=(q/p)$ or $(p/q)=-1=(q/p)$. We can now prove the statement. If $(q/p)=1$, then $(p/q)=1.$ So, by Exercise 7.1.5, $p\\equiv r \\pmod q$, where $r$ is a quadratic residue mod $q$. Suppose $p\\equiv r \\pmod q$, and $(r/q)=1$. But then $(p/q)=(r/q)$, and thus, $(p/q)=1$. Since $(q/p)=(p/q)$ by quadratic reciprocity, we must also have that $(q/p)=1$, which implies that $q$ is a quadratic residue mod $p$. This completes the proof of (a).", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.3.2 (b)}", "question": "Let $q$ be an odd prime. Prove that if $q\\equiv3 \\pmod 4$, then $q$ is a quadratic residue mod $p$ if and only if $p\\equiv\\pm b^{2} \\pmod{4q}$, where $b$ is an odd integer prime to $q$.", "solution": "Suppose $q\\equiv3 \\pmod 4$. Then, quadratic reciprocity gives us $(\\frac{q}{p})=(-1)^{\\frac{p-1}{2}}(\\frac{p}{q})$. Suppose $(q/p)=1$. Then, we have two cases:\nCase 1. $(-1)^{(p-1)/2}=-1$ and $(p/q)=-1$.\nCase 2. $(-1)^{(p-1)/2}=1$ and $(p/q)=1$.\n\nCase 1. First we note that $(-1)^{(p-1)/2}=-1$ implies that $p\\equiv3 \\pmod 4$. Because $q\\equiv3 \\pmod 4$, we have from an earlier exercise that $(\\frac{-1}{q})=-1$. But then, we find that $(p/q)=(\\frac{-1}{q})(\\frac{b^{2}}{q})=(\\frac{-b^{2}}{q})$. Hence $(p/q)=(-b^{2}/q)$, and $p\\equiv-b^{2} \\pmod q$. We can suppose that $b$ is odd. If not, we can replace it with $b^{\\prime}=b+q,$ which is odd. Since $b$ is odd, $b=2n+1$. Thus $b^{2}=4n^{2}+4n+1$, and so $-b^{2}\\equiv3 \\pmod 4$. Since we already deduced that $p\\equiv3 \\pmod 4$, we have $p\\equiv-b^{2} \\pmod 4$. Because $p\\equiv-b^{2} \\pmod q$, we conclude that $p\\equiv-b^{2} \\pmod{4q}$.\n\nCase 2. $(-1)^{(p-1)/2}=1$ implies that $p\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$. Also, $(p/q)=(b^{2}/q)$. Assume $b$ is odd for the same reason given above. So $p\\equiv b^{2} \\pmod q$. Because $b$ is odd, we have $b=2n+1$, which means that $b^{2}\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$. But $p\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$, so clearly $p\\equiv b^{2} \\pmod 4$. Since we also know that $p\\equiv b^{2} \\pmod q$, we conclude that $p\\equiv b^{2} \\pmod{4q}$.\n\nSuppose we have $p\\equiv\\pm b^{2} \\pmod{4q}$, where $b$ is coprime to $q$. We will examine each case, $p\\equiv b^{2} \\pmod{4q}$ and $p\\equiv-b^{2} \\pmod{4q}$ separately.\n\nIf $p\\equiv b^{2} \\pmod{4q}$, we have $p\\equiv b^{2}\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$, and $p\\equiv b^{2} \\pmod q$. But $p\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$ implies that $(-1)^{(p-1)/2}=1$. Since $p\\equiv b^{2} \\pmod q$ it follows that $(\\frac{p}{q})=1=(\\frac{b^{2}}{q})$. Hence $(\\frac{q}{p})=(-1)^{\\frac{p-1}{2}}(\\frac{p}{q})=1\\cdot1=1,$ so $q$ is a quadratic residue mod $p$.\n\nIf $p\\equiv-b^{2} \\pmod{4q}$, we have both that $p\\equiv-b^{2}\\equiv3 \\pmod 4$, and $p\\equiv-b^{2} \\pmod q$. So, $(-1)^{(p-1)/2}=-1$ from the fact that $p\\equiv3 \\pmod 4$. From $p\\equiv-b^{2} \\pmod q$, we deduce that $(\\frac{p}{q})=(\\frac{-b^{2}}{q})=(\\frac{-1}{q})(\\frac{b^{2}}{q})=(\\frac{-1}{q})$. Since $q\\equiv3 \\pmod 4$, we know that $(-1/q)=-1.$ So, $(p/q)=-1.$ Thus, $(\\frac{q}{p})=(-1)^{(p-1)/2}(\\frac{p}{q})=(-1)(-1)=1.$ It now follows that $q$ is a quadratic residue mod $p$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.3.3}", "question": "Compute $(\\frac{5}{p})$ and $(\\frac{7}{p})$.", "solution": "We will first compute $(5/p)$. Since $5\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$, we can use part (a) of Exercise 7.3.2. So $(5/p)=1$ if and only if $p\\equiv r \\pmod 5$, where $r$ is a quadratic residue mod 5. It is easy to determine which $r$ are quadratic residues mod 5; $1^{2}\\equiv1$, $2^{2}\\equiv4$, $3^{2}\\equiv4$, $4^{2}\\equiv1$. So, 1 and 4 are quadratic residues mod 5, while 2 and 3 are not. Thus $(\\frac{5}{p})=\\begin{cases} 1 & \\text{if } p\\equiv 1,4 \\pmod 5, \\\\ -1 & \\text{if } p\\equiv 2,3 \\pmod 5, \\\\ 0 & \\text{if } p=5. \\end{cases}$\n\nNow, we will find $(7/p)$. Since $7\\equiv3 \\pmod 4$, we must use part (b) of Exercise 7.3.2. So, we have to compute all the residues mod 28 of all the squares of odd integers prime to 7. Some calculation reveals that $1^{2}, 13^{2}, 15^{2}, 27^{2}\\equiv1 \\pmod{28}$, $3^{2}, 11^{2}, 17^{2}, 25^{2}\\equiv9 \\pmod{28}$, and $5^{2}, 9^{2}, 17^{2}?, 23^{2}\\equiv25 \\pmod{28}$. [Note: 19^2 = 361 = 12*28 + 25. 9^2=81=2*28+25. 23^2=529=18*28+25]. Thus $(\\frac{7}{p})=\\begin{cases} 1 & \\text{if } p\\equiv\\pm1,\\pm9,\\pm25 \\pmod{28}, \\\\ -1 & \\text{if } p\\equiv\\pm5,\\pm11,\\pm13 \\pmod{28}, \\\\ 0 & \\text{if } p=7. \\end{cases}$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.4.1 (a)}", "question": "Find the discriminant of $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})$ when $d\\equiv2,3 \\pmod 4$.", "solution": "If $d\\equiv2,3 \\pmod 4$, then $\\omega_{1}=1$, $\\omega_{2}=\\sqrt{d}$ forms an integral basis for $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Then an easy calculation shows that $d_{K}=4d.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.4.1 (b)}", "question": "Find the discriminant of $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})$ when $d\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$.", "solution": "For $d\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$, then $\\omega_{1}=1$, $\\omega_{2}=(1+\\sqrt{d})/2$ forms an integral basis. Then $d_{K}=d$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 7.4.2}", "question": "Assume $p$ is an odd prime. Show that $(d/p)=1$ if and only if $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}^{\\prime}$ where $\\mathfrak{p}\\ne\\mathfrak{p}^{\\prime}$, and $\\mathfrak{p}$ prime.", "solution": "From our assumption, we have $a^{2}\\equiv d \\pmod p$ for some $a$. Let $\\mathfrak{p}=(p,a+\\sqrt{d})$ and $\\mathfrak{p}^{\\prime}=(p,a-\\sqrt{d})$. We claim that $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}^{\\prime}$.\n$\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}^{\\prime}=(p,a+\\sqrt{d})(p,a-\\sqrt{d}) = (p^{2},p(a+\\sqrt{d}),p(a-\\sqrt{d}),a^{2}-d) = (p)(p,a+\\sqrt{d},a-\\sqrt{d},(a^{2}-d)/p) = (p)$. The last equality holds because $2a$ and $p$ are both elements of the second ideal. But $(2a,p)=1$. From this, it follows that $1\\in(p,a+\\sqrt{d},a-\\sqrt{d}, (a^{2}-d)/p)$. It is clear that $\\mathfrak{p}\\ne\\mathfrak{p}^{\\prime}$ because if they were equal, then $2a$ and $p$ would be in $\\mathfrak{p}$, from which it follows that $\\mathfrak{p}=\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ which is false. Since the norm of $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ is $p^{2}$, $N(\\mathfrak{p})$ must divide $p^{2}$. Since $\\mathfrak{p}\\ne(1)$, $N(\\mathfrak{p})\\ne1$. Also, it cannot be $p^{2}$ because then $N(\\mathfrak{p}^{\\prime})=1$, which is false. So, both $\\mathfrak{p}$ and $\\mathfrak{p}^{\\prime}$ have norm $p$, and thus, they must be prime.\n\nIn the comments after Exercise 7.4.1 we noted that $\\{1,(m+\\sqrt{m})/2\\}$ always forms an integral basis of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ where $m=d$ if $d\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$ and $m=4d$ if $d\\equiv2,3 \\pmod 4$. Since $\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}^{\\prime}=p\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ there must exist $a\\in\\mathfrak{p}$, but $a\\notin p\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. So, $a=x+y(m+\\sqrt{m})/2$, where $x, y\\in\\mathbb{Z},$ but $p$ does not divide both $x$ and $y$. Now, consider $a\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ the ideal generated by $a$. We can write $a\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{q}, \\mathfrak{q}\\subseteq\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Now, taking the norms of both sides, we discover that $N(\\mathfrak{p})=p$ must divide $N(a\\mathcal{O}_{K})=|(x+\\frac{ym}{2})^{2}-\\frac{y^{2}m}{4}|.$ So, $(2x+ym)^{2}\\equiv y^{2}m \\pmod p$. If $p|y$ then $p|(2x+ym)^{2}$. But then $p|2x$, and since $p$ is odd, $p|x$. This contradicts the fact that $p$ did not divide both $x$ and $y$. So $p$ does not divide $y$, and since $\\mathbb{Z}/p\\mathbb{Z}$ is a field, $\\frac{(2x+ym)^{2}}{y^{2}}\\equiv m \\pmod p$. But then we have found some $z$ such that $z^{2}\\equiv m \\pmod p$. Since $m=d$ or $m=4d,$ then $(d/p)=1$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.4.3}", "question": "Assume that $p$ is an odd prime. Show that $(d/p)=0$ if and only if $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathfrak{p}^{2}$, where $\\mathfrak{p}$ is prime.", "solution": "We claim that $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}=(p,\\sqrt{d})^{2}$. Notice that $(p,\\sqrt{d})^{2}=(p^{2},p\\sqrt{d},d)=(p)(p,\\sqrt{d},d/p).$ Because $d$ is squarefree, $d/p$ and $p$ are relatively prime. So, $(p,\\sqrt{d},d/p)=1.$ Since $(p,\\sqrt{d})$ is a prime ideal (for the same reason given above), we have shown that $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ ramifies.\n\nOnce again, let $m$ be the discriminant of $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})$. Since $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ ramifies we can find some $a\\in\\mathfrak{p}$, but $a\\notin p\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. So, $a=x+y(m+\\sqrt{m})/2$. Since $a^{2}\\in p\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, we get $\\frac{(2x+ym)^{2}+my^{2}}{4}+2y\\frac{(2x+ym)}{4}\\sqrt{m}\\in p\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Thus, $p|(2x+ym)^{2}+my^{2}$ and $p|y(2x+ym)$. If $p|y$, then $p|2x$. Since $p$ is odd, $p|x$. But then $a\\in p\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. This is a contradiction. So, $p|(2x+ym)$ and $p|my^{2}$. Thus, $p|m$. But this means that $(d/p)=0$, since $p$ is an odd prime.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.4.4}", "question": "Assume $p$ is an odd prime. Then $(d/p)=-1$ if and only if $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathfrak{p}$, where $\\mathfrak{p}$ is prime.", "solution": "This follows immediately from Theorem 7.4.3 [Note: Reference should be 7.4.2] and Exercise 7.4.3. If $(d/p)=-1$ then we know that $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ does not split, nor does it ramify. So $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ must stay inert. Conversely, if $p\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ is inert, the only possible value for $(d/p)$ is -1.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 7.4.5 (a)}", "question": "Suppose $p=2$. Show that $2\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathfrak{p}^{2}$, $\\mathfrak{p}$ prime if and only if $2|d_{K}$.", "solution": "If $2|d_{K}$, then $d\\equiv2,3 \\pmod 4$. If $d\\equiv2 \\pmod 4$, then we claim that $(2)=(2,\\sqrt{d})^{2}.$ Note that $(2,\\sqrt{d})^{2}=(4,2\\sqrt{d},d)=(2)(2,\\sqrt{d},d/2)$. Since $d$ is squarefree, then 2 and $d/2$ are relatively prime and thus the second ideal above is actually $\\mathcal{O}_{K}.$ So $(2)=(2,\\sqrt{d})^{2}$.\n\nIf $d\\equiv3 \\pmod 4$ we claim that $(2)=(2,1+\\sqrt{d})^{2}$, since $(2,1+\\sqrt{d})^{2}=(4,2+2\\sqrt{d},1+d+2\\sqrt{d})=(2)(2,1+\\sqrt{d},\\frac{1+d}{2}+\\sqrt{d})$. Now we note that $1+\\sqrt{d}$ and $(1+d)/2+\\sqrt{d}$ are relatively prime, and so the second ideal is $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$.\n\nWe consider $d_{K}$, which we know is congruent to either 0 or 1 mod 4. Suppose that $d_{K}\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$. Then $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ is generated as a Z-module by $1, (1+\\sqrt{d})/2$. There must exist some element $a$ in $\\mathfrak{p}$ which is not in $\\mathfrak{p}^{2}.$ So $a=m+n(1+\\sqrt{d})/2$ where we can assume that $m$ and $n$ are either 0 or 1, since for any $\\alpha\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, $a+2\\alpha$ is in $\\mathfrak{p}$ but not in $\\mathfrak{p}^{2}$. Now, if $n=0$, then $m\\ne0$ because otherwise $a=0$ and is obviously in (2). But if $m=1$, then $a=1$ and $a\\notin\\mathfrak{p}$. So, $n=1$ and $m=0$ or 1. We know that $a^{2}\\in(2)$, and $a^{2}=(m+\\frac{1+\\sqrt{d}}{2})^{2} =m^{2}+\\frac{d-1}{4}+(2m+1)\\frac{1+\\sqrt{d}}{2}\\in(2).$ But $2m+1$ is odd and so $a^{2}\\notin(2)$ and we have arrived at a contradiction. We conclude that $d_{K}\\equiv0 \\pmod 4$, and so clearly $2|d_{K}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 7.4.5 (b)}", "question": "Suppose $p=2$. Show that $2\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}^{\\prime}$, $\\mathfrak{p}$ prime if and only if $d\\equiv1 \\pmod 8$ and $2 \\nmid d_{K}$.", "solution": "Suppose that $d\\equiv1 \\pmod 8$. Then clearly from the previous problem $2 \\nmid d_{K}$. We claim that $(2)=(2,(1+\\sqrt{d})/2)(2,(1-\\sqrt{d})/2)$. Note that $(2,\\frac{1+\\sqrt{d}}{2})(2,\\frac{1-\\sqrt{d}}{2})=(2)(2,\\frac{1+\\sqrt{d}}{2},\\frac{1-\\sqrt{d}}{2},\\frac{1-d}{8})$. But the second ideal is just $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ since it contains $1=(1+\\sqrt{d})/2+(1-\\sqrt{d})/2$.\n\nNow suppose that (2) splits in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. We know from part (a) that $d\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$. If $(2)=\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}^{\\prime}$, then $N(\\mathfrak{p})=2$. There exists an element $a$ which is in $\\mathfrak{p}$ but not in $\\mathfrak{p}\\mathfrak{p}^{\\prime}=(2)$. Then $a=m+n(1+\\sqrt{d})/2$ where not both $m, n$ are even. Therefore 2 divides the norm of the ideal generated by $a$, and $N((a))=|N(a)|=|\\frac{(2m+n)^{2}}{4}-\\frac{n^{2}d}{4}|$. So $(2m+n)^{2}\\equiv n^{2}d \\pmod 8$. We know that $2 \\nmid d$. So suppose that $n$ is even, and further suppose that $n=2n_{1}$ where $n_{1}$ is odd. Then $2 | (m+n_{1})^{2}+n_{1}^{2}d,$ and since $2|n_{1}^{2}d$ then $2 \\nmid (m+n_{1})^{2}$, which implies that $m$ is even. But we assumed that not both $m$ and $n$ were even. Now suppose that $4|n$. Then $4|(2m+n)$ and so $m$ is even, a contradiction. Then $n$ must be odd, and we can find an integer $n_{2}$ such that $nn_{2}\\equiv1 \\pmod 8$. Then $d\\equiv n_{2}^{2}(2m+n)^{2} \\pmod 8$, and since $2 \\nmid d$, we conclude $n_{2}(2m+n)$ is odd, and $d\\equiv1 \\pmod 8$, as desired.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 7.4.5 (c)}", "question": "Suppose $p=2$. Show that $2\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathfrak{p}$, $\\mathfrak{p}$ prime if and only if $d\\equiv5 \\pmod 8$ and $2 \\nmid d_{K}$.", "solution": "Just as in Exercise 7.4.4, this follows directly from parts (a) and (b), since if $2 \\nmid d_{K}$ and $d\\not\\equiv1 \\pmod 8$, then $d\\equiv5 \\pmod 8$. We know that (2) cannot split or ramify in this case, so it must remain inert.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.5.1}", "question": "Show that there are infinitely many primes of the form $4k+1$.", "solution": "Suppose there are only a finite number of primes of this form. Let $p_{1},p_{2},...,p_{n}$ be these primes. Let $d=(2p_{1}p_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{n})^{2}+1$. Let $p$ be a prime that divides this number. So $d\\equiv0 \\pmod p$, which implies that $(-1/p)=1$. From Exercise 7.1.2, we know that this only occurs if $p\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$. So, $p\\in\\{p_{1},p_{2},...,p_{n}\\}$. But for any $p_{i}\\in\\{p_{1},p_{2},...,p_{n}\\}$, $p_{i}$ does not divide $d$ by construction. So $p\\notin\\{p_{1},p_{2},...,p_{n}\\}$. Thus, our assumption is incorrect, and so, there must exist an infinite number of primes of the form $4k+1$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.5.2}", "question": "Show that there are infinitely many primes of the form $8k+7$.", "solution": "Suppose the statement is false, that is, there exist only a finite number of primes of the form $8k+7$. Let $p_{1},p_{2},...,p_{n}$ be these primes. Construct the following integer, $d=(4p_{1}p_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{n})^{2}-2$. Let $p$ be any prime that divides this number. But then $(4p_{1}p_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{n})^{2}\\equiv2 \\pmod p$, so $(2/p)=1$. From Theorem 7.1.6, we can deduce that $p\\equiv\\pm1 \\pmod 8$. We claim that all the odd primes that divide $d$ cannot have the form $8k+1$. We observe that $d = (4p_{1}p_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{n})^{2}-2$. So, any odd prime that divides $d$ must divide $8(p_{1}p_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{n})^{2}-1$. If all primes were of the form $8k+1$, we would have $8(p_{1}p_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{n})^{2}-1=(8k_{1}+1)^{e_{1}}\\cdot(8k_{2}+1)^{e_{2}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot(8k_{m}+1)^{e_{m}}$. But now consider this equation mod 8. We find that $-1\\equiv1 \\pmod 8$, which is clearly false. So, there must be at least one odd prime $p$ of the form $8k+7$ that divides $d$. So, $p\\in\\{p_{1},p_{2},...,p_{n}\\}$. But $p$ cannot be in $\\{p_{1},p_{2},...,p_{n}\\}$ since every $p_{i}$ leaves a remainder of -2 when dividing $d$. So, $\\{p_{1},p_{2},...,p_{n}\\}$ does not contain all the primes of the form $8k+7$. But we assumed that it did. We have arrived at a contradiction. Therefore, there must be an infinite number of primes of the form $8k+7$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.5.3}", "question": "Show that $p\\equiv4 \\pmod 5$ for infinitely many primes $p$.", "solution": "From the preceding comments, we know that we can use a Euclid-type proof to prove this assertion since $4^{2}\\equiv1 \\pmod 5$. So, suppose there exists only a finite number of such primes, say $p_{1},p_{2},...,p_{n}$. Consider the integer $25(p_{1}p_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{n})^{2}-5$. Then for any prime divisor not equal to 5, we will have $(5/p)=1$. From Exercise 7.3.3, we know that this will only occur if $p\\equiv1,4 \\pmod 5$. Since $p\\ne5$, then $p|5(p_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{n})^{2}-1$. So, all the prime divisors cannot be congruent to 1 (mod 5), because if this was true, $-1\\equiv1 \\pmod 5$ which is clearly false. So, there is some $p\\equiv4 \\pmod 5$ that divides $5(p_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{n})^{2}-1$. But $p$ is not any of the $p_{1},...,p_{n}$ since none of these numbers divide $5(p_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{n})^{2}-1$. This gives us a contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Example 7.5.4}", "question": "Show there are an infinite number of primes in the arithmetic progession $15k+4$.", "solution": "Since $4^{2}\\equiv1 \\pmod{15}$, we can use a Euclid-type proof. We will start with a couple of observations about the polynomial $f(x)=x^{4}-x^{3}+2x^{2}+x+1$. First, we note that it can be factored in the following three ways:\n(7.2) $f(x)=(x^{2}-\\frac{x}{2}-1)^{2}+\\frac{15}{4}x^{2},$\n(7.3) $f(x)=(-x^{2}+\\frac{x}{2}-\\frac{1}{2})^2 - \\frac{3}{4}(x+1)^2$\n(7.4) $f(x)=(-x^{2}+\\frac{x}{2}-\\frac{3}{2})^2 - \\frac{5}{4}(x-1)^{2}$\n\nWe note by (7.2) that if $p$ divides $f(x)$, then 15 is a quadratic residue mod $p$. By quadratic reciprocity, $(\\frac{p}{3})(\\frac{p}{5})=1.$ So, there will be a solution only if $(p/3)=1$ and $(p/5)=1$ or if they both equal -1. The first case will happen if $p\\equiv1 \\pmod 3$ and $p\\equiv1,4 \\pmod 5$. The second happens if $p\\equiv2 \\pmod 3$ and $p\\equiv2,3 \\pmod 5$. So, $(\\frac{p}{15})=1$ if $p\\equiv1,2,4,8 \\pmod{15}$, and $-1$ if $p\\equiv7,11,13 \\pmod{15}$.\n\nFrom equation (7.3), we see that $(-3/p)=1$. Using Exercise 7.3.2, $(\\frac{3}{p})=1$ if $p\\equiv1,11 \\pmod{12}$, and $-1$ if $p\\equiv5,7 \\pmod{12}$. So, since we already know what $(-1/p)$ is, we find that $(\\frac{-3}{p})=1$ if $p\\equiv1,7 \\pmod{12}$, and $-1$ if $p\\equiv5,11 \\pmod{12}$.\n\nFinally, equation (7.4) tells us that $(5/p)=1$. But we know this only happens when $p\\equiv1,4 \\pmod 5$. When we combine all these results, we find that any prime divisor of $f(x)$ must be congruent to either 1 (mod 15) or 4 (mod 15). We can now begin the Euclid-type proof. Suppose that there were only a finite number of primes such that $p\\equiv4 \\pmod{15}$. Let $p_{1},...,p_{n}$ be these primes. We now consider the integer $d=f(15p_{1}p_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{n}+1).$ From what we have just said, $d$ is divisible by some prime $p$ such that $p\\equiv1,4 \\pmod 5$. Not all the prime divisors have the form $p\\equiv1 \\pmod 5$. This follows from the fact that $d=f(15p_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{n}+1)=15p_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{n}g(p_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{n})+4$ where $g(x)$ is some polynomial. So, there is a divisor $p$ such that $p\\equiv4 \\pmod{15}$. But $p$ cannot be in $p_{1},p_{2},...,p_{n}$ because when they divide $d$, they leave a remainder of 4. This gives us the needed contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.1}", "question": "Compute $(11/p)$.", "solution": "Since $11\\equiv3 \\pmod 4$, we use Exercise 7.3.2 (b) which says that 11 is a quadratic residue mod $p$ if and only if $p\\equiv\\pm b^{2} \\pmod{44}$ where $b$ is an odd integer prime to $p$. If we compute $b^{2} \\pmod{44}$ for all possible $b$, we get $1^{2}, 21^{2}, 23^{2}, 43^{2} \\equiv 1 \\pmod{44}$, $3^{2}, 19^{2}, 25^{2}, 41^{2} \\equiv 9 \\pmod{44}$, $5^{2}, 17^{2}, 27^{2}, 39^{2} \\equiv 25 \\pmod{44}$, $7^{2}, 15^{2}, 29^{2}, 37^{2} \\equiv 5 \\pmod{44}$, $9^{2}, 13^{2}, 31^{2}, 35^{2} \\equiv 37 \\pmod{44}$. It is now easy to determine the primes for which 11 is a quadratic residue by applying Exercise 7.3.2.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.3}", "question": "If $p\\equiv1 \\pmod 3$, prove that there are integers $a, b$ such that $p=a^{2}-ab+b^{2}$.", "solution": "Let $\\rho=(1+\\sqrt{-3})/2$ and consider $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-3})$. The ring of integers of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-3})$ is $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$. Since $p\\equiv1 \\pmod 3$, $x^{2}+3\\equiv0 \\pmod p$ has a solution. Hence $p$ splits in $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$. Now use the fact that $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$ is Euclidean.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.4}", "question": "If $p\\equiv\\pm1 \\pmod 8$, show that there are integers $a, b$ such that $a^{2}-2b^{2}=\\pm p$.", "solution": "Consider the Euclidean ring $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{2}]$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.5}", "question": "If $p\\equiv\\pm1 \\pmod 5$, show that there are integers $a, b$ such that $a^{2}+ab-b^{2}=\\pm p.$", "solution": "Let $\\omega=(1+\\sqrt{5})/2$ and consider $\\mathbb{Z}[\\omega]$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.10}", "question": "Show that the number of solutions of the congruence $x^{2}+y^{2}\\equiv1 \\pmod p$, $0<x<p$, $0<y<p$ ($p$ an odd prime), is even if and only if $p\\equiv\\pm3 \\pmod 8$.", "solution": "Pair up the solutions, $(x, y)$ with $(y, x)$. The number of solutions is even unless $(x, x)$ is a solution which means that 2 is a square mod $p$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.11}", "question": "If $p$ is a prime such that $p-1=4q$ with $q$ prime, show that 2 is a primitive root mod $p$.", "solution": "The only possible orders of 2 (mod $p$) are 1, 2, 4, $q$, $2q$, or $4q$. Since $p>q$ the orders 1, 2, 4 are impossible. If the order is $q$ or $2q$, then 2 is a quadratic residue mod $p$. However, $p\\equiv5 \\pmod 8$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.12}", "question": "(The Jacobi Symbol) Let $Q$ be a positive odd number. We can write $Q=q_{1}q_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot q_{s}$ where the $q_{i}$ are odd primes, not necessarily distinct. Define the Jacobi symbol $(\\frac{a}{Q})=\\prod_{j=1}^{s}(\\frac{a}{q_{i}})$. If $Q$ and $Q^{\\prime}$ are odd and positive, show that:\n(a) $(a/Q)(a/Q^{\\prime})=(a/QQ^{\\prime})$\n(b) $(a/Q)(a^{\\prime}/Q)=(aa^{\\prime}/Q)$.\n(c) $(a/Q)=(a^{\\prime}/Q)$ if $a\\equiv a^{\\prime} \\pmod Q$.", "solution": "All of these are evident from the properties of the Legendre symbol. For (c), note that $a\\equiv a^{\\prime} \\pmod Q$ implies $a\\equiv a^{\\prime} \\pmod{q_i}$ for $i=1,2,...,s.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.13}", "question": "If $Q$ is odd and positive, show that $(\\frac{-1}{Q})=(-1)^{(Q-1)/2}.$", "solution": "$(\\frac{-1}{Q})=\\prod_{j=1}^{s}(\\frac{-1}{q_{j}})=\\prod_{j=1}^{s}(-1)^{(q_{j}-1)/2}=(-1)^{\\sum_{j=1}^{s}(q_{j}-1)/2}.$ Now, if $a$ and $b$ are odd, observe that $\\frac{ab-1}{2}-(\\frac{a-1}{2}+\\frac{b-1}{2})=\\frac{(a-1)(b-1)}{2}\\equiv0 \\pmod 2$. Hence $\\frac{a-1}{2}+\\frac{b-1}{2} \\equiv \\frac{ab-1}{2} \\pmod 2$. Applying this observation repeatedly in our context gives $(\\frac{-1}{Q})=(-1)^{(Q-1)/2}.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.14}", "question": "If $Q$ is odd and positive, show that $(2/Q)=(-1)^{(Q^{2}-1)/8}$.", "solution": "If $a$ and $b$ are odd, then $\\frac{a^{2}b^{2}-1}{8}-(\\frac{a^{2}-1}{8}+\\frac{b^{2}-1}{8})=\\frac{(a^{2}-1)(b^{2}-1)}{8}\\equiv0 \\pmod 8$. so we have $\\frac{a^{2}-1}{8}+\\frac{b^{2}-1}{8} \\equiv \\frac{a^{2}b^{2}-1}{8} \\pmod 8$. Again applying this repeatedly in our context gives the result.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.15}", "question": "(Reciprocity Law for the Jacobi Symbol) If $P$ and $Q$ are odd, positive, and coprime, show that $(\\frac{P}{Q})(\\frac{Q}{P})=(-1)^{\\frac{P-1}{2}\\cdot\\frac{Q-1}{2}}$", "solution": "Write $P=\\prod_{i=1}^{r}p_{i}$ and $Q=\\prod_{j=1}^{s}q_{j}$. Then $(\\frac{P}{Q})=\\prod_{j=1}^{s}(\\frac{P}{q_{j}})=\\prod_{j=1}^{s}\\prod_{i=1}^{r}(\\frac{p_{i}}{q_{j}}) =\\prod_{j=1}^{s}\\prod_{i=1}^{r}(\\frac{q_{j}}{p_{i}})(-1)^{\\frac{p_{i}-1}{2}\\cdot\\frac{q_{j}-1}{2}} =(\\frac{Q}{P})(-1)^{\\sum_{i,j}\\frac{p_{i}-1}{2}\\cdot\\frac{q_{j}-1}{2}}$ by the reciprocity law for the Legendre symbol. But, as noted in the previous exercises, $\\sum_{i=1}^{r}\\frac{p_{i}-1}{2} \\equiv \\frac{P-1}{2} \\pmod 2$ and $\\sum_{j=1}^{s}\\frac{q_{j}-1}{2}\\equiv\\frac{Q-1}{2} \\pmod 2,$ which completes the proof.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.16}", "question": "(The Kronecker Symbol) We can define $(a/n)$ for any integer $a\\equiv0$ or 1 (mod 4), as follows. Define $(\\frac{a}{2})=(\\frac{a}{-2})=\\begin{cases}0&if~a\\equiv0~(mod~4),\\\\ 1~if~a\\equiv1~(mod~8),\\\\ -1~if~a\\equiv5~(mod~8).\\end{cases}$ For general $n$, write $n=2^{c}n_{1}$, with $n_{1}$ odd, and define $(\\frac{a}{n})=(\\frac{a}{2})^{c}(\\frac{a}{n_{1}})$ where $(a/2)$ is defined as above and $(a/n_{1})$ is the Jacobi symbol. Show that if $d$ is the discriminant of a quadratic field, and $n, m$ are positive integers, then $(\\frac{d}{n})=(\\frac{d}{m})$ for $n\\equiv m \\pmod d$ and $(\\frac{d}{n})=(\\frac{d}{m})sgn~d$ for $n\\equiv-m \\pmod d$.", "solution": "Let $d=2^{a}d^{\\prime}$, $n=2^{b}n^{\\prime}$, $m=2^{c}m^{\\prime}$ with $d^{\\prime}$, $n^{\\prime}.$ $m^{\\prime}$ odd. If $a>0$, the case $b>0$ is trivial since then $c>0$ and both the symbols are zero. So suppose $b=c=0$. Then $(\\frac{d}{n})=(\\frac{2^{a}d^{\\prime}}{n})=(\\frac{2}{n})^{a}(\\frac{d^{\\prime}}{n})=(-1)^{a(n^{2}-1)/8}(\\frac{n}{d^{\\prime}})(-1)^{(n-1)(d^{\\prime}-1)/4}$ and similarly $(\\frac{d}{m})=(\\frac{2^{a}d^{\\prime}}{m})=(-1)^{a(m^{2}-1)/8}(\\frac{m}{d^{\\prime}})(-1)^{(m-1)(d^{\\prime}-1)/2}.$ Since $4|d$, the first factors coincide for $m$ and $n$. The same is true for the other factors in the case $n\\equiv m \\pmod d$. But if $n\\equiv-m \\pmod d$, they differ by sgn $d'$ which is sgn $d$. In the case $a=0$, we note $d\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$. Then $(\\frac{d}{n})=(\\frac{d}{2^{b}n^{\\prime}})=(\\frac{d}{2})^{b}(\\frac{d}{n^{\\prime}})=(\\frac{2}{d})^{b}(\\frac{d}{n^{\\prime}})$ since $(d/2)=(2/d)$ for $d\\equiv1 \\pmod 4$. Thus $(d/n)=(n/d)$ and $(-1/d)=$ sgn $d$. Therefore $(\\frac{d}{m})=(\\frac{d}{n})$ for $m, n>0$, $m\\equiv n \\pmod d$ and $(\\frac{d}{n})=(\\frac{n}{d})=(\\frac{-m}{d})=sgn~d(\\frac{m}{d})=(\\frac{d}{m})sgn~d$ for $n\\equiv-m \\pmod d$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.17}", "question": "If $p$ is an odd prime show that the least positive quadratic nonresidue is less than $\\sqrt{p}+1$.", "solution": "Let $n$ be the least positive quadratic nonresidue and $m$ the least such that $mn>p$ so that $n(m-1)\\le p$. Since $p$ is prime, $n(m-1)<p<mn$. Now $mn-p<n$ so that $1=(\\frac{mn-p}{p})=(\\frac{mn}{p})=-(\\frac{m}{p})$. Therefore $m\\ge n$, so that $(n-1)^{2}<n(n-1)<p.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.18}", "question": "Show that $x^{4}\\equiv25 \\pmod{1013}$ has no solution.", "solution": "First observe that 1013 is prime. If $x^{4}\\equiv25 \\pmod{1013}$ had a solution $x_{0}$, then $x_{0}^{2}\\equiv\\pm5 \\pmod{1013}$. However, $(\\frac{\\pm5}{1013})=(\\frac{5}{1013})=(\\frac{1013}{5})=(\\frac{3}{5})=-1$ so the congruence has no solutions.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.19}", "question": "Show that $x^{4}\\equiv25 \\pmod p$ has no solution if $p$ is a prime congruent to 13 or 17 (mod 20).", "solution": "If the congruence has a solution, then $1=(\\frac{\\pm5}{p})=(\\frac{5}{p})=(\\frac{p}{5})=(\\frac{\\pm3}{5})=-1,$ a contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.20}", "question": "If $p$ is a prime congruent to 13 or 17 (mod 20), show that $x^{4}+py^{4}=25z^{4}$ has no solutions in integers.", "solution": "We may suppose that $gcd(x,y,z)=1$ because otherwise we can cancel the common factor. Also $gcd(p,z)=1$ for otherwise $p|x$ and $p|y$. Now reduce the equation mod $p$. We have a solution to $x^{4}\\equiv25z^{4} \\pmod p$ so that by the previous question, $1=(\\frac{\\pm5z^{2}}{p})=(\\frac{\\pm5}{p})=-1,$ a contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.21}", "question": "Compute the class number of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{33})$.", "solution": "The discriminant is 33 and the Minkowski bound is $\\frac{1}{2}\\sqrt{33}=2.87...$ Since $33\\equiv1 \\pmod 8$, 2 splits as a product of two ideals each of norm 2. Moreover, $2=\\frac{\\sqrt{33}-5}{2}\\cdot\\frac{\\sqrt{33}+5}{2}$ and so the principal ideals $(\\frac{\\sqrt{33}-5}{2})$ and $(\\frac{\\sqrt{33}+5}{2})$ are the only ones of norm 2. Hence the class number is 1.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.22}", "question": "Compute the class number of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{21})$.", "solution": "The discriminant is 21 and the Minkowski bound is 2.29.... However, $21\\equiv5 \\pmod 8$ so that 2 is inert in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{21})$. Therefore, there are no ideals of norm 2 and the class number is 1.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.23}", "question": "Show that $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-11})$ has class number 1.", "solution": "The field has discriminant -11 and Minkowski's bound is $\\frac{2}{\\pi}\\sqrt{11}=2.11.....$ We must examine ideals of norm 2. Since $-11\\equiv5 \\pmod 8$, by Theorem 7.4.5, 2 is inert in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-11})$ so that there are no ideals of norm 2. Hence the class number is 1.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.24}", "question": "Show that $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-15})$ has class number 2.", "solution": "The field has discriminant -15 and Minkowski's bound is $\\frac{2}{\\pi}\\sqrt{15}=2.26.....$ $-15\\equiv1 \\pmod 8$, by Theorem 7.4.5, 2 splits as a product of two ideals, $\\mathfrak{p}$ and $\\mathfrak{p}'$, each of norm 2. If $\\mathfrak{p}$ were principal, then $\\mathfrak{p}=(\\frac{u+v\\sqrt{-15}}{2})$ for integers $u, v$. However, $8=u^{2}+15v^{2}$ has no solution. Thus $\\mathfrak{p}$ is not principal and the class number is 2.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 7.6.25}", "question": "Show that $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-31})$ has class number 3.", "solution": "The discriminant is -31 [Text says 31, but context of imaginary field implies -31] and the Minkowski bound is $\\frac{2}{\\pi}\\sqrt{31}=3.26....$ So we must consider ideals of norm less than or equal to 3. Since $-31\\equiv1 \\pmod 8$, 2 splits as $\\mathfrak{p}_{2}\\cdot\\mathfrak{p}_{2}^{\\prime}$ (say). Since $(\\frac{-31}{3})=-1,$ 3 is inert so there are no ideals of norm 3. Moreover, neither $\\mathfrak{p}_2$ or $\\mathfrak{p}_{2}^{\\prime}$ are principal since we cannot solve $8=u^{2}+31v^{2}$. Since $8=\\frac{1^{2}+(31)\\cdot1^{2}}{4}=(\\frac{1-\\sqrt{-31}}{2})(\\frac{1+\\sqrt{-31}}{2})$ and $((1-\\sqrt{-31})/2)$ $((1+\\sqrt{-31})/2)$ are coprime, $\\mathfrak{p}_{2}^{3}$ and $(\\mathfrak{p}_{2}^{\\prime})^{3}$ are principal. $\\mathfrak{p}_{2}$ cannot be principal since $16=u^{2}+31v^{2}$ has no solution except $(u,v)=(\\pm4,0)$ in which case $\\mathfrak{p}_{2}^{2}=(4)=(2)^{2}=\\mathfrak{p}_{2}^{2}(\\mathfrak{p}_{2}^{\\prime})^{2}$ which implies $(\\mathfrak{p}_{2}^{\\prime})^{2}=1$ a contradiction. Thus, as each ideal class contains either (1), $\\mathfrak{p}_{2}$ or $\\mathfrak{p}_{2}^{\\prime}$ and because $\\mathfrak{p}_{2}^{2}$ is inequivalent to (1) or $\\mathfrak{p}_{2}$ we must have $\\mathfrak{p}_{2}^{2}\\sim\\mathfrak{p}_{2}^{\\prime}$. Thus, $\\mathfrak{p}_{2}^{3}\\sim(1)$. Thus, the class number is 3.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 8.1.3", "question": "Show that any discrete subgroup of $\\mathbb{R}^{m}$ is a lattice.", "solution": "Proof. We prove this by induction on m:\nIn the trivial case, where $\\Gamma=(0)$, $\\Gamma$ is a lattice of dimension 0. We will thus, heretofore, assume that $\\Gamma\\ne(0)$.\nSuppose first that $m=1$, so that $\\Gamma\\subseteq\\mathbb{R}$\nLet $\\alpha$ be a nonzero element of $\\Gamma$ and let $A=\\{\\lambda\\in\\mathbb{R}:\\lambda\\alpha\\in\\Gamma\\}$. By hypothesis, the set $\\{\\gamma\\in\\Gamma:|\\gamma|\\le|\\alpha|\\}$ is finite.\nThen $A\\cap[-1,1]$ is finite and contains a least positive element $0<\\mu\\le1$.\nLet $\\beta=\\mu\\alpha$ and suppose that $\\lambda\\beta\\in\\Gamma$ with $\\lambda\\in\\mathbb{R}$. Then\n$\\lambda\\beta-[\\lambda]\\beta=(\\lambda-[\\lambda])\\beta=(\\lambda-[\\lambda])\\mu\\alpha\\in\\Gamma$\nwhich, by the minimality of $\\mu$, implies that $\\lambda=[\\lambda]$, i.e., $\\lambda\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ which implies that $\\Gamma=\\mathbb{Z}\\beta$ is a lattice of dimension 1.\nNow, suppose that $m>1$.\nLet $\\{v_{1},...,v_{k}\\}$ be a maximal linearly independent subset of $\\Gamma$ (so that $\\Gamma\\subseteq\\mathbb{R}v_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{R}v_{k})$, let V be the subspace of $\\mathbb{R}^{m}$ spanned by $\\{v_{1},...,v_{k-1}\\}$ and let $\\Gamma_{0}=\\Gamma\\cap V.$ Then $\\Gamma_{0}$ is a discrete subgroup of $V\\simeq\\mathbb{R}^{k-1}$ (as vector spaces) so, by the induction hypothesis, is a lattice.\nThat is, there are linearly independent vectors $w_{1},...,w_{l}\\in V$ such that $\\Gamma_{0}=\\mathbb{Z}w_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}w_{l}$ and, since $v_{1},...,v_{k-1}\\in\\Gamma_{0}$ we must have $l=k-1$\nEvidently, $\\{w_{1},...,w_{k-1},w_{k}:=v_{k}\\}$ is also a maximal linearly independent subset of $\\Gamma$ (since span $\\{v_{1},...,v_{k-1}\\}=span\\{w_{1},...,w_{k-1}\\}=V)$. Let\n$T=\\{\\sum_{i=1}^{k}a_{i}w_{i}\\in\\Gamma:0\\le a_{i}<1~for~1\\le i\\le k-1~and~0\\le a_{k}\\le1\\}$\nT is bounded, hence finite, by hypothesis. We may therefore choose an element $x\\in T$ with smallest nonzero coefficient $a_{k}$ of $w_{k}$, say $x=\\sum_{i=1}^{k}b_{i}w_{i}$ .\nSince $b_{k}\\ne0$, the set $\\{w_{1},...,w_{k-1},x\\}$ is linearly independent.\nMoreover, for any $\\gamma\\in\\Gamma$, writing $\\gamma=c_{1}w_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+c_{k-1}w_{k-1}+c_{k}x.$ we see that there are integers $d_{1},...,d_{k-1}$ so that\n$\\gamma^{\\prime}=\\gamma-[c_{k}]x-\\sum_{i=1}^{k-1}d_{i}w_{i}\\in T.$\nSince the coefficient of $w_{k}$ in $\\gamma^{\\prime}$ is $(c_{k}-[c_{k}])b_{k}<b_{k}$, by the minimality of $b_{k}$, we must have that $c_{k}-[c_{k}]=0$ so that $c_{k}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ and $\\gamma^{\\prime}\\in\\Gamma_{0}\\Rightarrow\\gamma\\in \\Gamma_{0}+\\mathbb{Z}x\\Rightarrow\\Gamma=\\Gamma_{0}+\\mathbb{Z}x=\\mathbb{Z}w_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+\\mathbb{Z}w_{k-1}+\\mathbb{Z}x$ is a lattice of dimension k.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Lemma 8.1.4 (a)", "question": "Let $m,n\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ with $0<m\\le n$ and let $\\Delta=(d_{ij})\\in M_{n\\times m}(\\mathbb{R})$. For any integer $t>1$, show that there is a nonzero $x=(x_{1},...,x_{n})\\in \\mathbb{Z}^{n}$ with each $|x_{i}|\\le t$ such that, if $y=x\\Delta=(y_{1},...,y_{m})\\in\\mathbb{R}^{m}$, then each $|y_{i}|\\le ct^{1-n/m}$, where c is a constant depending only on the matrix $\\Delta$.", "solution": "Proof. (a) Let $\\delta=max_{1\\le j\\le m}\\sum_{i=1}^{n}|d_{ij}|$. Then, for $0\\ne x=(x_{1},...,x_{n})\\in\\mathbb{Z}_{\\ge0}^{n}$ with each $|x_{i}|\\le t$\n$|y_{j}|=|\\sum_{i=1}^{n}x_{i}d_{ij}|\\le\\delta t.$\nConsider the cube $[-\\delta t,\\delta t]^{m}\\in\\mathbb{R}^{m}$. Let h be an integer $\\ge 1$ and divide the given cube into $h^{m}$ equal subcubes so that each will have side length $2\\delta t/h.$ Now, for each $x=(x_{1},...,x_{n})\\in[0,t]^{n}\\cap\\mathbb{Z}^{n},y=(y_{1},...,y_{m})\\in [-\\delta t,\\delta t]^{m}$ which means that there are $(t+1)^{n}$ such points $y\\in[-\\delta t,\\delta t]^{m}$.\nThus, if $h^{m}<(t+1)^{n}$, then two of the points must lie in the same subcube.\nThat is, for some $x^{\\prime}\\ne x^{\\prime\\prime}$, we have that, if $y=(x^{\\prime}-x^{\\prime\\prime})\\Delta=(y_{1},...,y_{m})$, then each $|y_{i}|\\le2\\delta t/h$\nSince $t>1$ and $n/m\\ge1$, $(t+1)^{n/m}>t^{n/m}+1$ so there exists an integer h with $t^{n/m}<h<(t+1)^{n/m}$ (in particular, $h^{m}<(t+1)^{n})$.\nThen $|y_{i}|\\le2\\delta t/h<2\\delta t^{1-n/m}$ for each i.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Lemma 8.1.5 (a)", "question": "Let $E=A\\cup B$ be a proper partition of E. Show that there exists a sequence of nonzero integers $\\{\\alpha_{v}\\}\\subseteq\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$ such that\n$|\\alpha_{v}^{(k)}|>|\\alpha_{v+1}^{(k)}|$ for $k\\in A$, $|\\alpha_{v}^{(k)}|<|\\alpha_{v+1}^{(k)}|$ for $k\\in B$,\nand $|N_{K}(\\alpha_{v})|\\le c^{m}$, where c is a positive constant depending only on K and $m=|A\\cup\\overline{A}|$.", "solution": "Proof. (a) Let $t_{1}$ be an integer greater than 1 and let $\\{t_{v}\\}$ be the sequence defined recursively by the relation $t_{v+1}=Mt_{v}$ for all $v\\ge1$, where M is a positive constant that will be suitably chosen.\nBy Lemma 8.1.4, for each $v,\\exists\\alpha_{v}\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ such that\n$c^{1-m}t_{v}^{1-n/m}\\le|\\alpha_{v}^{(k)}|\\le ct_{v}^{1-n/m}$ for $k\\in A.$\n$c^{-m}t_{v}\\le|\\alpha_{v}^{(k)}|\\le t_{v}$ for $k\\in B$\nNow, let $\\kappa=min\\{1,n/m-1\\}$ and choose M such that $M^{\\kappa}>c^{m}$ so that both $M>c^{m}$ and $M^{n/m-1}>c^{m}$. Then, if $k\\in A$,\n$|\\alpha_{v}^{(k)}|\\ge c^{-m+1}t_{v}^{1-n/m}=c^{-m+1}(\\frac{t_{v+1}}{M})^{1-n/m}>ct_{v+1}^{1-n/m}\\ge|\\alpha_{v+1}^{(k)}|$\nand if $k\\in B$, then\n$|\\alpha_{v}^{(k)}|\\le t_{v}=\\frac{t_{v+1}}{M}<c^{-m}t_{v+1}\\le|\\alpha_{v+1}^{(k)}|.$\nAlso,\n$|N_{K}(\\alpha_{v})|=\\prod_{i\\in A\\cup\\overline{A}}|\\alpha_{v}^{(i)}|\\prod_{j\\in B\\cup\\overline{B}}|\\alpha_{v}^{(j)}|\\le(ct_{v}^{1-n/m})^{m}t_{v}^{n-m}=c^{m}.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Lemma 8.1.5 (b)", "question": "Let $E=A\\cup B$ be a proper partition of E. Show that there exists a unit $\\epsilon$ with $|\\epsilon^{(k)}|<1$, for $k\\in A$ and $|\\epsilon^{(k)}|>1$ for $k\\in B$", "solution": "Proof. (b) Let $\\{\\alpha_{v}\\}\\subseteq\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ be the sequence of algebraic integers in (a).\nDefine the sequence of principal ideals $\\mathcal{A}_{v}=(\\alpha_{v}).$ Then $N(\\mathcal{A}_{v})=N_{K}(\\alpha_{v})\\le c^{m}$ (where $N(\\mathcal{A}_{v}):=\\#\\mathcal{O}_{K}/\\mathcal{A}_{v})$.\nSince there are only finitely many integral ideals $\\mathcal{A}_{v}$ of bounded norm, $\\exists\\mu\\in\\mathbb{N}$ such that, for some $v>\\mu$.\n$\\mathcal{A}_{v}=\\mathcal{A}_{\\mu}$ which means that $\\alpha_{\\mu}=\\epsilon\\alpha_{v}$ for some unit $\\epsilon$. We conclude that\n$|\\epsilon^{(k)}|=|\\frac{\\alpha_{\\mu}^{(k)}}{\\alpha_{v}^{(k)}}|\\begin{cases}<1&for~k\\in A,\\\\ >1&for~k\\in B.\\end{cases}$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 8.1.6 (Dirichlet's Unit Theorem)", "question": "Let $U_{K}$ be the unit group of K. Let $n=[K:\\mathbb{Q}]$ and write $n=r_{1}+2r_{2}$, where, as usual, $r_{1}$ and $2r_{2}$ are, respectively, the number of real and nonreal embeddings of K in C. Show that there exist fundamental units $\\epsilon_{1},...,\\epsilon_{r},$ where $r=r_{1}+r_{2}-1$, such that every unit $\\epsilon\\in U_{K}$ can be written uniquely in the form\n$\\epsilon=\\zeta\\epsilon_{1}^{n_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\epsilon_{r}^{n_{r}}$,\nwhere $n_{1},...,n_{r}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ and $\\zeta$ is a root of unity in $\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$.\nMore precisely, if $W_{K}$ is the subgroup of $U_{K}$ consisting of roots of unity, show that $W_{K}$ is finite and cyclic and $U_{K}\\simeq W_{K}\\times\\mathbb{Z}^{r}$.", "solution": "Proof. Let $U_{K}$ be the unit group of K and consider the homomorphism\n$f:U_{K}\\rightarrow\\mathbb{R}^{r}$\n$\\epsilon\\mapsto(log|\\epsilon^{(1)}|,...,log|\\epsilon^{(r)}|)$.\nWe will show that:\n(a) ker $f=W_{K}$ and\n(b) Im $f=\\Gamma$ is a lattice of dim r in $\\mathbb{R}^{r}$.\na) Suppose that $\\epsilon\\in ker~f,$ i.e.,\n$|\\epsilon^{(1)}|=\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot=|\\epsilon^{(r_{1}+r_{2}-1)}|=1$ , $\\Rightarrow|\\epsilon^{(r_{1}+r_{2}+1)}|=\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot=|\\epsilon^{(r_{1}+2r_{2}-1)}|=1.$\nBut, since $\\epsilon\\in U_{K}$,\n$1=|N_{K}(\\epsilon)|=\\prod_{i=1}^{n}|\\epsilon^{(i)}|=|\\epsilon^{(r_{1}+r_{2})}|\\epsilon^{(r_{1}+2r_{2})}|=|\\epsilon^{(r_{1}+r_{2})}|^{2},$\n$\\Rightarrow|\\epsilon^{(r_{1}+r_{2})}|=|\\epsilon^{(r_{1}+2r_{2})}|=1$\nBy Exercise 8.1.1, the number of $\\epsilon\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ such that $|\\epsilon^{(i)}|\\le1$ for all i is finite.\n$\\epsilon$ must, therefore, have finite order in $U_{K}$, i.e, $\\epsilon^{k}=1$, for some positive integer k and so $\\epsilon\\in W_{K}$.\n(b) If $-M<log|\\epsilon^{(i)}|<M$ for $i=1,...,r$ then $e^{-M}<|\\epsilon^{(i)}|<e^{M}$ for all $i\\notin S=\\{r_{1}+r_{2},r_{1}+2r_{2}\\}$. But\n$|\\epsilon^{(r_{1}+r_{2})}|^{2}=\\frac{|N_{K}(\\epsilon)|}{\\prod_{i\\notin S}|\\epsilon^{i}|}<e^{M^{r_{1}+2(r_{2}-1)}<e^{Mn}.}$\nThus, we have that each $|\\epsilon^{(i)}|<e^{Mn/2}$. By Exercise 8.1.1, there are only finitely many $\\epsilon$ for which this inequality holds.\nTherefore, any bounded region in $\\mathbb{R}^{m}$ contains only finitely many points of $\\Gamma$ so, by Theorem 8.1.3, $\\Gamma$ is a lattice of dimension $t\\le r$.\nBy Lemma 8.1.5 (b), we can find for each $1\\le i\\le r,$ a unit $\\epsilon_{i}$ such that $|\\epsilon_{i}^{(i)}|>1$ and $|\\epsilon_{i}^{(j)}|<1$ for $j\\ne i$ and $1\\le j\\le r.$ Let $x_{i}$ be the image of $\\epsilon_{i}$ under the map f.\nWe claim that $x_{1},...,x_{r}$ are linearly independent. For suppose that\n$c_{1}x_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+c_{r}x_{r}=0$,\nwith the $c_{i}$ not all zero. We may suppose without loss of generality that $c_{1}>0$ and $c_{1}\\ge c_{j}$ for $1\\le j\\le r.$ Then,\n$0=\\sum_{i=1}^{r}c_{i}log|\\epsilon_{1}^{(i)}|\\ge c_{1}\\sum_{i=1}^{r}log|\\epsilon_{1}^{(i)}|,$\nso that $\\sum_{i=1}^{r}log|\\epsilon_{1}^{(i)}|\\le0.$\nNow the product of the conjugates of $\\epsilon_{1}$ has absolute value 1. By our choice of $\\epsilon_{1}$, we see that $|\\epsilon_{1}^{(i)}|<1$\nand we deduce that\n$\\sum_{i=1}^{r}log|\\epsilon_{1}^{(i)}|>0,$\nwhich is a contradiction. Thus, $U_{K}\\simeq W_{K}\\times\\Gamma$ and as shown above, $\\Gamma\\simeq\\mathbb{Z}^{r}$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 8.1.10 (a)", "question": "Let $\\zeta_{m}=e^{2\\pi i/m}$, $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m})$. Show that if m is even, the only roots of unity in K are the mth roots of unity, so that $W_{K}\\simeq\\mathbb{Z}/m\\mathbb{Z}$. If m is odd, show that the only ones are the 2mth roots of unity, so that $W_{K}\\simeq \\mathbb{Z}/2m\\mathbb{Z}$.", "solution": "Proof. (a) If m is odd, then $\\zeta_{2m}=-\\zeta_{2m}^{m+1}=-\\zeta_{m}^{(m+1)/2}$ which implies that $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m})=\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{2m})$.\nIt will, therefore, suffice to establish the statement for m even.\nSuppose that $\\theta\\in\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m})$ is a primitive kth root of unity, $k \\nmid m$. Then $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m})$ contains a primitive rth root of unity, where $r=lcm(k,m)>m.$ Then $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{r})\\subseteq\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m})$\n$\\Rightarrow \\varphi(r)=[\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{r}):\\mathbb{Q}]\\le[\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m}):\\mathbb{Q}]=\\varphi(m)$\n(where $\\varphi$ denotes the Euler phi-function). But m is even and m properly divides r implies that $\\varphi(m)$ properly divides $\\varphi(r)$, so that, in particular, $\\varphi(m)<\\varphi(r)$, a contradiction.\nThus, the mth roots of unity are the only roots of unity in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m})$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 8.1.10 (b)", "question": "Let $\\zeta_{m}=e^{2\\pi i/m}$, $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{m})$. Suppose that $[K:\\mathbb{Q}]=4$. Show that $W_{K}$ is one of the six groups Z/2lZ, $1\\le l\\le6$. If, furthermore, K has no real embedding, show that $U_{K}\\simeq W_{K}\\times\\mathbb{Z}.$", "solution": "Proof. (b) $W_{K}$ is cyclic, generated by an rth root of unity, for some even $r\\ge2$. $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{r})\\subseteq K$ means that $4=[K:\\mathbb{Q}]\\ge\\varphi(r)$.\nA straightforward computation shows that $\\varphi(r) \\le 4$\n$\\Rightarrow r\\in\\{2,4,6,8,10,12\\}$.\nIf K has no real embedding, then $r_{1}=0,$ $r_{2}=2\\Rightarrow r=r_{1}+r_{2}-1=1$. By Dirichlet's theorem, $U_{K}\\simeq W_{K}\\times\\mathbb{Z}.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 8.1.10 (c)", "question": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{p})$, p an odd prime. Show that for any unit $\\epsilon\\in U_{K}$, $\\epsilon=\\zeta_{p}^{k}u$, for some real unit $u\\in U_{K}\\cap\\mathbb{R}$, $k\\in\\mathbb{Z}/p\\mathbb{Z}$.", "solution": "Proof. (c) Let $\\epsilon\\in U_{K}$. Then $1=|(\\epsilon/\\overline{\\epsilon})^{(i)}|=|\\epsilon^{(i)}/\\overline{\\epsilon^{(i)}}|$, for $i=1,...,n=[K:\\mathbb{Q}]$. By the remark in the solution to Exercise 8.1.1, $\\epsilon/\\overline{\\epsilon}$ is a root of unity in K and so $\\epsilon/\\overline{\\epsilon}=\\pm\\zeta_{p}^{k}$, for some k.\nSince $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{p}]$ we may write $\\epsilon=\\sum_{i=0}^{p-2}a_{i}\\zeta_{p}^{i}$ each $a_{i}\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ Then\n$z^{p}=(\\sum_{i=0}^{p-2}a_{i}\\zeta_{p}^{i})^{p}\\equiv\\sum_{i=0}^{p-2}a_{i}(mod~p).$\nSince $\\overline{\\epsilon}=\\sum_{i=0}^{p-2}a_{i}\\zeta^{-i}$\n$\\overline{\\epsilon}^{p}\\equiv\\sum_{i=0}^{p-2}a_{i}\\equiv\\epsilon^{p}$ (mod p).\nIf $\\epsilon=-\\zeta_{p}^{k}\\overline{\\epsilon}$ then $\\epsilon^{p}\\equiv-\\overline{\\epsilon}^{p}(mod~p)$ This implies that $2\\epsilon^{p}\\equiv0$ (mod p) and so $\\epsilon^{p}\\equiv0$ (mod p).\nIn other words, $\\epsilon^{p}\\in(p)$, a contradiction, since $\\epsilon$ is a unit.\nThus $\\epsilon/\\overline{\\epsilon}=\\zeta_{p}^{k}$ for some k. $r\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ such that $2r\\equiv k(mod~p)$ and let $\\epsilon_{1}=\\zeta_{p}^{-r}\\epsilon$. Then $\\overline{\\epsilon_{1}}=\\zeta_{p}^{r}\\overline{\\epsilon}=\\zeta_{p}^{r-k}\\epsilon=\\zeta_{p}^{-r}\\epsilon=\\epsilon_{1}\\Rightarrow\\epsilon_{1}\\in\\mathbb{R}$ and $\\epsilon=\\zeta_{p}^{r}\\epsilon_{1}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 8.1.10 (d)", "question": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{p})$, p an odd prime, and let $L=\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{p}+\\zeta_{p}^{-1})$. Show that $L=K\\cap\\mathbb{R}$ and conclude that $U_{K}=\\langle\\zeta_{p}\\rangle\\times U_{L}$.", "solution": "Proof. (d) Let $\\alpha=\\zeta_{p}+\\zeta_{p}^{-1}$ Then $\\alpha=2~cos(2\\pi/p)\\in\\mathbb{R}$ so $L=\\mathbb{Q}(\\alpha)\\subseteq K\\cap\\mathbb{R}$.\nBut since $[K:K\\cap\\mathbb{R}]=2$ and $\\zeta_{p}^{2}-\\alpha\\zeta_{p}+1=0$ so that $[K:\\mathbb{Q}(\\alpha)]\\le2$, we have that $L=K\\cap\\mathbb{R}$.\nThus, $\\epsilon\\in U_{K}$, meaning $\\epsilon=\\pm\\zeta_{p}^{k}\\epsilon_{1}$, for some $\\epsilon_{1}\\in L$, so that $U_{K}=\\langle\\zeta_{p}\\rangle\\times U_{L}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 8.1.10 (e)", "question": "For $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{5})$, show that $U_{K}=\\{\\pm\\zeta_{5}^{k}\\epsilon^{l}:k\\in\\mathbb{Z}/5\\mathbb{Z},l\\in\\mathbb{Z}\\}$ where $\\epsilon=(1+\\sqrt{5})/2$ is the fundamental unit of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{5})$.", "solution": "Proof. (e) It remains only to show that $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{5}+\\zeta_{5}^{-1})=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{5}).$ Let $\\alpha=\\zeta_{5}+\\zeta_{5}^{-1}$.\n$\\zeta_{5}^{4}+\\zeta_{5}^{3}+\\zeta_{5}^{2}+\\zeta_{5}+1=0$\n$\\zeta_{5}^{2}+\\zeta_{5}+1+\\zeta_{5}^{-1}+\\zeta_{5}^{-2}=0$\nor $\\alpha^{2}+\\alpha-1=0$ Since $\\alpha=2~cos(2\\pi/5)>0$ this implies that $\\alpha= (-1+\\sqrt{5})/2$ and we conclude that $\\mathbb{Q}(\\alpha)=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{5}).$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 8.2.4 (a)", "question": "Let $\\alpha$ be an irrational number and let $C_{j}=p_{j}/q_{j}$, for $j\\in\\mathbb{N}$, be the convergents of the simple continued fraction of $\\alpha$. If $r, s\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ with $s>0$ and k is a positive integer such that $|s\\alpha-r|<|q_{k}\\alpha-p_{k}|,$ then show that $s\\ge q_{k+1}$.", "solution": "Proof. (a) Suppose, on the contrary, that $1\\le s<q_{k+1}$. For each $k\\ge0$ consider the system of linear equations\n$p_{k}x+p_{k+1}y=r$ ,\n$q_{k}x+q_{k+1}y=s.$\nUsing Gaussian elimination, we easily find that\n$(p_{k+1}q_{k}-p_{k}q_{k+1})y=rq_{k}-sp_{k}$ ,\n$(p_{k}q_{k+1}-p_{k+1}q_{k})x=rq_{k+1}-sp_{k+1}$\nBy Exercise 8.2.1 (b), $p_{k+1}q_{k}-p_{k}q_{k+1}=(-1)^{k}$ so $p_{k}q_{k+1}-p_{k+1}q_{k}=(-1)^{k+1}$. Thus, the unique solution to this system is given by\n$\\begin{matrix}x&=&(-1)^{k}(sp_{k+1}-rq_{k+1}\\end{matrix})$ ,\n$\\begin{matrix}y&=&(-1)^{k}(rq_{k}-sp_{k}\\end{matrix})$ .\nWe will show that x and y are nonzero and have opposite signs.\nIf $x=0$, then\n$\\frac{r}{s}=\\frac{p_{k+1}}{q_{k+1}}$\nand since $(p_{k+1},q_{k+1})=1.$ this implies that $q_{k+1}|s$ and so $q_{k+1}\\le s,$ contradicting our hypothesis.\nIf $y=0$, then $r=p_{k}x,$ $s=q_{k}x$, so that\n$|s\\alpha-r|=|x|\\cdot|q_{k}\\alpha-p_{k}|\\ge|q_{k}\\alpha-p_{k}|$,\nagain contradicting our hypothesis.\nSuppose now that $y<0$ Then since $q_{k}x=s-q_{k+1}y$ and each $q_{j}\\ge 0,x>0$ On the other hand, if $y>0$ then $q_{k+1}y\\ge q_{k+1}>s$ SO $q_{k}x= s-q_{k+1}y<0$ and $x<0$.\nBy Exercise 8.2.1 (d), if k is even,\n$\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}}<\\alpha<\\frac{p_{k+1}}{q_{k+1}}$\nwhile, if k is odd,\n$\\frac{p_{k+1}}{q_{k+1}}<\\alpha<\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}}$ .\nThus, in either case, $q_{k}\\alpha-p_{k}$ and $q_{k+1}\\alpha-p_{k+1}$ have opposite signs so that $x(q_{k}\\alpha-p_{k})$ and $y(q_{k+1}\\alpha-p_{k+1})$ have the same sign.\n$\\Rightarrow|s\\alpha-r|=|(q_{k}x+q_{k+1}y)\\alpha-(p_{k}x+p_{k+1}y)|$\n$=|x(q_{k}\\alpha-p_{k})+y(q_{k+1}\\alpha-p_{k+1})|$\n$\\ge|x|\\cdot|q_{k}\\alpha-p_{k}|+|y|\\cdot|q_{k+1}\\alpha-p_{k+1}|$\n$\\ge|x|\\cdot|q_{k}\\alpha-p_{k}|\\ge|q_{k}\\alpha-p_{k}|$,\na contradiction, thus establishing our assertion.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 8.2.4 (b)", "question": "If $\\alpha$ is an irrational number and $r/s$ is a rational number in lowest terms, $s>0$, such that $|\\alpha-r/s|<\\frac{1}{2s^{2}}$ then show that $r/s$ is a convergent of the continued fraction of $\\alpha$.", "solution": "Proof. (b) Suppose that $r/s$ is not a convergent of the continued fraction of $\\alpha$, i.e., $r/s\\ne p_{n}/q_{n}$ for all n. Let k be the largest nonnegative integer such that $s\\ge q_{k}$. (Since $s\\ge q_{0}=1$ and $q_{k}\\rightarrow\\infty$ as $k\\rightarrow\\infty$, we know that such a k exists.) Then $q_{k}\\le s\\le q_{k+1}$ and by (a),\n$|q_{k}\\alpha-p_{k}|\\le|s\\alpha-r|=s|\\alpha-r/s|<\\frac{1}{2s}$\n$\\Rightarrow|\\alpha-\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}}|<\\frac{1}{2sq_{k}}.$\nSince $r/s \\ne p_k/q_k$, $|sp_{k}-rq_{k}|\\ge1$,\n$\\frac{1}{sq_{k}}\\le\\frac{|sp_{k}-rq_{k}|}{sq_{k}}=|\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}}-\\frac{r}{s}|$\n$=|\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}}-\\frac{r}{s}+\\alpha-\\alpha|$\n$\\le|\\alpha-\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}}|+|\\alpha-\\frac{r}{s}|$\n$<\\frac{1}{2sq_{k}}+\\frac{1}{2s^{2}}$\nThis would imply that $\\frac{1}{2sq_{k}}<\\frac{1}{2s^{2}}$ so $q_{k}>s$, a contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 8.2.9 (a)", "question": "Let n be the period of the continued fraction of $\\sqrt{d}$. Show that all integer solutions to the equation $x^{2}-dy^{2}=\\pm1$ are given by $x+y\\sqrt{d}=\\pm(p_{n-1}+q_{n-1}\\sqrt{d})^{l}:l\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ where $p_{n-1}/q_{n-1}$ is the $(n-1)th$ convergent of the continued fraction of $\\sqrt{d}$.", "solution": "Proof. (a) For any solution (x, y) to the given equation,\n$(x+\\sqrt{d}y)^{-1}=\\pm(x-\\sqrt{d}y)$.\nTherefore, one of $\\pm(a,\\pm b)$ is a solution to $x^{2}-dy^{2}=\\pm1$ if and only if each of the four pairs is a solution. It will, thus, suffice to show that all positive solutions are given by\n$x+y\\sqrt{d}=(p_{n-1}+q_{n-1}\\sqrt{d})^{m}:m>0$\nBy Exercise 8.2.5, if $x^{2}-dy^{2}=\\pm1$, then $x=p_{k-1}$, $Y = q_{k-1}$, for some k.\nBy Exercise 8.2.8, $p_{k-1}^{2}-dq_{k-1}^{2}=(-1)^{k}Q_{k}=\\pm1\\Rightarrow Q_{k}=\\pm1$ and, by our Remark, this implies that $n|k$. Since\n$p_{n-1}<p_{2n-1}<\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot$ and $q_{n-1}<q_{2n-1}<\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot$,\nwe have that, in particular, the least positive solution to the given equation is $x_{1}=p_{n-1},y_1=q_{n-1}$ We will now show that all positive solutions $(x_{m},y_{m})$ are given by $x_{m}+y_{m}\\sqrt{d}=(x_{1}+y_{1}\\sqrt{d})^{m}$, m > 0.\nTaking Q-conjugates, $x_{m}-y_{m}\\sqrt{d}=(x_{1}-y_{1}\\sqrt{d})^{m}$\n$(x_{m}+y_{m}\\sqrt{d})(x_{m}-y_{m}\\sqrt{d})=(x_{1}^{2}-dy_{1}^{2})^{m}=(\\pm1)^{m}=\\pm1$,\nso that $(x_{m},y_{m})$ is indeed a solution. Evidently, $x_{1}<x_{m}$, $y_{1}<y_{m}$, so that $(x_{m},y_{m})$ is a positive solution.\nNow, suppose that (X, Y) is a positive solution that is not one of the $(x_{m},y_{m})$.\nThen an integer $\\kappa\\ge0$ such that\n$(x_{1}+y_{1}\\sqrt{d})^{\\kappa}<X+Y\\sqrt{d}<(x_{1}+y_{1}\\sqrt{d})^{\\kappa+1}$,\nоr\n$1<(x_{1}+y_{1}\\sqrt{d})^{-\\kappa}(X+Y\\sqrt{d})<x_{1}+y_{1}\\sqrt{d}.$\nBut $x_{1}^{2}-dy_{1}^{2}=\\pm1$ which implies that $(x_{1}+y_{1}\\sqrt{d})^{-\\kappa}=[\\pm(x_{1}-y_{1}\\sqrt{d})]^{\\kappa}.$ Define the integers s, t such that\n$s+t\\sqrt{d}=(x_{1}+y_{1}\\sqrt{d})^{-\\kappa}(X+Y\\sqrt{d})=\\pm(x_{1}-y_{1}\\sqrt{d})^{\\kappa}(X+Y\\sqrt{d}).$\nThen\n$s^{2}-dt^{2}=[\\pm(x_{1}-y_{1}\\sqrt{d})^{\\kappa}(X+Y\\sqrt{d})][\\pm(x_{1}+y_{1}\\sqrt{d})^{\\kappa}(X-Y\\sqrt{d})]$\n$=X^{2}-dY^{2}=\\pm1.$\nThus, (s, t) is a solution to the given equation with\n$1<s+t\\sqrt{d}<x_{1}+y_{1}\\sqrt{d}.$\nAlso,\n$0<(x_{1}+y_{1}\\sqrt{d})^{-1}<(s+t\\sqrt{d})^{-1}<1<s+t\\sqrt{d}.$\nBut this implies that\n$\\begin{matrix}s&=&s+t\\sqrt{d}\\pm[\\pm(s-t\\sqrt{d})\\end{matrix}]=s+t\\sqrt{d}\\pm(s+t\\sqrt{d})^{-1}>0\\end{matrix}$ ,\n$\\begin{matrix}2t\\sqrt{d}&=&s+t\\sqrt{d}\\mp[\\pm(s-t\\sqrt{d})\\end{matrix}]>0$ ,\nand so (s, t) is a positive solution. By hypothesis, then, $s\\ge x_{1}$, $t\\ge y_{1}$ and, since $s+t\\sqrt{d}<x_{1}+y_{1}\\sqrt{d}.$ we have a contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 8.2.9 (b)", "question": "Let n be the period of the continued fraction of $\\sqrt{d}$. If d is squarefree, $d\\equiv2,3(mod~4)$, show that $p_{n-1}+q_{n-1}\\sqrt{d}$ is the fundamental unit of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})$.", "solution": "Proof. (b) Since $p_{n-1}+q_{n-1}\\sqrt{d}>1$ this follows immediately from part (a).", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 8.2.9 (c)", "question": "Let n be the period of the continued fraction of $\\sqrt{d}$. Show that the equation $x^{2}-dy^{2}=-1$ has an integer solution if and only if n is odd.", "solution": "Proof. (c) $x^2-dy^2=-1$ implies $x = p_{k-1}$, $y=q_{k-1}$ for some k, by Exercise 8.2.5.\nBut $p_{k-1}^{2}-dq_{k-1}^{2}=(-1)^{k}Q_{k}=-1$ if and only if $n|k$ and k is odd. Clearly then, a solution exists if and only if n is odd.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Theorem 8.2.9 (d)", "question": "Let n be the period of the continued fraction of $\\sqrt{d}$. If d has a prime divisor $p\\equiv3$ (mod 4), show that the equation $x^{2}-dy^{2}=-1$ has no integer solution.", "solution": "Proof. (d) $x^{2}-dy^{2}=-1$ implies that $x^{2}\\equiv-1(mod~p)$ for all $p|d$. But, for $p\\equiv3$ mod 4, this congruence has no solutions.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.1.1 (a)", "question": "Let K be a number field and $\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$ its ring of integers. Show that there are only finitely many roots of unity in K.", "solution": "Solution. (a) Suppose that $\\alpha^{m}=1$ Then $\\alpha\\in\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$, $|\\alpha|^{m}=1\\Rightarrow|\\alpha|=1$ and, if $\\sigma_{1},...,\\sigma_{n}$ are the distinct embeddings of K in C, then, for each $\\alpha^{(i)}=\\sigma_{i}(\\alpha)$, we have that $\\sigma_{i}(\\alpha)^{m}=\\sigma_{i}(\\alpha^{m})=1\\Rightarrow|\\alpha^{(i)}|=1$ for $i=1,...,n.$\nThe characteristic polynomial of a is\n$f_{\\alpha}(x)=\\prod_{i=1}^{n}(x-\\alpha^{(i)})=x^{n}+a_{n-1}x^{n-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{0}\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x].$\nNow,\n$a_{n-j}=(-1)^{j}s_{j}(\\alpha^{(1)},...,\\alpha^{(n)})$\nwhere $s_{j}(\\alpha^{(1)},...,\\alpha^{(n)})$ is the jth symmetric function in the $\\alpha^{(i)}$ i.e., the sum of all products of the $\\alpha^{(i)}$, taken j at a time.\nThis implies that\n$|a_{n-j}|\\le\\binom{n}{j}\\le n!.$\nThus, since the $a_{j}$ are bounded, there are only finitely many choices for the coefficients of the characteristic polynomial of a root of unity $\\alpha\\in K$ and, hence, only finitely many such roots of unity.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.1.1 (b)", "question": "Let K be a number field and $\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$ its ring of integers. Show, similarly, that for any positive constant c, there are only finitely many $\\alpha\\in\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$ for which $|\\alpha^{(i)}|\\le c$ for all i.", "solution": "Solution. (b) Suppose that $\\alpha\\in\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$ such that $|\\alpha^{(i)}|\\le c$ for all $i=1,...,n.$ As in (a), let\n$f_{\\alpha}(x)=\\prod_{i=1}^{n}(x-\\alpha^{(i)})=x^{n}+a_{n-1}x^{n-1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{0}\\in\\mathbb{Z}[x]$\nbe the characteristic polynomial of a. Then\n$|a_{n-j}|=|s_{j}(\\alpha^{(1)},...,\\alpha^{(n)})|\\le c^{j}\\binom{n}{j}\\le c^{n}n!.$\nThus, the coefficients of the characteristic polynomial of such an a in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ are bounded.\nThere are, therefore, only finitely many such a.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.1.2", "question": "Show that $W_{K}$, the group of roots of unity in K, is cyclic, of even order.", "solution": "Solution. Let $\\alpha_{1},...,\\alpha_{l}$ be the roots of unity in K. For $j=1,...,l$, $\\alpha_{j}^{q_{j}}=1$ for some $q_{j}$ which implies that $\\alpha_{j}=e^{2\\pi ip_{j}/q_{j}}$, for some $0\\le p_{j}\\le q_{j}-1.$ Let $q_{0}=\\prod_{i=1}^{l}q_{j}$ Then, clearly, each $\\alpha_{i}\\in\\langle e^{2\\pi i/q_{0}}\\rangle$ so $W_{K}$ is a subgroup of the cyclic group $\\langle e^{2\\pi i/q_{0}}\\rangle$ and is, thus, cyclic.\nMoreover, since $\\{\\pm1\\}\\subseteq W_{K}$, $W_{K}$ has even order.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.1.7 (a)", "question": "Let $\\Gamma$ be a lattice of dimension n in $\\mathbb{R}^{n}$ and suppose that $\\{v_{1},...,v_{n}\\}$ and $\\{w_{1},...,w_{n}\\}$ are two bases for $\\Gamma$ over Z. Let V and W be the $n\\times n$ matrices with rows consisting of the $v_{i}$ and $w_{i}$, respectively.\nShow that det $V|=|det~W|$. Thus, we can unambiguously define the volume of the lattice $\\Gamma$, $vol(\\Gamma)=$ the absolute value of the determinant of the matrix formed by taking, as its rows, any basis for $\\Gamma$ over Z.", "solution": "Solution. (a) Since $\\{w_{1},...,w_{n}\\}$ is a Z-basis for $\\Gamma$ , we can express each $v_{i}$ as a Z-linear combination of the $w_{j}$, say $v_{i}=\\sum_{j=1}^{n}a_{ij}w_{j}$ .\nSetting $A=(a_{ij})$, we have that $V=AW$. Since $\\{v_{1},...,v_{n}\\}$ is also an integral basis for $\\Gamma$ , the matrix A is invertible, $A\\in GL_{n}(\\mathbb{Z})\\Rightarrow$ det $A\\in\\mathbb{Z}^{*}=\\{\\pm1\\}.$\nThus, det $V|=|det~A||det~W|=|det~W|$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.1.7 (b)", "question": "Let $\\epsilon_{1},...,\\epsilon_{r}$ be a fundamental system of units for a number field K. Show that the regulator of K, $R_{K}=|det(log|\\epsilon_{j}^{(i)}|)|$, is independent of the choice of $\\epsilon_{1},...,\\epsilon_{r}$.", "solution": "Solution. (b) As before, define\n$f:U_{K}\\rightarrow\\mathbb{R}^{r}$,\n$\\epsilon\\mapsto(log|\\epsilon^{(1)}|,...,log|\\epsilon^{(r)}|)$.\nIm f is a lattice of dimension r in $\\mathbb{R}^{r}.$ with Z-basis $\\{f(\\epsilon_{1}),...,f(\\epsilon_{r})\\},$ for any system of fundamental units, $\\epsilon_{1},...,\\epsilon_{r}$.\nBy definition, $R_{K}$ is the absolute value of the determinant of the matrix formed by taking, as its rows, the $f(\\epsilon^{(i)})^{\\prime}s$.\nBy (a) then, $R_{K}$ is independent of the particular system of fundamental units.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.1.8 (a)", "question": "Show that, for any real quadratic field $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})$, where d is a positive squarefree integer, $U_{K}\\simeq\\mathbb{Z}/2\\mathbb{Z}\\times\\mathbb{Z}.$ That is, there is a fundamental unit $\\epsilon\\in U_{K}$ such that $U_{K}=\\{\\pm\\epsilon^{k}:k\\in\\mathbb{Z}\\}$. Conclude that the equation $x^{2}-dy^{2}=1$ (erroneously dubbed Pell's equation) has infinitely many integer solutions for $d\\equiv2,3$ mod 4 and that the equation $x^{2}-dy^{2}=4$ has infinitely many integer solutions for $d\\equiv1$ mod 4.", "solution": "Solution. (a) Since $K\\subseteq\\mathbb{R}$, the only roots of unity in K are $\\{\\pm1\\}$, so $W_{K}=\\{\\pm1\\}$.\nMoreover, since there are $r_{1}=2$ real and $2r_{2}=0$ nonreal embeddings of K in C, by Dirichlet's theorem, we have that $U_{K}\\simeq W_{K}\\times\\mathbb{Z}\\simeq \\mathbb{Z}/2\\mathbb{Z}\\times\\mathbb{Z}$\nSuppose that $d\\equiv2,3$ (mod 4), so that $\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{d}]$. If $\\epsilon=a+b\\sqrt{d}\\in U_{K}^{2}$, then $N_{K}(\\epsilon)=(a+b\\sqrt{d})(a-b\\sqrt{d})=a^{2}-db^{2}=1$\ni.e., each $\\epsilon=a+b\\sqrt{d}\\in U_{K}^{2}$ yields a solution $(a,b)\\in\\mathbb{Z}^{2}$ to the equation $x^{2}-dy^{2}=1.$ Since $U_{K}^{2}\\simeq\\mathbb{Z}$ is infinite, there are infinitely many such solutions.\nSuppose, now, that $d\\equiv1$ (mod 4), so that\n$\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\{\\frac{a+b\\sqrt{d}}{2}:a,b\\in\\mathbb{Z},a\\equiv b(mod~2)\\}$\nIf $\\epsilon=(a+b\\sqrt{d})/2\\in U_{K}^{2}$, then $N_{K}(\\epsilon)=(a^{2}-db^{2})/4=1\\Rightarrow a^{2}-db^{2}=4.$ Since $U_{K}^{2}$ is infinite and each of its elements yields an integral solution to $x^{2}-dy^{2}=4$, this equation has infinitely many solutions x $,y\\in\\mathbb{Z}$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.1.8 (b)", "question": "Let $d\\equiv2,3$ (mod 4). Let b be the smallest positive integer such that one of $db^{2}\\pm1$ is a square, say $a^{2}$, $a>0.$ Then $a+b\\sqrt{d}$ is a unit. Show that it is the fundamental unit. Using this algorithm, determine the fundamental units of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{2})$ $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{3})$", "solution": "Solution. (b) We have that $db^{2}\\pm1=a^{2}$ so $N_{K}(a+b\\sqrt{d})=\\pm1$ and $a+b\\sqrt{d}\\in U_{K}$.\nAlso, a, $b>0$ means that $a+b\\sqrt{d}>1$ so $a+b\\sqrt{d}=\\epsilon^{k}$, for some $k\\ge1$, where $\\epsilon$ is the fundamental unit in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})$.\nIf $k>1$, then write $\\epsilon=\\alpha+\\beta\\sqrt{d},$ $\\alpha,\\beta>0$ It is easy to see that $a+b\\sqrt{d}=(\\alpha+\\beta\\sqrt{d})^{k}$ implies that $\\alpha<a$ and $\\beta\\le b$.\nBut $d\\beta^{2}\\pm1=\\alpha^{2}$, contradicting the minimality of b. Therefore, $a+b\\sqrt{d}$ is, in fact, the fundamental unit.\nIn $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{2})$, $2(1)^{2}-1=1^{2}\\Rightarrow1+\\sqrt{2}$ is the fundamental unit. In $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{3})$, $3(1)^{2}+1=2^{2}\\Rightarrow2+\\sqrt{3}$ is the fundamental unit.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.1.8 (c)", "question": "Devise a similar algorithm to compute the fundamental unit in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})$, for $d\\equiv1$ (mod 4). Determine the fundamental unit of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{5})$.", "solution": "Solution. (c) Let $d\\equiv1$ (mod 4). The same argument as in (b) shows that, if b is the smallest positive integer such that one of $db^{2}\\pm4$ is a square, say $a^{2}$, $a>0$ then $(a+b\\sqrt{d})/2$ is the fundamental unit in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})$.\nIn $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{5})$,\n$5(1)^{2}-4=1^{2}\\Rightarrow(1+\\sqrt{5})/2$ is the fundamental unit.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.1.9 (a)", "question": "For an imaginary quadratic field $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-d})$ (d a positive, squarefree integer), show that\n$U_{K}\\simeq\\begin{cases}\\mathbb{Z}/4\\mathbb{Z}&for~d=1,\\\\ \\mathbb{Z}/6\\mathbb{Z}&for~d=3,\\\\ \\mathbb{Z}/2\\mathbb{Z}&otherwise.\\end{cases}$", "solution": "Solution. (a) Suppose that $-d\\equiv2,3$ (mod 4) so that $\\mathfrak{O}_{K}=\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{-d}]$. Let $a+b\\sqrt{-d}\\in U_{K}$.\nThen $a^{2}+db^{2}=1$ (since $a^{2}$, $b^{2}$, $d\\ge0$, $a^{2}+db^{2}\\ne-1)$ If $b=0$, then $a=\\pm1$. If $b\\ne0$, then $a^{2}+db^{2}\\ge d;$ thus,\n$d>1\\Rightarrow U_{K}=\\{\\pm1\\}\\simeq\\mathbb{Z}/2\\mathbb{Z}$ .\nFor d $=1,a^{2}+db^{2}=a^{2}+b^{2}=1\\Rightarrow(a,b)\\in\\{(\\pm1,0),(0,\\pm1)\\}$\n$U_{K}=\\{\\pm1,\\pm i\\}=\\langle i\\rangle\\simeq\\mathbb{Z}/4\\mathbb{Z}.$\nSuppose now that $-d\\equiv1$ (mod 4). Then $(a+b\\sqrt{-d})/2\\in U_{K}\\Rightarrow$ $a^{2}+db^{2}=4$ If $d>4$ then the only solutions to this equation are $(a,b)=$ (±2,0)\n$\\Rightarrow U_{K}\\simeq\\mathbb{Z}/2\\mathbb{Z}$\nIf $d=3$, then $a^{2}+db^{2}=a^{2}+3b^{2}=4$ Then $(a,b)\\in\\{(\\pm2,0),(\\pm1,\\pm1)\\}$ so that\n$U_{K}=\\{\\pm\\zeta_{3},\\pm\\zeta_{3}^{2},\\pm1\\}=\\langle-\\zeta_{3}\\rangle\\simeq\\mathbb{Z}/6\\mathbb{Z}$\n(where $\\zeta_{3}=(-1+\\sqrt{-3})/2)$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.1.9 (b)", "question": "Show that $U_{K}$ is finite $\\Leftrightarrow K=\\mathbb{Q}$ or K is an imaginary quadratic field.", "solution": "Solution. (b) We have already shown that for K a quadratic imaginary field, $U_{K}$ is finite.\nNow, suppose that $U_{K}$ is finite. Then $r_{1}+r_{2}=1$ which implies that either $r_{1}=1$, $r_{2}=0$ so that $[K:\\mathbb{Q}]=r_{1}+2r_{2}=1$ and $K=\\mathbb{Q}$ or $r_{1}=0$, $r_{2}=1$ and $[K:\\mathbb{Q}]=2$ and $K\\notin\\mathbb{R}$ so that K is quadratic imaginary.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.1.9 (c)", "question": "Show that, if there exists an embedding of K in R, then $W_{K}\\simeq\\{\\pm1\\}\\simeq\\mathbb{Z}/2\\mathbb{Z}.$ Conclude that, in particular, this is the case if $[K:\\mathbb{Q}]$ is odd.", "solution": "Solution. (c) If there exists an embedding $\\sigma:K\\rightarrow\\mathbb{R}$ then $K\\simeq\\sigma(K)$ and in particular $W_{K}\\simeq W_{\\sigma(K)}\\subseteq\\mathbb{R}$ Since the only real roots of unity are $\\{\\pm1\\}$, we must have $W_{K}=\\sigma^{-1}(\\{\\pm1\\})=\\{\\pm1\\}$ In particular, if $[K:\\mathbb{Q}]=r_{1}+2r_{2}$ is odd, then $r_{1}$ is odd and, therefore, $\\ge1$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.1.11 (a)", "question": "Let $[K:\\mathbb{Q}]=3$ and suppose that K has only one real embedding. Then, by Exercise 8.1.8 (c), $W_{K}=\\{\\pm1\\}$ implies that $U_{K}=\\{\\pm u^{k}:k\\in\\mathbb{Z}\\}$, where $u>1$ is the fundamental unit in K.\nLet $u,\\rho e^{i\\theta}$, $\\rho e^{-i\\theta}$ be the Q-conjugates of u. Show that $u=\\rho^{-2}$ and that $d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(u)=-4~sin^{2}\\theta(\\rho^{3}+\\rho^{-3}-2~cos~\\theta)^{2}$.", "solution": "Solution. (a) $N_{K}(u)=u\\rho^{2}=\\pm1$ so $u=\\pm\\rho^{-2}$, but $u>1$ implies that $u=\\rho^{-2}$\n$d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(u)=\\prod_{1\\le r<s\\le3}(u^{(r)}-u^{(s)})^{2}$\n$=(\\rho^{-2}-\\rho e^{i\\theta})^{2}(\\rho^{-2}-\\rho e^{-i\\theta})^{2}(\\rho e^{i\\theta}-\\rho e^{-i\\theta})^{2}$\n$=(\\rho^{-4}-\\rho(e^{i\\theta}+e^{-i\\theta})+\\rho^{2})^{2}(\\rho(e^{i\\theta}-e^{-i\\theta}))^{2}$\n$=(\\rho^{-4}-\\rho(2~cos~\\theta)+\\rho^{2})^{2}(\\rho(2i~sin~\\theta))^{2}$\n$=-4~sin^{2}\\theta(\\rho^{3}+\\rho^{-3}-2~cos~\\theta)^{2}$ .", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.1.11 (b)", "question": "Let $[K:\\mathbb{Q}]=3$ and suppose that K has only one real embedding. Let u be the fundamental unit in K. Show that $|d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(u)|<4(u^{3}+u^{-3}+6)$.", "solution": "Solution. (b)\n$|d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(u)|=4~sin^{2}\\theta(\\rho^{3}+\\rho^{-3}-2~cos~\\theta)^{2}$.\nNow set $x=\\rho^{3}+\\rho^{-3}$ $c=cos~\\theta$ and consider\n$f(x)=(1-c^{2})(x-2c)^{2}-x^{2}.$\nThis function attains a maximum when $x=-2(1-c^{2})/c$ and this maximum is $4(1-c^{2})\\le4$ Therefore\n$|d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(u)|\\le4(\\rho^{3}+\\rho^{-3})^{2}+16 =4(u^{3}+u^{-3}+6)$ .", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.1.11 (c)", "question": "Let $[K:\\mathbb{Q}]=3$ and suppose that K has only one real embedding. Let u be the fundamental unit in K. Conclude that $u^{3}>d/4-6-u^{-3}>d/4-7,$ where $d=|d_{K}|.$", "solution": "Solution. (c) Since $d=|d_{K}|<|d_{K/\\mathbb{Q}}(u)|$, we have\n$u^{3}>\\frac{d}{4}-6-u^{-3}>\\frac{d}{4}-7.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.1.12 (a)", "question": "Let $\\alpha=\\sqrt[3]{2}$, $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\alpha)$. Given that $d_{K}=-108$. Show that, if u is the fundamental unit in K, $u^{3}>20$.", "solution": "Solution. (a) By Exercise 8.1.11, $u^{3}>108/4-7=20$ so $u^{2}>20^{2/3}>7.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.1.12 (b)", "question": "Let $\\alpha=\\sqrt[3]{2}$, $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\alpha)$. Given that $d_{K}=-108$. Show that $\\beta=(\\alpha-1)^{-1}=\\alpha^{2}+\\alpha+1$ is a unit, $1<\\beta<u^{2}$. Conclude that $\\beta=u.$", "solution": "Solution. (b) Computation shows that $\\frac{1}{7}<\\alpha-1<1$ and therefore $1<(\\alpha-1)^{-1}<7<u^{2}$.\nSince $\\beta$ is a power of u, this power must be 1. Therefore $\\beta=u$ is the fundamental unit in K.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.1.13 (a)", "question": "Show that, if $\\alpha\\in K$ is a root of a monic polynomial $f\\in \\mathbb{Z}[x]$ and $f(r)=\\pm1$, for some $r\\in\\mathbb{Z}.$ then $\\alpha-r$ is a unit in K.", "solution": "Solution. (a) Let $g(x)=f(x+r)$. Then $g(x)$ is a monic polynomial in $\\mathbb{Z}[x]$ with constant term $g(0)=f(r)=\\pm1$ Since $g(\\alpha-r)=0$ the minimal polynomial of $\\alpha-r\\in\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ divides $g(x)$ and, thus, has constant term $\\pm1$.\nTherefore $N_{K}(\\alpha-r)=\\pm1$ so $\\alpha-r\\in U_{K}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.1.13 (b)", "question": "Using the fact that if $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt[3]{m})$, then $d_{K}=-27m^{2}$, for any cubefree integer m, determine the fundamental unit in $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt[3]{7})$.", "solution": "Solution. (b) $d_{K}=-27\\cdot7^{2}$ implies that $u^{3}>27\\cdot7^{2}/4-7>323$ and so $u^{2}> (323)^{2/3}>47$ by Exercise 8.1.11.\nLet $f(x)=x^{3}-7$ and note that $f(2)=1$ Then $\\sqrt[3]{7}-2\\in U_{K}$. Also, $1/u^{2}<1/47<2-\\sqrt[3]{7}<1$ implies that $1<(2-\\sqrt[3]{7})^{-1}<u^{2}$.\nTherefore, $(2-\\sqrt[3]{7})^{-1}$ is the fundamental unit of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt[3]{7})$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.1.13 (c)", "question": "Determine the fundamental unit in $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt[3]{3})$.", "solution": "Solution. (c) Let $\\alpha=\\sqrt[3]{3}$, $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\alpha)$. $d_{K}=-27\\cdot3^{2}=-3^{5}$ . We observe that $\\alpha^{2}$ is a root of $f(x)=x^{3}-9$ and $f(2)=-1$ so $\\alpha^{2}-2\\in U_{K}.$ We have $u^{3}>3^{5}/4-7>53$ and thus $u^{2}>14$ Since $\\frac{1}{14}<\\alpha^{2}-1< 1,1<(\\alpha^{2}-2)^{-1}<14<u^{2}$.\nThus, $(\\alpha^{2}-2)^{-1}$ is the fundamental unit of $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\alpha)$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.2.1 (a)", "question": "Consider the continued fraction $[a_{0},...,a_{n}]$. Define the sequences $p_{0},...,p_{n}$ and $q_{0},...,q_{n}$ recursively as follows:\n$p_{0}=a_{0}$\n$p_{1}=a_{0}a_{1}+1$,\n$p_{k}=a_{k}p_{k-1}+p_{k-2}$\n$q_{0}=1$,\n$q_{1}=a_{1}$,\n$q_{k}=a_{k}q_{k-1}+q_{k-2}$,\nfor $k\\ge2$ Show that the kth convergent $C_{k}=p_{k}/q_{k}$.", "solution": "Solution. (a) We prove this by induction on k.\nFor $k=0$, $C_{0}=[a_{0}]=p_{0}/q_{0}.$ For $k=1$,\n$C_{1}=[a_{0},a_{1}]=a_{0}+\\frac{1}{a_{1}}=\\frac{a_{0}a_{1}+1}{a_{1}}=\\frac{p_{1}}{q_{1}}.$\nFor $k>1$, suppose that\n$C_{k}=\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}}=\\frac{a_{k}p_{k-1}+p_{k-2}}{a_{k}q_{k-1}+q_{k-2}}.$\nSince $p_{k-1},p_{k-2},q_{k-1},q_{k-2}$ depend only on $a_{0},...,a_{k-1}$,\n$\\begin{matrix}C_{k+1}&=&[\\begin{matrix}a_{0},a_{1},...,a_{k-1},a_{k}+\\frac{1}{a_{k+1}}\\end{matrix}]\\end{matrix}$\n$=\\frac{(a_{k}+\\frac{1}{a_{k+1}})p_{k-1}+p_{k-2}}{(a_{k}+\\frac{1}{a_{k+1}})q_{k-1}+q_{k-2}}$\n$=\\frac{a_{k+1}(a_{k}p_{k-1}+p_{k-2})+p_{k-1}}{a_{k+1}(a_{k}q_{k-1}+q_{k-2})+q_{k-1}}$\n$=\\frac{a_{k+1}p_{k}+p_{k-1}}{a_{k+1}q_{k}+q_{k-1}}=\\frac{p_{k+1}}{q_{k+1}}.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.2.1 (b)", "question": "Consider the continued fraction $[a_{0},...,a_{n}]$. Define the sequences $p_{0},...,p_{n}$ and $q_{0},...,q_{n}$ recursively as follows:\n$p_{0}=a_{0}, p_{1}=a_{0}a_{1}+1, p_{k}=a_{k}p_{k-1}+p_{k-2}$\n$q_{0}=1, q_{1}=a_{1}, q_{k}=a_{k}q_{k-1}+q_{k-2}$, for $k\\ge2$.\nShow that $p_{k}q_{k-1}-p_{k-1}q_{k}=(-1)^{k-1},$ for $k\\ge1.$", "solution": "Solution. (b) Again, we apply induction on k. For $k=1$\n$p_{1}q_{0}-p_{0}q_{1}=(a_{0}a_{1}+1)\\cdot1-a_{0}a_{1}=1$.\nFor $k\\ge1$,\n$p_{k+1}q_{k}-p_{k}q_{k+1}=(a_{k+1}p_{k}+p_{k-1})q_{k}-p_{k}(a_{k+1}q_{k}+q_{k-1})$\n$=p_{k-1}q_{k}-p_{k}q_{k-1}=-(-1)^{k-1}=(-1)^{k},$\nby our induction hypothesis.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.2.1 (c)", "question": "Consider the continued fraction $[a_{0},...,a_{n}]$. Define the sequences $p_{0},...,p_{n}$ and $q_{0},...,q_{n}$ recursively as follows:\n$p_{0}=a_{0}, p_{1}=a_{0}a_{1}+1, p_{k}=a_{k}p_{k-1}+p_{k-2}$\n$q_{0}=1, q_{1}=a_{1}, q_{k}=a_{k}q_{k-1}+q_{k-2}$, for $k\\ge2$.\nDerive the identities\n$C_{k}-C_{k-1}=\\frac{(-1)^{k-1}}{q_{k}q_{k-1}}$ for $1\\le k\\le n$, and\n$C_{k}-C_{k-2}=\\frac{a_{k}(-1)^{k}}{q_{k}q_{k-2}}$ for $2\\le k\\le n$.", "solution": "Solution. (c) By (b),\n$p_{k}q_{k-1}-q_{k}p_{k-1}=(-1)^{k-1}$ .\nDividing by $q_{k}q_{k-1}$, we obtain the first identity. Now,\n$C_{k}-C_{k-2}=\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}}-\\frac{p_{k-2}}{q_{k-2}}=\\frac{p_{k}q_{k-2}-p_{k-2}q_{k}}{q_{k}q_{k-2}}.$\nBut\n$p_{k}q_{k-2}-p_{k-2}q_{k}=(a_{k}p_{k-1}+p_{k-2})q_{k-2}-p_{k-2}(a_{k}q_{k-1}+q_{k-2})$\n$=a_{k}(p_{k-1}q_{k-2}-p_{k-2}q_{k-1})=a_{k}(-1)^{k-2}$\nestablishing the second identity.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.2.1 (d)", "question": "Show that\n$C_{1}>C_{3}>C_{5}>\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot,$\n$C_{0}<C_{2}<C_{4}<\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot,$\nand that every odd-numbered convergent $C_{2j+1}$ $j\\ge0$, is greater than every even-numbered convergent $C_{2k}$, $k\\ge0$.", "solution": "Solution. (d) By (c),\n$C_{k}-C_{k-2}=\\frac{a_{k}(-1)^{k}}{q_{k}q_{k-2}}.$\nThus, $C_{k}<C_{k-2}$ for k odd and $C_{k}>C_{k-2}$ for k even. In addition,\n$C_{2m}-C_{2m-1}=\\frac{(-1)^{2m-1}}{q_{2m}q_{2m-1}}<0\\Rightarrow C_{2m-1}>C_{2m},$\n$\\Rightarrow C_{2k}<C_{2(j+k+1)}<C_{2(j+k)+1}<C_{2j+1}.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.2.2", "question": "Let $\\{a_{i}\\}_{i\\ge0}$ be an infinite sequence of integers with $a_{i}\\ge0$ for $i\\ge1$ and let $C_{k}=[a_{0},...,a_{k}]$. Show that the sequence $\\{C_{k}\\}$ converges.", "solution": "Solution. By Exercise 8.2.1 (d), we have\n$C_{1}>C_{3}>C_{5}>\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot$\nMoreover, each $C_{2j+1}>a_{0}$ so that the sequence $\\{C_{2j+1}\\}_{j\\ge0}$ is decreasing and bounded from below and is, thus, convergent, say $lim_{j\\rightarrow\\infty}C_{2j+1}=\\alpha_{1}$.\nAlso,\n$C_{0}<C_{2}<C_{4}<\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot$\nand $C_{2j}<C_{2k+1}$ for all $j,k\\ge0$ In particular, each $C_{2j}<C_{1}$. The sequence $\\{C_{2j}\\}_{j\\ge0}$ is increasing and bounded from above and, therefore, also converges, say $lim_{j\\rightarrow\\infty}C_{2j}=\\alpha_{2}$ We will show that $\\alpha_{1}=\\alpha_{2}$.\nSince each $a_{i}\\ge1,q_{0},q_{1}\\ge1$, we easily see, by induction on k, that $q_{k}=a_{k}q_{k-1}+q_{k-2}\\ge2k-3.$ By Exercise 8.2.1 (c),\n$C_{2j+1}-C_{2j}=\\frac{1}{q_{2j+1}q_{2j}}\\le\\frac{1}{(4j-1)(4j-3)}\\rightarrow0,$\nas $j\\rightarrow\\infty$. Thus, both sequences converge to the same limit and $lim_{j\\rightarrow\\infty}C_{j}=\\alpha=\\alpha_{1}=\\alpha_{2}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.2.3", "question": "Let $\\alpha=\\alpha_{0}$ be an irrational real number greater than 0. Define the sequence $\\{a_{i}\\}_{i\\ge0}$ recursively as follows:\n$a_{k}=[\\alpha_{k}]$,\n$\\alpha_{k+1}=\\frac{1}{\\alpha_{k}-a_{k}}$\nShow that $\\alpha=[a_{0},a_{1},...]$ is a representation of a as a simple continued fraction.", "solution": "Solution. By induction on k, we easily see that each $\\alpha_{k}$ is irrational. Therefore $\\alpha_{k+1}>1$ which means that $a_{k+1}\\ge1$ so that $[a_{0},a_{1},...]$ is a simple continued fraction. Also,\n$\\alpha=\\alpha_{0}=[\\alpha_{0}]+(\\alpha_{0}-[\\alpha_{0}])=a_{0}+\\frac{1}{\\alpha_{1}}$\n$=[\\begin{matrix}a_{0},\\alpha_{1}\\end{matrix}]=[a_{0},a_{1},\\alpha_{2}\\end{matrix}]=\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot=[a_{0},a_{1},...,a_{k},\\alpha_{k+1}\\end{matrix}]$\nfor all k. By Exercise 8.2.1 (a),\n$\\alpha=\\frac{\\alpha_{k+1}p_{k}+p_{k-1}}{\\alpha_{k+1}q_{k}+q_{k-1}}$\nso that\n$|\\alpha-C_{k}|=|\\frac{\\alpha_{k+1}p_{k}+p_{k-1}}{\\alpha_{k+1}q_{k}+q_{k-1}}-\\frac{p_{k}}{q_{k}}|$\n$=|\\frac{-(p_{k}q_{k-1}-p_{k-1}q_{k})}{(\\alpha_{k+1}q_{k}+q_{k-1})q_{k}}|$\n$=|\\frac{1}{(\\alpha_{k+1}q_{k}+q_{k-1})q_{k}}|$\n$<\\frac{1}{q_{k}^{2}}\\le\\frac{1}{(2k-3)^{2}}\\rightarrow0$\nas $k\\rightarrow\\infty$ Thus,\n$\\alpha=lim_{k\\rightarrow\\infty}C_{k}=[a_{0},a_{1},...].$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.2.5", "question": "Let d be a positive integer, not a perfect square. Show that, if $|x^{2}-dy^{2}|<\\sqrt{d}$ for positive integers x, y, then $x/y$ is a convergent of the continued fraction of $\\sqrt{d}.$", "solution": "Solution. Suppose first that $0<x^{2}-dy^{2}<\\sqrt{d}$ Then\n$(x+y\\sqrt{d})(x-y\\sqrt{d})>0\\Rightarrow x>y\\sqrt{d};$\n$\\Rightarrow|\\sqrt{d}-\\frac{x}{y}|=\\frac{x}{y}-\\sqrt{d}=\\frac{x-y\\sqrt{d}}{y}$\n$=\\frac{x^{2}-dy^{2}}{y(x+y\\sqrt{d})}<\\frac{x^{2}-dy^{2}}{y(2y\\sqrt{d})}<\\frac{1}{2y^{2}}$\nThus, by Theorem 8.2.4 (b), $x/y$ is a convergent of the continued fraction of $\\sqrt{d}$.\nSimilarly, if $-\\sqrt{d}<x^{2}-dy^{2}<0$ then\n$0<y^{2}-\\frac{1}{d}x^{2}<\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{d}}\\Rightarrow y>\\frac{x}{\\sqrt{d}}.$\n$\\Rightarrow|\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{d}}-\\frac{y}{x}|=\\frac{y}{x}-\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{d}}=\\frac{y-x/\\sqrt{d}}{x}$\n$=\\frac{y^{2}-x^{2}/d}{x(y+x/\\sqrt{d})}<\\frac{y^{2}-x^{2}/d}{2x^{2}/\\sqrt{d}}<\\frac{1}{2x^{2}}.$\nThus $y/x$ is a convergent of the continued fraction of $1/\\sqrt{d}$.\nLet a be any irrational number. Then $\\alpha=[a_{0},a_{1},...]$ implies $1/\\alpha=[0,a_{0},a_{1},...]$. We therefore have that the $(k+1)t$ th convergent of the continued fraction of $1/\\alpha$ is the reciprocal of the kth convergent of a, for all $k\\ge0$.\nUsing this fact, we find that, as before, $x/y$ is a convergent of the continued fraction of $\\sqrt{d}.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.2.6", "question": "Let a be a quadratic irrational (i.e, the minimal polynomial of the real number a over has degree 2). Show that there are integers $P_{0}$, $Q_{0}$, d such that\n$\\alpha=\\frac{P_{0}+\\sqrt{d}}{Q_{0}}$\nwith $Q_{0}|(d-P_{0}^{2})$. Recursively define\n$\\alpha_{k}=\\frac{P_{k}+\\sqrt{d}}{Q_{k}};$ $a_{k}=[\\alpha_{k}],$\n$P_{k+1}=a_{k}Q_{k}-P_{k},$ $Q_{k+1}=\\frac{d-P_{k+1}^{2}}{Q_{k}};$\nfor $k=0,1,2,...$ Show that $[a_{0},a_{1},a_{2},...]$ is the simple continued fraction of $\\alpha$.", "solution": "Solution. There exist a, b, e, $f\\in\\mathbb{Z}$, e, $f>0,$ e not a perfect square, such that\n$\\alpha=\\frac{a+b\\sqrt{e}}{f}=\\frac{af+\\sqrt{eb^{2}f^{2}}}{f^{2}}$\nand, evidently, $f^{2}|(a^{2}f^{2}-eb^{2}f^{2})$. Set $P_{0}=af$ $Q_{0}=f^{2}$, $d=eb^{2}f^{2}$ This sequence is well-defined, since d is not a perfect square $\\Rightarrow Q_{k}\\ne0$ for all k.\nBy Exercise 8.2.3, it will suffice to show that $\\alpha_{k+1}=\\frac{1}{\\alpha_{k}-a_{k}}$ for all k.\n$\\begin{matrix}\\alpha_{k}-a_{k}&=&\\frac{P_{k}+\\sqrt{d}}{Q_{k}}-a_{k}\\end{matrix}$\n$=\\frac{\\sqrt{d}-(a_{k}Q_{k}-P_{k})}{Q_{k}}$\n$=\\frac{\\sqrt{d}-P_{k+1}}{Q_{k}}$\n$=\\frac{d-P_{k+1}^{2}}{Q_{k}(\\sqrt{d}+P_{k+1})}$\n$=\\frac{Q_{k}Q_{k+1}}{Q_{k}(\\sqrt{d}+P_{k+1})}$\n$=\\frac{1}{\\alpha_{k+1}}.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.2.7", "question": "Show that the simple continued fraction expansion of a quadratic irrational a is periodic.", "solution": "Solution. By Exercise 8.2.6, we may write\n$\\alpha=\\frac{P_{0}+\\sqrt{d}}{Q_{0}}$\nwith $Q_{0}|(P_{0}^{2}-d)$. Setting\n$\\alpha_{k}=\\frac{P_{k}+\\sqrt{d}}{Q_{k}},$ $a_{k}=[\\alpha_{k}],$ $P_{k+1}=a_{k}Q_{k}-P_{k},$ $Q_{k+1}=\\frac{d-P_{k+1}^{2}}{Q_{k}}$\nwe have\n$P_{0}=0, P_{1}=d, Q_{0}=1, Q_{1}=1, \\alpha_{0}=\\sqrt{d^{2}+1}, \\alpha_{1}=d+\\sqrt{d^{2}+1}, a_{0}=d, a_{1}=2d.$\nand $\\alpha=[a_{0},a_{1},...]$. Now,\n$\\alpha=\\frac{\\alpha_{k}p_{k-1}+p_{k-2}}{\\alpha_{k}q_{k-1}+q_{k-2}}$\nand if $\\alpha^{\\prime}$ denotes the Q-conjugate of a,\n$\\alpha^{\\prime}=\\frac{\\alpha_{k}^{\\prime}p_{k-1}+p_{k-2}}{\\alpha_{k}^{\\prime}q_{k-1}+q_{k-2}}\\Rightarrow\\alpha_{k}^{\\prime}=-\\frac{q_{k-2}}{q_{k-1}}(\\frac{\\alpha^{\\prime}-C_{k-2}}{\\alpha^{\\prime}-C_{k-1}})$\nSince $C_{k-1},C_{k-2}\\rightarrow\\alpha~as~k\\rightarrow\\infty$, $\\frac{\\alpha^{\\prime}-C_{k-2}}{\\alpha^{\\prime}-C_{k-1}}\\rightarrow1.$\nTherefore, $\\alpha_{k}^{\\prime}<0$, and, since $\\alpha_{k}>0$ $\\alpha_{k}-\\alpha_{k}^{\\prime}=2\\sqrt{d}/Q_{k}>0,$ for all sufficiently large k. We also have $Q_{k}Q_{k+1}=d-P_{k+1}^{2}$ SO $Q_{k}\\le Q_{k}Q_{k+1}=d-P_{k+1}^{2}\\le d$ and $P_{k+1}^{2}\\le d-Q_{k}\\le d$ for sufficiently large k. Thus there are only finitely many possible values for $P_{k}$, $Q_{k}$ and we conclude that there exist integers $i<j$ such that $P_{i}=P_{j},Q_{i}=Q_{j}$ Then $a_{i}=a_{j}$ and, since the $a_{i}$ are defined recursively, we have $\\alpha=[a_{0},a_{1},...,a_{i-1},\\overline{a_{i},...,a_{j-1}}]$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.2.8", "question": "Show that, if d is a positive integer but not a perfect square, and $\\alpha=\\alpha_{0}=\\sqrt{d},$ then\n$p_{k-1}^{2}-dq_{k-1}^{2}=(-1)^{k}Q_{k},$\nfor all $k\\ge1$, where $p_{k}/q_{k}$ is the kth convergent of the continued fraction of a and $Q_{k}$ is as defined in Exercise 8.2.6.", "solution": "Solution. By inspection, $p_{0}^{2}-dq_{0}^{2}=[\\sqrt{d}]^{2}-d=-Q_{1}$. Now, suppose that $k\\ge2$ Writing\n$\\sqrt{d}=\\alpha_{0}=[a_{0},a_{1},...,a_{k-1},\\alpha_{k}]=\\frac{\\alpha_{k}p_{k-1}+p_{k-2}}{\\alpha_{k}q_{k-1}+q_{k-2}}$\nand recalling that $\\alpha_{k}=(P_{k}+\\sqrt{d})/Q_{k}$, we have\n$\\sqrt{d}=\\frac{(P_{k}+\\sqrt{d})p_{k-1}+Q_{k}p_{k-2}}{(P_{k}+\\sqrt{d})q_{k-1}+Q_{k}q_{k-2}},$\n$\\Rightarrow dq_{k-1}+(P_{k}q_{k-1}+Q_{k}q_{k-2})\\sqrt{d}=P_{k}p_{k-1}+Q_{k}p_{k-2}+p_{k-1}\\sqrt{d}.$\nEquating coefficients in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})$, we have\n$dq_{k-1}=P_{k}p_{k-1}+Q_{k}p_{k-2}$ and $p_{k-1}=P_{k}q_{k-1}+Q_{k}q_{k-2}.$\nComputation yields\n$p_{k-1}^{2}-dq_{k-1}^{2}=(p_{k-1}q_{k-2}-p_{k-2}q_{k-1})Q_{k}=(-1)^{k}Q_{k}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.2.10 (a)", "question": "Find the simple continued fractions of $\\sqrt{6},\\sqrt{23}.$", "solution": "Solution. (a) Using notation of previous exercises, setting $\\alpha=\\alpha_{0}=\\sqrt{6},$ we have\n$P_{0}=0, P_{1}=2, P_{2}=2, Q_{0}=1, Q_{1}=2, Q_{2}=1, \\alpha_{0}=\\sqrt{6}, a_{0}=2, \\alpha_{1}=\\frac{2+\\sqrt{6}}{2}, a_{1}=2, \\alpha_{2}=2+\\sqrt{6}, a_{2}=4.$\nThus, the period of the continued fraction of a is $2\\Rightarrow\\sqrt{6}=[a_{0},\\overline{a_{1},a_{2}}]=[2,2,4]$. Applying the same procedure, we find $\\sqrt{23}=[4,\\overline{1,3,1,8}]$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.2.10 (b)", "question": "Using Theorem 8.2.9 (c), compute the fundamental unit in both $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{6})$ and $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{23})$.", "solution": "Solution. (b) For $\\sqrt{6}$ $C_{1}=p_{1}/q_{1}=[a_{0},a_{1}]=a_{0}+1/a_{1}=2+1/2=5/2$ Thus, the fundamental unit in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{6})$ is $5+2\\sqrt{6}$\nFor $\\sqrt{23}$, $C_{3}=[4,1,3,1]=24/5$. Therefore the fundamental unit in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{23})$ is $24+5\\sqrt{23}$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.2.11 (a)", "question": "Show that $[d,\\overline{2d}]$ is the continued fraction of $\\sqrt{d^{2}+1}.$", "solution": "Solution. (a) Observing that $d^{2}<d^{2}+1\\le(d+1)^{2}$ for all $d>0$, we see that $[\\sqrt{d^{2}+1}]=d$ and setting $\\alpha=\\alpha_{0}=\\sqrt{d^{2}+1},$ we have\n$P_{0}=0, P_{1}=d, Q_{0}=1, Q_{1}=1, \\alpha_{0}=\\sqrt{d^{2}+1}, \\alpha_{1}=d+\\sqrt{d^{2}+1}, a_{0}=d, a_{1}=2d.$\nThis implies that the period of the continued fraction of $\\sqrt{d^{2}+1}$ is 1.\nTherefore $\\sqrt{d^{2}+1}=[a_{0},\\overline{a_{1}}]=[d,\\overline{2d}]$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.2.11 (b)", "question": "Conclude that, if $d^{2}+1$ is squarefree, $d\\equiv1,3$ (mod 4), then the fundamental unit of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d^{2}+1})$ is $d+\\sqrt{d^{2}+1}.$ Compute the fundamental unit of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{2})$, $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{10})$, $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{26})$.", "solution": "Solution. (b) $d\\equiv1,3$ (mod 4) and thus $d^{2}+1\\equiv2$ (mod 4). Thus, if $d^{2}+1$ is squarefree, then the fundamental unit of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d^{2}+1})$ is $p_{0}+q_{0}\\sqrt{d^{2}}+1=d+\\sqrt{d^{2}+1}.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.2.11 (c)", "question": "Show that the continued fraction of $\\sqrt{d^{2}+2}$ is $[d,\\overline{d,2d}]$.", "solution": "Solution. (c) Observing that $d^{2}<d^{2}+2<(d+1)^{2}$ for all $d\\ge1$ we get $[\\sqrt{d^{2}+2}]=d$ and setting $\\alpha=\\alpha_{0}=\\sqrt{d^{2}+2}$, we have\n$P_{0}=0, Q_{0}=1, a_{0}=d, P_{1}=d, Q_{1}=2, a_{1}=d, \\alpha_{0}=\\sqrt{d^{2}+2}, \\alpha_{1}=\\frac{d+\\sqrt{d^{2}+2}}{2}, P_{2}=d, Q_{2}=1, \\alpha_{2}=d+\\sqrt{d^{2}+2}, a_{2}=2d$\nTherefore the period of the continued fraction of $\\sqrt{d^{2}+2}$ is 2, so\n$\\sqrt{d^{2}+2}=[a_{0},\\overline{a_{1},a_{2}}]=[d,\\overline{d,2d}]$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.2.11 (d)", "question": "Conclude that, if $d^{2}+2$ is squarefree, then the fundamental unit of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d^{2}+2})$ is $d^{2}+1+d\\sqrt{d^{2}+2}$ Compute the fundamental unit in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{3})$, $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{11})$, $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{51})$, and $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{66})$.", "solution": "Solution. (d) For all d, $d^{2}+2\\equiv2,3$ (mod 4) so, if d is squarefree, the fundamental unit in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d^{2}+2})$ is $p_{1}+q_{1}\\sqrt{d^{2}+2}=d^{2}+1+d\\sqrt{d^{2}+2}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.3.1", "question": "If $n^{2}-1$ is squarefree, show that $n+\\sqrt{n^{2}-1}$ is the fundamental unit of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{n^{2}-1})$.", "solution": "Solution. The continued fraction of $\\sqrt{n^{2}-1}$ is $[n-1,1,2(n-1)]$, so that the first two convergents are $(n-1)/1$ and $n/1$. Now apply Theorem 8.2.9.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.3.2", "question": "Determine the units of an imaginary quadratic field from first principles.", "solution": "Solution. We have already determined the units of $\\mathbb{Q}(i)$ and $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-3}).$ They are $\\pm1$, $\\pm i$ and $\\pm1$, $\\pm\\rho,\\pm\\rho^{2}$, respectively.\nNow we determine the units of an arbitrary field $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-d})$ where $-d\\equiv2,3$ (mod 4).\nAll units are of the form $a+b\\sqrt{-d}$ with $a^{2}+db^{2}=1$ It is easy to see that since $d\\ge2$, this has no solution except for $a=\\pm1,$ $b=0$ If $-d\\equiv1$ (mod 4), then units will be of the form $(a+b\\sqrt{-d})/2$ where $a\\equiv b$ (mod 2) and $a^{2}+db^{2}=4$ Since we already know the units for $d=3$ then $d\\ge7$ and once again, the only solution is $a=\\pm1$, $b=0$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.3.3", "question": "Suppose that $2^{2n}+1=dy^{2}$ with d squarefree. Show that $2^{n}+y\\sqrt{d}$ is the fundamental unit of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})$ whenever $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})\\ne\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{5})$", "solution": "Solution. Suppose not. Let $(a+b\\sqrt{d})/2$ be the fundamental unit. Then $2^{n}+y\\sqrt{d}=(\\frac{a+b\\sqrt{d}}{2})^{j}$ for some integer j. If an odd prime p divides j, we can write $2^{n}+y\\sqrt{d}=(\\frac{u+v\\sqrt{d}}{2})^{p}$ where $(u+v\\sqrt{d})/2$ is again a unit. Hence\n$2^{n+p}=\\sum_{k}\\binom{p}{2k}v^{2k}d^{k}u^{p-2k}=uA,$\nsay. Clearly, $(u,A)=1$ so we must have either $u=1$, $A=2^{n+p}$ or $u=2^{n+p}$, $A=1$ The latter case is impossible since $A=pv^{p-1}d^{(p-1)/2}>1.$ Hence $u=1$ But then $dv^{2}=5$ or -3. The former case is ruled out by the hypothesis and the latter is impossible.\nThus, if $2^{n}+y\\sqrt{d}$ is not the fundamental unit, it must be the square of a unit. But then, this means that $2^{n+4}+4y\\sqrt{d}=(u+v\\sqrt{d})^{2}=(u^{2}+dv^{2})+2uv\\sqrt{d}$ and this case is also easily ruled out.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.3.4 (a)", "question": "Determine the continued fraction expansion of $\\sqrt{51}$ and use it to obtain the fundamental unit $\\epsilon$ of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{51})$.", "solution": "Solution. See Exercise 8.2.11.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.3.4 (b)", "question": "Prove from first principles that all units of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{51})$ are given by $\\epsilon^{n}$, $n\\in\\mathbb{Z.}$", "solution": "Solution. See Exercise 8.2.11.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.3.5", "question": "Determine a unit $\\ne\\pm1$ in the ring of integers of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\theta)$ where $\\theta^{3}+6\\theta+8=0$.", "solution": "Solution. Consider $\\eta=1+\\theta.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.3.6", "question": "Let p be an odd prime $>3$ and suppose that it does not divide the class number of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{p})$ Show that $x^{p}+y^{p}+z^{p}=0$ is impossible for integers x, y, z such that $p\\nmid xyz$.", "solution": "Solution. We factor $x^{p}+y^{p}=\\prod_{i=0}^{p-1}(x+\\zeta_{p}^{i}y)=-z^{p}.$ Since $p\\nmid xyz$, the terms $(x+\\zeta_{p}^{i}y)$ are mutually coprime for $0\\le i\\le p-1.$ Moreover, viewing the equation as an ideal equation gives $(x+\\zeta_{p}^{i}y)=\\mathfrak{a}_{i}^{p}$ for some ideal $\\mathfrak{a}_{i}$. Since p does not divide the class number, $\\mathfrak{a}_{i}$ itself must be principal. Therefore $(x+\\zeta_{p}^{i}y)=\\epsilon\\alpha^{p}$, where $\\epsilon$ is a unit in $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{p})$ and a is an integer of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{p})$.\nBy Exercise 4.3.7, $\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{p}]$ is the ring of integers of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{p})$ and $1,\\zeta_{p},\\zeta_{p}^{2},...,\\zeta_{p}^{p-2}$ is an integral basis. Therefore, we can express $\\alpha=a_{0}+a_{1}\\zeta_{p}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{p-2}\\zeta_{p}^{p-2}$, so that $\\alpha^{p}\\equiv a_{0}^{p}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+a_{p-2}^{p}\\equiv a(mod~p);$, where $a=a_{0}+...+a_{p-2}$, by a simple application of Fermat's little Theorem (Exercise 1.1.13).\nAlso, we may write $\\epsilon=\\zeta_{p}^{s}\\eta$ where $0\\le s<p$ and $\\eta$ is a real unit, by Theorem 8.1.10. Hence, for $i=1$,\n$x+\\zeta_{p}y\\equiv\\zeta_{p}^{s}\\beta(mod~p)$\nwhere $\\beta$ is a real integer of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{p})$. Also, by complex conjugation,\n$x+\\zeta_{p}^{-1}y\\equiv\\zeta_{p}^{-s}\\beta(mod~p)$ .\nThen\n$\\zeta_{p}^{-s}(x+\\zeta_{p}y)-\\zeta_{p}^{s}(x+\\zeta_{p}^{-1}y)\\equiv0(mod~p).$\nSince $1,\\zeta_{p},...,\\zeta_{p}^{p-2}$ is an integral basis for $\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{p})$,\n$C_{0} + C_{1}\\zeta_p +... + C_{p-2}\\zeta_p^{p-2}=0 (mod p)$\nholds if and only if $c_{0}\\equiv c_{1}\\equiv\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\equiv c_{p-2}\\equiv0(mod~p)$.\nWrite $\\zeta_{p}^{p-s}(x+\\zeta_{p}y)-(\\zeta_{p}^{s}x+\\zeta_{p}^{s-1}y)\\equiv0(mod~p)$. If $2<s\\le p-2$ and $s\\ne(p+1)/2$ the powers of $\\zeta_{p}$ are all different and less than $p-1$ in the above congruence. Hence $x\\equiv y\\equiv0$ (mod p), a contradiction.\nIf $s=(p+1)/2$ then $x+\\zeta_{p}y\\equiv\\zeta_{p}x+y(mod~p)$ so that $x\\equiv y(mod~p)$. Similarly, $x\\equiv z(mod~p)$ so that $x^{p}+y^{p}+z^{p}\\equiv3x^{p}\\equiv0(mod~p)$. Since $p>3$, we get $p|x$ a contradiction.\nIf $s=0$, then $x+\\zeta_{p}y-(x+\\zeta_{p}^{-1}y)\\equiv0(mod~p)$ so that y = 0 (mod p), a contradiction.\nIf $s=1$, $\\zeta_{p}^{-1}x+y\\equiv\\zeta_{p}x+y$ (mod p) and so $p|x$, a contradiction.\nIf $s=2$, $x+\\zeta_{p}y\\equiv\\zeta_{p}^{4}x+\\zeta_{p}^{3}y$ and so $x\\equiv y\\equiv0(mod~p).$ again a contradiction.\nFinally, if $s=p-1,$ that is, $\\zeta_{p}(x+\\zeta_{p}y)\\equiv\\zeta_{p}^{-1}x+\\zeta_{p}^{-2}y(mod~p)$, $\\zeta_{p}^{3}(x+\\zeta_{p}y)\\equiv\\zeta_{p}x+y(mod~p).$ which gives $p|x$ (since $p\\ge5$, again a contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.3.7", "question": "Let K be a quadratic field of discriminant d. Let $P_{0}$ denote the group of principal fractional ideals $\\alpha\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ with $\\alpha\\in K$ satisfying $N_{K}(\\alpha)>0$. The quotient group $H_{0}$ of all nonzero fractional ideals modulo $P_{0}$ is called the restricted class group of K. Show that $H_{0}$ is a subgroup of the ideal class group H of K and $[H:H_{0}]\\le2$.", "solution": "Solution. If $d<0$, the norm of any nonzero element is greater than 0 and so the notions of restricted class group and ideal class group coincide. If $d>0$, then $H=H_{0}$ if and only if there exists a unit in K of norm -1. This is because $\\sqrt{d}\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$ is in the same coset of $\\mathcal{U}_{K}$ (mod $P_{0})$ if and only if $\\sqrt{d}=\\epsilon\\alpha$ with $N_{K}(\\alpha)>0$, and $\\epsilon$ is a unit. Since $N_{K}(\\sqrt{d})<0$, this can happen if and only if $\\epsilon$ is a unit of norm -1.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.3.8", "question": "Given an ideal a of a quadratic field K, let $\\mathfrak{a^{\\prime}}$ denote the conjugate ideal. If K has discriminant d, write $|d|=p_{1}^{\\alpha_{1}}p_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{t}$, where $p_{1}=2$, $\\alpha_{1}=0,2,$ or 3 and $p_{2},...,p_{t}$ are distinct odd primes. If we write $p_{i}\\mathcal{O}_{K}=\\rho_{i}^{2}$ show that for any ideal a of $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ satisfying $\\mathfrak{a}=\\mathfrak{a}^{\\prime}$ we can write\n$\\mathfrak{a}=r\\rho_{1}^{a_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\rho_{t}^{a_{t}}$,\n$r>0$ $a_{i}=0,$ 1 uniquely.", "solution": "Solution. We first factor a as a product of prime ideals. The fact that $\\mathfrak{a}=\\mathfrak{a}^{\\prime}$ implies that if a prime ideal divides a, so does $8^{\\prime}$. If is inert then it is principal and generated by a rational prime. If splits, then (which both occur in a with the same multiplicity) can be paired to give again a principal ideal generated by a rational prime. Only the ramified prime ideals cannot be so paired. Since $\\rho_{i}^{2}=p_{i}\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, we see immediately that a has a factorization of the form described above.\nIf we have another factorization $\\mathfrak{a}=r_{1}\\rho^{b_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\rho^{b_{t}}$ , $r_{1}>0$ $b_{i}=0,1$, then taking norms we obtain $r^{2}p_{1}^{a_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{t}^{a_{t}}=r_{1}^{2}p_{1}^{b_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{t}^{b_{t}}$ so that $a_{i}\\equiv b_{i}$ (mod 2). Since $a_{i}=0$ or 1, and $b_{i}=0$ or 1, this means $a_{i}=b_{i}$. Hence $r=r_{1}$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.3.9", "question": "An ideal class C of $H_{0}$ is said to be ambiguous if $C^{2}=1$ in $H_{0}.$ Show that any ambiguous ideal class is equivalent (in the restricted sense) to one of the at most $2^{t}$ ideal classes\n$\\rho_{1}^{a_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\rho_{t}^{a_{t}}$\n$a_{i}=0,1.$", "solution": "Solution. Let a be an ideal lying in an ambiguous class. Then $\\mathfrak{a}^{2}=(\\alpha)$ with $N_{K}(\\alpha)>0$ But we have $\\mathfrak{aa}^{\\prime}=(N_{K}(\\mathfrak{a}))$. Therefore\n$\\mathfrak{aa}^{\\prime}=(N_{K}(\\mathfrak{a})/\\alpha)(\\alpha)=(N_{K}(\\mathfrak{a})/\\alpha)\\mathfrak{a}^{2}$\nso that $\\mathfrak{a}=\\mathfrak{a}^{\\prime}$ By the previous question, a can be written as\n$r\\rho_{1}^{a_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\rho_{t}^{a_{t}}$.\n$r>0$, $a_{i}=0,1$ . In the restricted class group, these form at most $2^{t}$ ideal classes.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.3.10", "question": "With the notation as in the previous two questions, show that there is exactly one relation of the form\n$\\rho_{1}^{a_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\rho_{t}^{a_{t}}=\\rho\\mathcal{O}_{K}$ , $N_{K}(\\rho)>0$\nwith $a_{i}=0$ or 1, $\\sum_{i=1}^{t}a_{i}>0$", "solution": "Solution. We first show there is at least one such relation. If $d<0$, then $\\rho_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\rho_{t}=(\\sqrt{d})$ If $d>0$ let $\\epsilon$ be a generator of all the totally positive units of K (i.e., units $\\epsilon>0$ and $\\epsilon^{\\prime}>0)$. Set $\\mu=\\sqrt{d}(1-\\epsilon)$ . Then $\\mu^{\\prime}=-\\sqrt{d}(1-\\epsilon^{\\prime})$ so that $\\epsilon\\mu^{\\prime}=-\\sqrt{d}(\\epsilon-1)=\\mu.$ Therefore $(\\mu)=(\\mu^{\\prime})$ and by the penultimate question, we have the result.\nTo establish uniqueness, consider first the case $d<0.$ If\n$\\rho_{1}^{a_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\rho_{t}^{a_{t}}=\\rho\\mathcal{O}_{K}$, $N_{K}(\\rho)>0$\nthen $(\\rho)=(\\rho^{\\prime})$ since $\\rho_{i}^{\\prime}=\\rho_{i}$ . Therefore $\\rho=b\\sqrt{d}$ for some $b\\in\\mathbb{Q}$ The other two cases of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-1})$ are $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{-3})$ are similarly dealt with.\nIf now $d>0$, then $\\rho=\\eta\\rho^{\\prime}$ with $\\eta$ a totally positive unit. We write $\\eta=\\epsilon^{m}$ for some m. With $\\mu$ defined as above, notice that $\\rho/\\mu^{m}=\\rho^{\\prime}/(\\mu^{\\prime})^{m}$ so that $\\rho/\\mu^{m}=r\\in\\mathbb{Q}$. Hence $(\\rho)=(\\mu)^{m}$. Since ( ) has order 2 in the (restricted) class group we are done.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.3.11", "question": "Let K be a quadratic field of discriminant d. Show that the number of ambiguous ideal classes is $2^{t-1}$ where t is the number of distinct primes dividing d. Deduce that $2^{t-1}$ divides the order of the class group.", "solution": "Solution. This is now immediate from the previous two exercises. Since the restricted class group has index 1 or 2 in the ideal class group, the divisibility assertion follows.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.3.12", "question": "If K is a quadratic field of discriminant d and class number 1, show that d is prime or $d=4$ or 8.", "solution": "Solution. If d has t distinct prime divisors, then $2^{t-1}$ divides the class number. Thus $t\\le1$ Since the discriminant is either squarefree or four times a squarefree number, the result is now clear.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.3.13", "question": "If a real quadratic field K has odd class number, show that K has a unit of norm-1.", "solution": "Solution. Since K has odd class number, $H=H_{0}$ This means there is a unit of norm -1.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.3.14", "question": "Show that $15+4\\sqrt{14}$ is the fundamental unit of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{14}).$", "solution": "Solution. The continued fraction development of $\\sqrt{14}$ is [3, 1, 2, 1,6] and the convergents are easily computed: $\\frac{3}{1},\\frac{4}{1},\\frac{11}{3},\\frac{15}{4},....$\nBy Theorem 8.2.9, we find that $15+4\\sqrt{14}$ is the fundamental unit.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.3.15", "question": "In Chapter 6 we showed that $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{14}]$ is a PID (principal ideal domain). Assume the following hypothesis: given $\\alpha, \\beta\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{14}]$, such that $gcd(\\alpha,\\beta)=1$ there is a prime $\\pi\\equiv\\alpha$ (mod 3) for which the fundamental unit $\\epsilon=15+4\\sqrt{14}$ generates the coprime residue classes (mod $\\pi$). Show that $\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{14}]$ is Euclidean.", "solution": "Solution. We define the Euclidean algorithm inductively as follows. For $u\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{14}]$ define $\\varphi(u)=1$ If $\\pi$ generates the residue classes (mod $\\pi$), where $\\pi$ is prime, define $\\varphi(\\pi)=2$ If $\\beta$ is a prime for which $\\epsilon$ does not generate the residue classes (mod 3), define $\\varphi(\\beta)=3.$ Now for any $\\gamma\\in \\mathbb{Z}[\\sqrt{14}]$ factor $\\gamma=\\pi_{1}^{e_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\pi_{r}^{e_{r}}\\beta_{1}^{f_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\beta_{s}^{f_{s}}$ where $\\varphi(\\pi_{i})=2$, $\\varphi(\\beta_{i})=3.$ Define $\\varphi(\\gamma)=2(e_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+e_{r})+3(f_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+f_{s})$. An easy induction argument using the Chinese Remainder Theorem (Theorem 5.3.13) shows that is a Euclidean algorithm.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.3.16", "question": "Let $d=a^{2}+1$. Show that if $|u^{2}-dv^{2}|\\ne0,1$ for integers u, v, then $|u^{2}-dv^{2}|>\\sqrt{d}.$", "solution": "Solution. The continued fraction expansion of $\\sqrt{d}$ is $[a,2a,2a,...]$ and the convergents $p_{k}/q_{k}$ always satisfy $p_{k}^{2}-dq_{k}^{2}=\\pm1$ If $|u^{2}-dv^{2}|<\\sqrt{d},$ then $u/v$ is a convergent of $\\sqrt{d},$ by Exercise 8.2.5. Since $|u^{2}-dv^{2}|\\ne0,1$, we are done.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "Exercise 8.3.17", "question": "Suppose that n is odd, $n\\ge5$, and that $n^{2g}+1=d$ is squarefree. Show that the class group of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})$ has an element of order 2g.", "solution": "Solution. We have $(n)^{2g}=(\\sqrt{d}-1)(\\sqrt{d}+1)$. Since n is odd, each of the ideals $(-1+\\sqrt{d})$ and $(1+\\sqrt{d})$ must be coprime. By Exercise 5.3.12, each of them must be a 2gth power. Therefore\n$\\mathfrak{a}^{2g}=(\\sqrt{d}-1)$ and $(\\mathfrak{a}^{\\prime})^{2g}=(\\sqrt{d}+1)$\nWe claim that a has order greater than or equal to g. Observe that $n^{2g}+1\\equiv$ 2 (mod 4) because n is odd. Therefore 1, $\\sqrt{d}$ is an integral basis of $\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{d})$. If $\\mathfrak{a}^{m}$ were principal, then $\\mathfrak{a}^{m}=(u+v\\sqrt{d})$ implies that $n^{m}=|u^{2}-dv^{2}|$ which by the previous exercise is either 0,1 or $>\\sqrt{d}.$ The former cannot hold since $n\\ge5$ Thus,\n$n^{m}>\\sqrt{d}=\\sqrt{n^{2g}+1}>n^{g}.$\nHence, $m>g.$ Since m| 2g, we must have that a has order 2g.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.1.2}", "question": "If $\\pi\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$ is such that $N(\\pi)=p$ a rational prime, show that $\\pi$ is a prime of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$.", "solution": "If $\\pi$ factored in $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$, then $\\pi=\\alpha\\beta$ and $p=N(\\pi)=N(\\alpha)N(\\beta)$ which implies that $N(\\alpha)=1$ or $N(\\beta)=1$ so that $\\pi$ cannot be factored nontrivially in $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.1.3a}", "question": "If $p$ is a rational prime congruent to 2 (mod 3), show that $p$ is prime in $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$.", "solution": "Let $p\\equiv2$ (mod 3) be a rational prime. If $p=\\pi\\gamma$, with $N(\\gamma) > 1, N(\\pi)>1$, then $p^{2}=N(\\pi)N(\\gamma)$ implies that $N(\\pi)=p$ and $N(\\gamma)=p.$ Writing $\\pi=a+b\\rho$, we find $p=N(\\pi)=a^{2}-ab+b^{2}$ so that $4p=4a^{2}-4ab+4b^{2}=(2a-b)^{2}+3b^{2}$. Hence $p\\equiv(2a-b)^{2}$ (mod 3), a contradiction since 2 is not a square mod 3.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.1.4}", "question": "Let $\\pi$ be a prime of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$. Show that $\\alpha^{N(\\pi)-1}\\equiv1 \\pmod \\pi$ for all $\\alpha\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$ which are coprime to $\\pi$.", "solution": "Since $\\pi$ is prime, the ideal $(\\pi)$ is prime. Hence $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]/(\\pi)$ is a field, containing $N(\\pi)$ elements. Its multiplicative group, consisting of classes coprime to $\\pi$, has $N(\\pi)-1$ elements. Thus, by Lagrange's theorem, the result is immediate.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.1.5a}", "question": "Let $\\pi$ be a prime not associated to $(1-\\rho)$. First show that $3|N(\\pi)-1$.", "solution": "By Exercise 9.1.3, we know that $\\pi|(\\alpha^{N(\\pi)-1}-1)$. By Exercise 9.1.4, we know $N(\\pi)\\equiv1$ (mod 3).", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.1.5b}", "question": "Let $\\pi$ be a prime not associated to $(1-\\rho)$. If $(\\alpha,\\pi)=1$, show that there is a unique integer $m=0, 1$ or 2 such that $\\alpha^{(N(\\pi)-1)/3}\\equiv\\rho^{m} \\pmod \\pi$.", "solution": "We can write $\\beta=\\alpha^{(N(\\pi)-1)/3}$ and observe that $\\beta^{3}-1=(\\beta-1)(\\beta-\\rho)(\\beta-\\rho^{2})$. Since $\\pi$ is prime and divides $\\beta^{3}-1,$ it must divide one of the three factors on the right. If $\\pi$ divides at least two factors, then $\\pi|(1-\\rho)$ which means $\\pi$ is an associate of $1-\\rho$, contrary to assumption. Thus, $\\beta\\equiv1, \\rho, \\text{or } \\rho^{2} \\pmod \\pi$ as desired.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.1.6a}", "question": "Show that $(\\alpha/\\pi)_{3}=1$ if and only if $x^{3}\\equiv\\alpha \\pmod \\pi$ is solvable in $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$.", "solution": "Clearly if $x^{3}\\equiv\\alpha \\pmod \\pi$ has a solution, then by Exercise 9.1.4, $\\alpha^{(N(\\pi)-1)/3}\\equiv1 \\pmod \\pi$ so that $(\\alpha/\\pi)_{3}=1$. For the converse, let $g$ be a primitive root of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]/(\\pi)$. Then, writing $\\alpha=g^{r}$ we find $g^{(rN(\\pi)-1)/3}\\equiv1 \\pmod \\pi$ so that $\\frac{r(N(\\pi)-1)}{3}\\equiv0 \\pmod{N(\\pi)-1}$. Hence $3 | r$, and $\\alpha$ is a cube mod $\\pi$. That is, $x^{3}\\equiv\\alpha \\pmod \\pi$ has a solution. This proves (a).", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.1.6b}", "question": "Show that $(\\alpha\\beta/\\pi)_{3}=(\\alpha/\\pi)_{3}(\\beta/\\pi)_{3}$.", "solution": "$(\\frac{\\alpha\\beta}{\\pi})_{3}\\equiv(\\alpha\\beta)^{(N(\\pi)-1)/3}\\equiv\\alpha^{(N(\\pi)-1)/3}\\beta^{(N(\\pi)-1)/3} \\equiv(\\frac{\\alpha}{\\pi})_{3}(\\frac{\\beta}{\\pi})_{3} \\pmod \\pi.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.1.6c}", "question": "Show that if $\\alpha\\equiv\\beta \\pmod \\pi$, then $(\\alpha/\\pi)_{3}=(\\beta/\\pi)_{3}$.", "solution": "If $\\alpha\\equiv\\beta \\pmod \\pi$ then $(\\frac{\\alpha}{\\pi})_{3}\\equiv\\alpha^{(N(\\pi)-1)/3}\\equiv\\beta^{(N(\\pi)-1)/3}\\equiv(\\frac{\\beta}{\\pi})_{3} \\pmod \\pi.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.1.7a}", "question": "Show that $\\overline{\\chi_{\\pi}(\\alpha)}=\\chi_{\\pi}(\\alpha)^{2}=\\chi_{\\pi}(\\alpha^{2}).$", "solution": "$\\chi_{\\pi}(\\alpha)$ is by definition one of $1, \\rho, \\text{or } \\rho^{2}$ so that (a) is immediate.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.1.9}", "question": "Let $N(\\pi)=p\\equiv1$ (mod 3). Among the associates of $\\pi$, show there is a unique one which is primary.", "solution": "Write $\\pi=a+b\\rho.$ All the associates of $\\pi$ can be written down: $a+b\\rho,-b+(a-b)\\rho,(b-a)-a\\rho,-a-b\\rho,b+(b-a)\\rho,(a-b)+a\\rho$. Since $p=a^{2}-ab+b^{2}$, not both $a$ and $b$ are divisible by 3. If $b\\equiv0$ (mod 3), then $\\pi\\equiv1$ (mod 3) implies $a\\equiv1$ (mod 3) so that $-a\\equiv2$ (mod 3) and hence $-a-b\\rho$ is the primary. If $a\\equiv0$ (mod 3) then one of $(b-a)-a\\rho$ or $(a-b)+a\\rho$ is primary. If both $a$ and $b$ are coprime to 3, then we must have $a\\equiv b$ (mod 3), for otherwise $3|p,$ contrary to assumption. Thus $a\\equiv b\\equiv\\pm1$ (mod 3), so that one of $b+(b-a)\\rho$ or $-b+(a-b)\\rho$ is primary, as desired.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Theorem 9.1.10}", "question": "Prove Theorem 9.1.10: If $\\chi\\ne\\chi_{0}$, then $|g(\\chi)|=\\sqrt{p}$.", "solution": "We first observe that $a\\ne0$ and $\\chi\\ne\\chi_{0}$ together imply that $g_{a}(\\chi)=\\chi(a^{-1})g(\\chi)$ because $\\chi(a)g_{a}(\\chi) = \\chi(a)\\sum_{t\\in\\mathbb{F}_{p}}\\chi(t)\\zeta^{at} = \\sum_{t\\in\\mathbb{F}_{p}}\\chi(at)\\zeta^{at} = g(\\chi)$. With our conventions that $\\chi_{0}(0)=1$ we see for $a\\ne0$, $g_{a}(\\chi_{0})=\\sum_{t\\in\\mathbb{F}_{p}}\\zeta^{at}=0,$ since this is just the sum of the $p$th roots of unity. Finally, $g_{0}(\\chi)=0$ if $\\chi\\ne\\chi_{0}$ and $g_{0}(\\chi_{0})=p$. Now, by our first observation, $\\sum_{a\\in\\mathbb{F}_{p}}g_{a}(\\chi)\\overline{g_{a}(\\chi)}=|g(\\chi)|^{2}(p-1).$ On the other hand, $\\sum_{a\\in\\mathbb{F}_{p}}g_{a}(\\chi)\\overline{g_{a}(\\chi)}=\\sum_{s\\in\\mathbb{F}_{p}}\\sum_{t\\in\\mathbb{F}_{p}}\\chi(s)\\overline{\\chi(t)}\\sum_{a\\in\\mathbb{F}_{p}}\\zeta^{as-at}.$ If $s\\ne t$, the innermost sum is zero, being the sum of all the $p$th roots of unity. If $s=t$ the sum is $p$. Hence $|g(\\chi)|^{2}=p.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.1.11}", "question": "If $\\chi_{1},...,\\chi_{r}$ are nontrivial and the product $\\chi_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\chi_{r}$ is also nontrivial prove that $g(\\chi_{1})\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot g(\\chi_{r})=J(\\chi_{1},...,\\chi_{r})g(\\chi_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\chi_{r})$.", "solution": "Define $\\psi:\\mathbb{F}_{p}\\rightarrow\\mathbb{C}$ by $\\psi(t)=\\zeta^{t}$. Then $\\psi(t_{1}+t_{2})=\\psi(t_{1})\\psi(t_{2})$ and we can write $g(\\chi)=\\sum_{t}\\chi(t)\\psi(t).$ This is just for notational convenience. Now $g(\\chi_{1})\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot g(\\chi_{r}) = (\\sum_{t_{1}}\\chi_{1}(t_{1})\\psi(t_{1}))\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot(\\sum_{t_{r}}\\chi_{r}(t_{r})\\psi(t_{r})) = \\sum_{s}\\psi(s)(\\sum_{t_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+t_{r}=s}\\chi_{1}(t_{1})\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\chi_{r}(t_{r}))$. If $s\\ne0$, writing $t_{i}=su_{i}$, the inner sum becomes $(\\chi_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\chi_{r})(s)J(\\chi_{1},...,\\chi_{r})$. If $s=0$, then the inner sum is $\\sum_{t_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+t_{r}=0}\\chi_{1}(t_{1})\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\chi_{r}(t_{r})=0$ since $t_{1},...,t_{r-1}$ can be chosen arbitrarily so that $t_{r}=-t_{1}-\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot-t_{r-1}$, and each of the sums corresponding to $t_{1},...,t_{r-1}$ is zero since $\\chi_{1},...,\\chi_{r}$ are nontrivial. This completes the proof.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.1.12}", "question": "If $\\chi_{1},...,\\chi_{r}$ are nontrivial, and $\\chi_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\chi_{r}$ is trivial, show that $g(\\chi_{1})\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot g(\\chi_{r})=\\chi_{r}(-1)pJ(\\chi_{1},...,\\chi_{r-1}).$", "solution": "By the previous exercise, $g(\\chi_{1})\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot g(\\chi_{r-1})=J(\\chi_{1},...,\\chi_{r-1})g(\\chi_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\chi_{r-1})$. Multiplying both sides of the equation by $g(\\chi_{r})$ leads us to evaluate $g(\\chi_{r})g(\\chi_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\chi_{r-1})$. However, $(\\chi_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\chi_{r-1})\\chi_{r}=\\chi_{0}$ means that $g(\\chi_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\chi_{r-1})=g(\\overline{\\chi_{r}})=\\chi_{r}(-1)p$ by the proof of Theorem 9.1.10.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Lemma 9.1.13}", "question": "Prove Lemma 9.1.13: Let $\\pi$ be a prime of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$ such that $N(\\pi)=p\\equiv1$ (mod 3). The character $\\chi_{\\pi}$ introduced above can be viewed as a character of the finite field $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]/(\\pi)$ of $p$ elements. Show that $J(\\chi_{\\pi},\\chi_{\\pi})=\\pi$.", "solution": "If $\\chi$ is any cubic character, Exercise 9.1.12 shows that $g(\\chi)^{3}= pJ(\\chi,\\chi)$ since $\\chi(-1)=1$. We can write $J(\\chi,\\chi)=a+b\\rho$ for some $a, b\\in\\mathbb{Z}$. But $g(\\chi)^{3}=(\\sum_{t}\\chi(t)\\zeta^{t})^{3} \\equiv\\sum_{t}\\chi^{3}(t)\\zeta^{3t} \\pmod{3} \\equiv\\sum_{t\\ne0}\\zeta^{3t} \\pmod{3} \\equiv-1 \\pmod{3}$. Therefore, $a+b\\rho\\equiv-1 \\pmod{3}$. In a similar way, $g(\\overline{\\chi})^{3}\\equiv a+b\\overline{\rho}\\equiv-1 \\pmod{3}$. Thus, $b\\sqrt{-3}\\equiv0 \\pmod{3}$ which means $-3b^{2}/9$ is an algebraic integer and by Exercise 3.1.2, it is an ordinary integer. Thus, $b\\equiv0 \\pmod{3}$ and $a\\equiv-1 \\pmod{3}$. Also, from Exercise 9.1.12 and Theorem 9.1.10, it is clear that $|J(\\chi,\\chi)|^{2}=p=J(\\chi,\\chi)\\overline{J(\\chi,\\chi)}$. Therefore, $J(\\chi,\\chi)$ is a primary prime of norm $p$. Set $J(\\chi_{\\pi},\\chi_{\\pi})=\\pi^{\\prime}$. Since $\\pi\\overline{\\pi}=p=\\pi^{\\prime}\\overline{\\pi^{\\prime}}$, we have $\\pi|\\pi^{\\prime}$ or $\\pi|\\overline{\\pi^{\\prime}}.$ We want to eliminate the latter possibility. By definition, $J(\\chi_{\\pi},\\chi_{\\pi})=\\sum_{t}\\chi_{\\pi}(t)\\chi_{\\pi}(1-t) \\equiv\\sum_{t}t^{(p-1)/3}(1-t)^{(p-1)/3} \\pmod \\pi.$ The polynomial $x^{(p-1)/3}(1-x)^{(p-1)/3}$ has degree $\\frac{2}{3}(p-1)<p-1.$ Let $g$ be a primitive root (mod $\\pi$). Then $\\sum_{t}t^{j}=\\sum_{a=0}^{p-2}g^{aj}\\equiv0 \\pmod \\pi$ if $g^{j}\\not\\equiv1 \\pmod \\pi$ which is the case since $j<p-1$. Thus, $J(\\chi_{\\pi},\\chi_{\\pi})\\equiv0 \\pmod \\pi$. Therefore $\\pi|\\pi^{\\prime}$ as desired.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.1.14}", "question": "Show that $g(\\chi)^{3}=p\\pi.$", "solution": "By Exercise 9.1.12, $g(\\chi)^{3}=pJ(\\chi,\\chi)$ and by the previous exercise, $J(\\chi,\\chi)=\\pi.$", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Lemma 9.1.15}", "question": "Prove Lemma 9.1.15: Let $\\pi_{1}=q\\equiv2$ (mod 3) and $\\pi_{2}=\\pi$ be a prime of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$ of norm $p$. Show that $\\chi_{\\pi}(q)=\\chi_{q}(\\pi)$.", "solution": "Let $\\chi_{\\pi}=\\chi,$ and consider the Jacobi sum $J(\\chi,...,\\chi)$ with $q$ terms. Since $3 \\nmid q+1$, we have, by Exercise 9.1.12, $g(\\chi)^{q+1}=pJ(\\chi,...,\\chi)$. By Exercise 9.1.14, $g(\\chi)^{3}=p\\pi$ so that $g(\\chi)^{q+1}=(p\\pi)^{(q+1)/3}$. Recall that $J(\\chi,...,\\chi)=\\sum\\chi(t_{1})\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\chi(t_{q})$, where the sum is over all $t_{1},...,t_{q}\\in\\mathbb{Z}/p\\mathbb{Z}$ such that $t_{1}+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+t_{q}=1$. The term in which $t_{1}=\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot=t_{q}$ satisfies $qt_{1}=1$ and so $\\chi(q)\\chi(t_{1})=1.$ Raising both sides to the $q$th power and noting that $q\\equiv2$ (mod 3) gives $\\chi(q)^{2}\\chi(t_{1})^{q}=1$ and so $\\chi(t_{1})^{q}=\\chi(q)$. Therefore, the \"diagonal\" term which corresponds to $t_{1}=\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot=t_{q}$ has the value $\\chi(q)$. If not all the $t_{i}$ are equal, then we get $q$ different $q$-tuples from a cyclic permutation of $(t_{1},...,t_{q}).$ Thus $J(\\chi,...,\\chi)\\equiv\\chi(q)$ (mod $q$). Hence $(p\\pi)^{(q+1)/3}\\equiv p\\chi(q) \\pmod q$ so that $p^{(q-2)/3}\\pi^{(q+1)/3} \\equiv \\chi(q) \\pmod q$. We raise both sides of this congruence to the $(q-1)$ st power (recalling that $q-1\\equiv1$ (mod 3)): $p^{(q-2)(q-1)/3}\\pi^{(q^{2}-1)/3}\\equiv\\chi(q)^{q-1}\\equiv\\chi(q) \\pmod q.$ By Fermat's little Theorem, $p^{q-1}\\equiv1 \\pmod q$. Therefore, $\\chi_{\\pi}(q)\\equiv\\pi^{(q^{2}-1)/3}\\equiv\\chi_{q}(\\pi)$ (mod $q$) so that $\\chi_{\\pi}(q)=\\chi_{q}(\\pi)$ as desired.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.1.17}", "question": "Let $\\pi$ be a prime of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\rho]$. Show that $x^{3}\\equiv2 \\pmod \\pi$ has a solution if and only if $\\pi\\equiv1 \\pmod 2$.", "solution": "We first observe that $x^{3}\\equiv2 \\pmod \\pi$ is solvable if and only if $x^{3}\\equiv2 \\pmod{\\pi^{\\prime}}$ is solvable for any associate $\\pi^{\\prime}$ of $\\pi$. Thus we may assume that $\\pi$ is primary. If $\\pi=q$ is a rational prime, then $\\chi_{q}(2)=\\chi_{2}(q)=\\chi_{2}(1)=1$ so that 2 is a cubic residue for all such primes. If $\\pi=a+b\\rho$ is primary, by cubic reciprocity, $\\chi_{\\pi}(2)=\\chi_{2}(\\pi)$. The norm of (2) is 4 and $\\pi=\\pi^{(4-1)/3}\\equiv\\chi_{2}(\\pi) \\pmod 2$. Thus $\\chi_{\\pi}(2)=\\chi_{2}(\\pi)=1$ if and only if $\\pi\\equiv1 \\pmod 2$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.1}", "question": "Let $\\wp$ be a prime ideal of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{m}]$ not containing $m$. Let $q$ be its norm. Show that $q\\equiv1$ (mod $m$) and that $1,\\zeta_{m},\\zeta_{m}^{2},...,\\zeta_{m}^{m-1}$ are distinct coset representatives mod $\\wp$.", "solution": "Observe that $\\frac{x^{m}-1}{x-1}=1+x+\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot+x^{m-1}=\\prod_{i=1}^{m-1}(x-\\zeta_{m}^{i}).$ Putting $x=1$ in this identity gives $m=\\prod_{i=1}^{m-1}(1-\\zeta_{m}^{i}).$ If $\\zeta_{m}^{i}\\equiv\\zeta_{m}^{j} \\pmod \\wp$ (say), then $\\zeta_{m}^{j-i}\\equiv1 \\pmod \\wp$ so that $m\\equiv0 \\pmod \\wp$, contrary to $m\\notin\\wp$. Thus $1,\\zeta_{m},...,\\zeta_{m}^{m-1}$ are distinct mod $\\wp$. Moreover, the cosets they represent form a multiplicative subgroup of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{m}]/\\wp$ of order $m$. Since $(\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{m}]/\\wp)^{*}$ has order $q-1=N(\\wp)-1$, we must have $m|q-1$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.2}", "question": "Let $\\alpha\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{m}]$, $\\alpha\\notin\\wp$. Show that there is a unique integer $i$ (modulo $m$) such that $\\alpha^{(q-1)/m}\\equiv\\zeta_{m}^{i} \\pmod \\wp$.", "solution": "Since $(\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{m}]/\\wp)^{*}$ has $q-1$ elements, we have $\\alpha^{q-1}\\equiv1 \\pmod \\wp$. Thus $\\prod_{i=1}^{m-1}(\\alpha^{(q-1)/m}-\\zeta_{m}^{i})\\equiv0 \\pmod \\wp$. Since $\\wp$ is a prime ideal, there is an integer $i$, $0\\le i<m$, such that $\\alpha^{(q-1)/m}\\equiv\\zeta_{m}^{i} \\pmod \\wp.$ This $i$ is unique by Exercise 9.2.1.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.3a}", "question": "Show that $(\\alpha/\\wp)_{m}=1$ if and only if $x^{m}\\equiv\\alpha \\pmod \\wp$ is solvable in $\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{m}]$.", "solution": "If $x^{m}\\equiv\\alpha \\pmod \\wp$ has a solution, then $\\alpha^{(N(\\wp)-1)/m}\\equiv x^{N(\\wp)-1}\\equiv1 \\pmod \\wp$ by the analogue of Fermat's little Theorem. Thus, $(\\alpha/\\wp)_{m}=1$. For the converse, we know that $(\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{m}]/\\wp)^{*}$ is cyclic, being the multiplicative group of a finite field. Let $g$ be a generator, and set $\\alpha=g^{r}$. If $(\\alpha/\\wp)=1$, then $\\alpha^{(q-1)/m}\\equiv1 \\pmod \\wp$. Hence $g^{r(q-1)/m}\\equiv1 \\pmod \\wp$. Since $g$ has order $q-1$ we must have $r\\frac{q-1}{m}\\equiv0 \\pmod{q-1}.$ Hence, $m|r$, so that $\\alpha$ is an $m$th power. This proves (a).", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.3b}", "question": "Show that for all $\\alpha\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{m}],$ $\\alpha^{(N(\\wp)-1)/m}\\equiv(\\alpha/\\wp)_{m} \\pmod \\wp$.", "solution": "We need only note the case $\\alpha\\equiv0 \\pmod \\wp$ which is clear.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.3c}", "question": "Show that $(\\alpha\\beta/\\wp)_{m}=(\\alpha/\\wp)_{m}(\\beta/\\wp)_{m}$.", "solution": "Parts (c) and (d) are proved exactly as in the case of the cubic residue symbol in Exercise 9.1.6.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.3d}", "question": "Show that if $\\alpha\\equiv\\beta \\pmod \\wp$, then $(\\alpha/\\wp)_{m}=(\\beta/\\wp)_{m}$.", "solution": "Parts (c) and (d) are proved exactly as in the case of the cubic residue symbol in Exercise 9.1.6.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.4}", "question": "If $\\wp$ is a prime ideal of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{m}]$ not containing $m$, show that $(\\frac{\\zeta_{m}}{\\wp})_{m}=\\zeta_{m}^{(N(\\wp)-1)/m}$.", "solution": "By definition, $(\\frac{\\zeta_{m}}{\\wp})_{m}\\equiv\\zeta_{m}^{(N(\\wp)-1)/m} \\pmod \\wp$. Since both $(\\zeta_{m}/\\wp)_{m}$ and $\\zeta_{m}^{(N(\\wp)-1)/m}$ are $m$th roots of unity and by Exercise 9.2.1, distinct roots represent distinct classes, we must have $(\\frac{\\zeta_{m}}{\\wp})_{m}=\\zeta_{m}^{(N(\\wp)-1)/m}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.5a}", "question": "Suppose $\\mathfrak{a}$ and $\\mathfrak{b}$ are ideals coprime to $(m)$. Show that $(\\alpha\\beta/\\mathfrak{a})_{m}=(\\alpha/\\mathfrak{a})_{m}(\\beta/\\mathfrak{a})_{m}$.", "solution": "Parts (a) and (b) are immediate from Exercise 9.2.3.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.5b}", "question": "Suppose $\\mathfrak{a}$ and $\\mathfrak{b}$ are ideals coprime to $(m)$. Show that $(\\alpha/\\mathfrak{ab})_{m}=(\\alpha/\\mathfrak{a})_{m}(\\beta/\\mathfrak{b})_{m}$.", "solution": "Parts (a) and (b) are immediate from Exercise 9.2.3.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.5c}", "question": "Suppose $\\mathfrak{a}$ and $\\mathfrak{b}$ are ideals coprime to $(m)$. If $\\mathfrak{a}$ is prime to $\\alpha$ and $x^{m}\\equiv\\alpha \\pmod{\\mathfrak{a}}$ is solvable in $\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{m}]$ then $(\\alpha/\\mathfrak{a})_{m}=1.$", "solution": "For (c), we note that $x^{m}\\equiv\\alpha \\pmod \\wp$ has a solution for every prime ideal $\\wp$ dividing $\\mathfrak{a}$. Thus by Exercise 9.2.3 (a), $(\\alpha/\\wp)_{m}=1$ for every prime ideal dividing $\\mathfrak{a}$. thus, $(\\alpha/\\mathfrak{a})_{m}=1$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.6}", "question": "Show that the converse of (c) in the previous exercise is not necessarily true.", "solution": "Choose two distinct prime ideals $\\wp_{1}$ $\\wp_{2}$ coprime to $(m)$. The map $\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{m}]/\\wp_{1}\\rightarrow\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{m}]/\\wp_{1}$, $\\beta \\pmod{\\wp_1} \\mapsto \\beta^{(N(\\wp_1)-1)/m} \\pmod{\\wp_1}$ is a homomorphism with kernel consisting of the subgroup of $m$th powers by Exercise 9.2.3 (a). This subgroup has size $(N(\\wp_{1})-1)/m.$ Hence the image is the subgroup of $m$th roots of unity. Thus, we can find $\\beta, \\gamma$ so that $\\beta^{(N(\\wp_{1})-1)/m}\\equiv\\zeta_{m} \\pmod{\\wp_{1}},$ $\\gamma^{(N(\\wp_{2})-1)/m}\\equiv\\zeta_{m}^{m-1} \\pmod{\\wp_{2}}$. By the Chinese Remainder Theorem (Theorem 5.3.13), we can find $\\alpha\\equiv\\beta \\pmod{\\wp_{1}},$ $\\alpha\\equiv\\gamma \\pmod{\\wp_{2}}.$ Then $(\\alpha/\\wp_{1})_{m}=(\\beta/\\wp_{1})_{m}=\\zeta_{m}, (\\alpha/\\wp_{2})_{m}=(\\gamma/\\wp_{2})_{m}=\\zeta_{m}^{m-1}$, and therefore $(\\alpha/\\wp_{1}\\wp_{2})_{m}=1$. But then $x^{m}\\equiv\\alpha \\pmod{\\wp_{1}\\wp_{2}}$ has no solution because neither $x^{m}\\equiv\\alpha \\pmod{\\wp_{1}}$ nor $x^{m}\\equiv\\alpha \\pmod{\\wp_{2}}$ has a solution.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.7}", "question": "If $\\alpha\\in\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{l}]$ is coprime to $l$, show that there is an integer $c\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ (unique mod $l$) such that $\\zeta_{l}^{c}\\alpha$ is primary.", "solution": "Let $\\lambda=1-\\zeta_{l}$. Since the prime ideal $(\\lambda)$ has degree 1, there is an $a\\in\\mathbb{Z}$ such that $\\alpha\\equiv a \\pmod \\lambda$. Hence $(\\alpha-a)/\\lambda\\equiv b \\pmod \\lambda$. So we can write $\\alpha\\equiv a+b\\lambda \\pmod{\\lambda^{2}}$. Since $\\zeta_{l}=1-\\lambda$, we have $\\zeta_{l}^{c}\\equiv1-c\\lambda \\pmod{\\lambda^{2}}$. Thus, $\\zeta_{l}^{c}\\alpha\\equiv(1-c\\lambda)(a+b\\lambda)\\equiv a+(b-ac)\\lambda \\pmod{\\lambda^{2}}$. Now, $(a,l)=1$ for otherwise $\\lambda|\\alpha$ contrary to assumption. Choose $c$ so that $ac\\equiv b \\pmod \\lambda$. Then $\\zeta_{l}^{c}\\alpha\\equiv a \\pmod{\\lambda^{2}}$. Moreover $c$ is clearly unique mod $l$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.8}", "question": "With notation as above ($x^l+y^l+z^l=0$, etc.), show that $(x+\\zeta^{i}y)$ and $(x+\\zeta^{j}y)$ are coprime in $\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{l}]$ whenever $i\\ne j$ $0\\le i, j<l$.", "solution": "Suppose $\\mathfrak{a}$ is an ideal of $\\mathbb{Z}[\\zeta_{l}]$ which contains both $(x+\\zeta^{i}y)$ and $(x+\\zeta^{j}y)$ Then $(\\zeta^{j}-\\zeta^{i})y\\in\\mathfrak{a}$ and $(\\zeta^{j}-\\zeta^{i})x=\\zeta^{j}(x+\\zeta^{i}y)-\\zeta^{i}(x+\\zeta^{j}y)\\in\\mathfrak{a}$. Since $x$ and $y$ are coprime, we deduce that $(\\zeta^{j}-\\zeta^{i})\\in\\mathfrak{a}.$ By Exercise 4.3.7 or by 4.5.9, we deduce that $\\mathfrak{a}$ and $(l)$ are not coprime. Since $(l)$ is totally ramified and $(l)=(1-\\zeta)^{l-1}$ we see that $(1-\\zeta)=\\lambda\\in\\mathfrak{a}$. Thus $(z)\\in(\\lambda)$ which implies $l|z$ contrary to assumption.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.9}", "question": "Show that the ideals $(x+\\zeta^{i}y)$ are perfect $l$th powers.", "solution": "Since the ideals $(x+\\zeta^{i}y)$, $1\\le i\\le l-1$, are mutually coprime, and their product is an $l$th power, each ideal must be an $l$th power (see Exercise 5.3.12).", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.10a}", "question": "Consider the element $\\alpha=(x+y)^{l-2}(x+\\zeta y)$. Show that the ideal $(\\alpha)$ is a perfect $l$th power.", "solution": "(a) is immediate from the previous exercise.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.10b}", "question": "Consider the element $\\alpha=(x+y)^{l-2}(x+\\zeta y)$. Show that $\\alpha\\equiv1-u\\lambda \\pmod{\\lambda^{2}}$ where $u=(x+y)^{l-2}y$.", "solution": "To prove (b), observe that $x+\\zeta y=x+y-\\lambda y$. Thus $\\alpha=(x+y)^{l-1}-\\lambda y(x+y)^{l-2}=(x+y)^{l-1}-\\lambda u.$ Now $x^{l}+y^{l}+z^{l}\\equiv x+y+z \\pmod l$, by Fermat's little Theorem. If $l|(x+y)$, then $l|z$, contrary to assumption. Therefore $(x+y)^{l-1}\\equiv1 \\pmod l$ since $l \\nmid (x+y)$. Since $(l)=(\\lambda)^{l-1}$ we find $\\alpha\\equiv1-u\\lambda \\pmod{\\lambda^{2}}$ which gives (b).", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.11}", "question": "Show that $\\zeta^{-u}\\alpha$ is primary.", "solution": "We have $\\zeta^{-u}\\alpha=(1-\\lambda)^{-u}\\alpha\\equiv(1+u\\lambda)(1-u\\lambda) \\pmod{\\lambda^{2}}$ so that $\\zeta^{-u}\\alpha\\equiv1 \\pmod{\\lambda^{2}}$. Hence, $\\zeta^{-u}\\alpha$ is primary.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.12}", "question": "Use Eisenstein reciprocity to show that if $x^{l}+y^{l}+z^{l}=0$ has a solution in integers, $l \\nmid xyz$, then for any $p|y$, $(\\zeta/p)_{l}^{-u}=1$ (Hint: Evaluate $(p/\\zeta^{-u}\\alpha)_{l}$)", "solution": "By Exercise 9.2.11, $\\zeta^{-u}\\alpha$ is primary so by Eisenstein reciprocity, $(\\frac{p}{\\zeta^{-u}\\alpha})_{l}=(\\frac{\\zeta^{-u}\\alpha}{p})_{l}=(\\frac{\\zeta}{p})_{l}^{-u}(\\frac{\\alpha}{p})_{l}$. Now $(\\zeta^{-u}\\alpha)=(\\alpha)$ is an $l$th power by Exercise 9.2.10 (a). So the left-hand side of the above equation is 1. To evaluate $(\\alpha/p)_{l}$, note that $\\alpha\\equiv(x+y)^{l-1} \\pmod p$ since $p|y$. Thus, since $p$ is primary, $(\\frac{\\alpha}{p})_{l}=(\\frac{(x+y)^{l-1}}{p})_{l}=(\\frac{p}{(x+y)^{l-1}})_{l}$ : again by Eisenstein reciprocity. By Exercise 9.2.9, $(x+y)$ is an $l$th power of an ideal so that $(\\alpha/p)_{l}=1$ Therefore $(\\zeta/p)_{l}^{-u}=1$ for every $p|y$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.13}", "question": "Show that if $x^{l}+y^{l}+z^{l}=0$ has a solution in integers, $l \\nmid xyz$ then for any $p|xyz$, $(\\zeta/p)_{l}^{-u}=1$.", "solution": "We proved this for $p|y$ in the previous exercise. Since the equation is symmetric in $x, y, z$ the same applies for $p|x$ or $p|z$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.14}", "question": "Show that $(\\zeta/p)_{l}^{-u}=1$ implies that $p^{l-1}\\equiv1 \\pmod{l^2}$.", "solution": "Let us factor $(p)=\\wp_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\wp_{g}$ as a product of prime ideals. We know that $N(\\wp_{i})=p^{f}$ and that $gf=l-1$. Thus, by Exercises 9.2.4 and 9.2.5, $(\\frac{\\zeta}{p})_{l}=\\prod_{i=1}^{g}(\\frac{\\zeta}{\\wp_{i}})_{l}=\\prod_{i=1}^{g}\\zeta^{(N(\\wp_{i})-1)/l}=\\zeta^{g(p^{f}-1)/l}.$ Since $(\\zeta/p)_{l}^{u}=1$, we have $ug\\frac{p^f-1}{l} \\equiv 0 \\pmod l$. Moreover, $(g,l)=1, (u,l)=1$, so that $p^{f}\\equiv1 \\pmod{l^2}$. Since $f|l-1,$ we deduce that $p^{l-1}\\equiv1 \\pmod{l^2}$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.2.15}", "question": "If $l$ is an odd prime and $x^{l}+y^{l}+z^{l}=0$ for some integers $x, y, z$ coprime to $l$, then show that $p^{l-1}\\equiv1 \\pmod{l^2}$ for every $p|xyz$. Deduce that $2^{l-1}\\equiv1 \\pmod{l^2}$.", "solution": "By Exercise 9.2.14, the first assertion is immediate. For the second part, observe that at least one of $x, y, z$ must be even.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.3.1}", "question": "Show that there are infinitely many primes $p$ such that $(2/p)=-1$.", "solution": "We know that $(2/p)=-1$ if and only if $p\\equiv\\pm3$ (mod 8). Suppose there are only finitely many such primes $q_{1},...,q_{k}$ (say) excluding 3. Consider the number $b=8q_{1}q_{2}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot q_{k}+3$. By construction $b$ is not divisible by any $q_{i}$. Moreover, $b\\equiv3$ (mod 8) so that $(2/b)=-1$. Let $b=p_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{m}$ be the prime decomposition of $b$ with $p_{i}$ not necessarily distinct. Since $-1=(\\frac{2}{b})=\\prod_{i=1}^{m}(\\frac{2}{p_{i}})$ we must have $(2/p_{i})=-1$ for some $i$. Since $p_{i}$ is distinct from $q_{1},...,q_{k},$ this is a contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.3.2}", "question": "Let $a$ be a nonsquare integer greater than 1. Show that there are infinitely many primes $p$ such that $(a/p)=-1$.", "solution": "Without loss of generality, we may suppose $a$ is squarefree and greater than 2 by the previous exercise. Suppose there are only finitely many primes $q_{1},...,q_{k}$, (say) such that $(a/q_{i})=-1$. (This set could possibly be empty.) Write $a=2^{e}r_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot r_{m}$ for the prime factorization of $a$ with $e=0$ or 1 and $r_{i}$ odd and distinct. By the Chinese Remainder Theorem, we can find a solution to the simultaneous congruences $x \\equiv 1 \\pmod{q_i}$, $1\\le i\\le k$, $x\\equiv1 \\pmod 8$, $x\\equiv 1 \\pmod{r_{i}}$, $1\\le i\\le m-1,$ $x \\equiv c \\pmod{r_{m}}$, with $c$ any nonresidue mod $r_{m}$. (It is here that we are assuming $a$ has at least one odd prime divisor.) Let $b$ be a solution greater than 1 and write $b=p_{1}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot p_{t}$ as its prime decomposition with $p_{i}$ not necessarily distinct. Since $b\\equiv1$ (mod 8), $(2/b)=1$ Also, by the quadratic reciprocity law for the Jacobi symbol, $(r_{i}/b)=(b/r_{i})$. Thus $(\\frac{a}{b})=(\\frac{2}{b})^{e}\\prod_{i=1}^{m}(\\frac{r_{i}}{b})=(\\frac{c}{r_{m}})=-1.$ Also, $(\\frac{a}{b})=\\prod_{i=1}^{t}(\\frac{a}{p_{i}})$. Therefore, $(a/p_{i})=-1$ for some $p_{i}$. Moreover, $p_{i}|b$ and $b$ is coprime to $q_{1},...,q_{k}$ by construction. This is a contradiction.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.3.3}", "question": "Suppose that $x^{2}\\equiv a \\pmod p$ has a solution for all but finitely many primes. Show that $a$ is a perfect square.", "solution": "Write $a=b^{2}c$ with $c$ squarefree. Then $(c/p)=1$ for all but finitely many primes. By the previous exercise, this is not possible if $c>1$. Thus, $c=1$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.3.4}", "question": "Let $K$ be a quadratic extension of $\\mathbb{Q}$. Show that there are infinitely many primes which do not split completely in $K$.", "solution": "Let $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\sqrt{D})$, with $D$ squarefree and greater than 1. By the previous question, there are infinitely many primes $p$ such that $x^{2}\\equiv D \\pmod p$ has no solution. Hence $(D/p)=-1$ By the theory of the Kronecker symbol, we deduce that $p$ does not split in $K$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.3.5}", "question": "Suppose that $a$ is an integer coprime to the odd prime $q$. If $x^{q}\\equiv a \\pmod p$ has a solution for all but finitely many primes, show that $a$ is a perfect $q$th power.", "solution": "We must show that if $a$ is not a $q$th power, then there are infinitely many primes $p$ such that $x^{q}\\equiv a \\pmod p$ has no solution. We will work in the field $K=\\mathbb{Q}(\\zeta_{q})$. Write $(a)=\\wp_{1}^{e_{1}}\\cdot\\cdot\\cdot\\wp_{n}^{e_{n}}$, where the $\\wp_i$ are distinct prime ideals of $\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$. We claim that $q \\nmid e_{i}$ for some $i$. To see this, let $p_{i}=\\wp_{i}\\cap\\mathbb{Z}$ Since $(q,a)=1$ we have $q\\ne p_{i}$ for any $i$, so each $p_{i}$ is unramified in $\\mathcal{O}_{K}$. Thus $ord_{p_{i}}a=ord_{\\wp_{i}}(a)=e_{i}$. If $q|e_{i}$ for all $i$, then $a$ would be a $q$th power. So we may suppose $q \\nmid e_{n}$. Now let $\\mathfrak{q}_{1},...,\\mathfrak{q}_{k}$ be a finite set of prime ideals different from $\\wp_{1},...,\\wp_{n}$ and $(1-\\zeta_{q})$. By the Chinese Remainder Theorem (Exercise 5.3.13), we can find an $x\\in\\mathfrak{O}_{K}$ satisfying the simultaneous congruences $x\\equiv1 \\pmod{\\mathfrak{q}_i}$, $1\\le i\\le k$, $x\\equiv 1 \\pmod q,$ $x\\equiv 1 \\pmod{\\wp_{j}},$ $1\\le j\\le n-1$, $x\\equiv c \\pmod{\\wp_{n}}$, where $c$ is chosen so that $(c/\\wp_{n})=\\zeta_{q}$. Let $b$ be a solution greater than 1. Then $b\\equiv1$ (mod $q$) and hence is primary. Hence $(\\frac{a}{b})_{q}=(\\frac{b}{a})_{q} = \\prod_{i=1}^{n}(\\frac{b}{\\wp_{i}})_{q}^{e_{i}}=\\zeta_{q}^{e_{n}}\\ne1,$ by the Eisenstein reciprocity law. Now $(\\frac{a}{b})_{q}\\ne1$ since $q \\nmid e_{n}$ On the other hand, factoring $b$ into a product of prime ideals and using the multiplicativity of the $q$th power residue symbol, we deduce that $(\\frac{a}{\\wp})_{q}\\ne1$ for some prime ideal $\\wp$ dividing $b$. Hence $x^{q}\\equiv a \\pmod \\wp$ has no solution. Since $b$ is coprime to the given set $\\mathfrak{q}_{1},...,\\mathfrak{q}_{k}$ of prime ideals (possibly empty), we can produce inductively infinitely many prime ideals $\\wp$ such that $x^{q}\\equiv a \\pmod \\wp$ has no solution. A fortiori, there are infinitely many primes $p$ such that $x^{q}\\equiv a \\pmod p$ has no solution.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
{"label": "\\label{ques: Exercise 9.3.8}", "question": "Show that the equation $x^{3}-2y^{3}=23z^{m}$ has no integer solutions with $gcd(x,y,z)=1$.", "solution": "Reduce the equation mod 23 to find $x^{3}\\equiv2y^{3}$ (mod 23). If $23 \\nmid y$, 2 is a cubic residue (mod 23). By the previous exercise, we can write $23=C^{2}+27D^{2}$ which is not possible. If $23 | y$, then $23 | x$ and then $23 | gcd(x,y,z)$.", "source": "ProblemsInANT"}
